Charon: Charon here. You're listening to State of Play, episode twenty, recorded eighteenth of May, twenty-twenty-six, from Port Pirie. This is our first episode on the new audio pipeline — joint-stereo, properly mastered to broadcast loudness, a music bed under the sign-off, transcripts shipped alongside the audio. The sound floor moved up a couple of rungs. If something feels different in your ears, that's the joint-stereo at minus sixteen LUFS landing in your podcast app. Cast tonight — Charon as anchor, then Kore, Vindemiatrix, Rasalgethi, and Achernar. We're running about fifty minutes today because the topic warrants it. The topic is ColPali, and the broader family of whole-page document embeddings. Here's the question I want you holding in your head for the next fifty minutes — what if your search index could see the page? Not extract text from it, not OCR it into a flat string and embed the string. See it. With patches. With layout. With the bar chart in the corner and the handwritten margin note and the table that nobody ever quite parses correctly. That's the shift. We'll cover the science, we'll cover six concrete applications in my own work, we'll cover the cross-topic synergies, and we'll spend time on something nobody in the published literature has properly named yet — the new biometric risk surface that whole-page embeddings open up, and what that means for Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander data sovereignty. Kore, take it from the top.
Kore: Kore here. So the starting point is the problem that nobody has admitted is unsolved for thirty years. Documents are not text. Documents are pages. A clinical guideline has tables. A research paper has figures. A textbook has callouts and margin diagrams. An EFTPOS receipt has a logo and a printed total and a handwritten tip line. The standard retrieval pipeline pretends none of that exists. You run OCR over the page, you get a flat string, you embed the string with something like BGE or E5 or text-embedding-three-large, you do nearest-neighbour search. Everything that wasn't text on that page — gone. Every layout cue — gone. Every figure — gone. The bar chart that proves the point — gone. And the OCR itself loses one to five percent of characters even on clean pages and considerably more on anything that's been scanned, photographed, faxed, or annotated. ColPali, published in July twenty-twenty-four by Manuel Faysse and a team out of Illuin Technology and CentraleSupélec, took the obvious-in-hindsight position[1]. Don't OCR the page. Don't even describe the page. Just embed the page. As a picture.
Charon: Charon — and the architecture matters because it explains why this is different from the previous attempt at this. CLIP could embed an image. So could SigLIP. So could every multimodal model since twenty-twenty-one. What's the trick?
Kore: The trick is that ColPali doesn't pool. The starting model is PaliGemma three-B — Google's three-billion-parameter vision-language model. PaliGemma takes a four-forty-eight by four-forty-eight page image, splits it into a thirty-two by thirty-two grid of patches — that's one thousand and twenty-four patches per page — runs each patch through a SigLIP vision encoder, and then runs the whole sequence through a Gemma-two-B language model. The conventional move, the one CLIP makes, the one DSE makes, the one Cohere Embed-v-four makes — you pool those one thousand patch hidden states into a single dense vector. You collapse the page into one number-per-dimension summary. ColPali refuses to pool. ColPali keeps every patch vector — about one thousand and thirty vectors including a few trailing instruction tokens — and projects each one down to a hundred and twenty-eight dimensions through a single linear layer[1][4]. So a single page becomes one thousand and thirty separate one-hundred-and-twenty-eight-dim vectors. Stored as bfloat16, that's about two hundred and fifty-eight kilobytes of vector per page.
Achernar: This is Achernar. Two hundred and fifty-eight kilobytes per page sounds like a lot. For a hundred thousand pages, that's twenty-six gigabytes of index. That's the trade-off everyone wrings their hands about. We'll come back to the storage math in a few segments. The retrieval side is the other half of the trick.
Kore: Right — late interaction. The scoring operator is what's called MaxSim, inherited from ColBERT, Omar Khattab's two-thousand-twenty paper out of Stanford[7]. For every query token, compute cosine similarity against every patch vector on every page. Take the maximum — so each query token effectively lights up its single best-matching patch. Then sum the per-token maxima to give the page score. So if your query is "what's the bar chart showing quarter three revenue?" — the query token for bar chart finds the visual patches representing a bar chart shape. The token for Q3 finds the legend label. The token for revenue finds the axis title. The MaxSim sums those three signals. A bi-encoder that pools cannot do this because the page-summary vector has to be averaged in a way that smears out fine-grained signal. The late-interaction operator preserves it. Faysse and the team reported an average NDCG-at-five of eighty-one point three on the ViDoRe benchmark when ColPali launched — about sixteen points ahead of the strongest OCR-based pipeline they tested[1][9].
Charon: Charon. And then the family tree exploded. Tell us the descendants.
Kore: Within four months of the ColPali release, the same recipe was being applied to every vision-language backbone with weights out in public. The headline successor is ColQwen2, swapping PaliGemma-three-B for Qwen2-VL-two-B from Alibaba[13][14]. Same architecture, much better backbone, fully Apache-two-licensed. ColQwen2 ships a plus-five-NDCG improvement over ColPali on ViDoRe-v-one — pushing average scores into the high eighties. ColQwen2-point-five-V-L came in twenty-twenty-five, a further improvement. ColSmol, in two sizes, two-hundred-and-fifty-six-million parameters and five-hundred-million parameters, built on HuggingFace's SmolVLM — that's the run-on-a-laptop variant[15][16]. ColFlor, by Ahmed Masry, only one-hundred-and-seventy-four million parameters built on Microsoft's Florence-two — seventeen times smaller than ColPali, nine-point-eight times faster query encoding, five-point-two-five times faster image encoding, and only one-point-eight percentage points behind on English text-rich documents[18][19]. ColIdefics, ColInternVL, ColSmolVLM-base — a whole genus.
Achernar: Achernar — and the small-end story is the one that matters for our deployment context. Most of what Jacob runs sits on a single M-series Mac. A three-billion-parameter model will encode pages at maybe one to three pages per second on that hardware. ColFlor at one-hundred-and-seventy-four million parameters indexes at about ten pages per second on the same machine. For a working clinician's vault of a few thousand pages, that's tens of seconds, not hours. The smaller models also fit comfortably in eight gigabytes of RAM with room to spare for the LLM that'll generate the answer.
Charon: Charon — and the benchmark these all live on is ViDoRe. Achernar, talk us through the bar that ColPali had to clear.
Achernar: Achernar. ViDoRe — Visual Document Retrieval Benchmark. Three versions now. ViDoRe-v-one was published alongside ColPali in July twenty-twenty-four. Ten subtasks — ArxivQA on English academic figures, DocVQA, InfographicVQA, TabFQuAD on French formal tables, TATDQA on tables and text, and five synthetic subsets covering shifts, energy, government, healthcare, and AI[1][20]. Metric is NDCG-at-five. ColPali launched at eighty-one. The leaderboard is now north of ninety — several v-one subsets are effectively saturated. ViDoRe-v-two landed in April twenty-twenty-five and raised the bar — blind contextual queries, written without sight of the gold page so they can't be lexically copied; long and cross-document queries; multilingual extension to French, German, Spanish, Italian, English[21]. The current top systems on v-two sit around sixty-five to seventy NDCG-at-five. Then in early twenty-twenty-six, Antoine Edy and a team co-built with NVIDIA released ViDoRe-v-three[22][23] — ten professional domains, twenty-six thousand page images, three thousand queries in six languages, evaluating not just retrieval but visual grounding with bounding boxes and end-to-end answer generation against human-reviewed truth. The headline result on v-three — even the best late-interaction models score under sixty-five percent NDCG-at-ten. Multi-hop, open-ended, and non-textual queries are the worst categories. So when you hear me say throughout this episode that ColPali is good but not solved, that's the citation. The live leaderboard for all three versions sits at huggingface-dot-co-slash-spaces-slash-vidore-slash-vidore-leaderboard[24].
Vindemiatrix: Vindemiatrix here — and the single-vector alternative, the one that does pool, is worth naming because it's the right answer for some workloads. Tell us about DSE.
Kore: Kore. DSE — Document Screenshot Embedding — by Xueguang Ma, Sheng-Chieh Lin, Minghan Li, Wenhu Chen, and Jimmy Lin out of Waterloo and Vespa, EMNLP twenty-twenty-four[26][27]. DSE pre-dates ColPali by about a month and offers an explicit different design choice. One vector per page. No late interaction. The document tower is a vision-language model — Phi-three-vision in their paper, with a larger eight-billion-parameter variant. The query tower is the same model in text mode. Both produce a single thousand-to-two-thousand-dim dense vector. Scoring is plain cosine. Storage per page is one vector, about four kilobytes. Versus ColPali's two-fifty-eight kilobytes. So sixty-four times less storage. When does DSE win? When you have huge corpora — billions of pages, where multi-vector storage is genuinely impossible. When latency matters more than the last five NDCG points. And when documents are predominantly text-on-page rather than figure-heavy. On Ma et al.'s own evaluation DSE beats BM25 by seventeen NDCG-at-one points on slide-screenshot retrieval and beats OCR-plus-text-retrieval by fifteen-plus NDCG-at-ten[26]. When does ColPali win? On figure-heavy and table-heavy queries, ColPali is consistently five to ten NDCG points ahead. Multi-vector late interaction lets specific tokens like "bar chart" or "p less than zero-point-zero-five" hit specific patches. Pooling collapses that signal[28]. The pragmatic production pattern people are converging on is DSE first, ColPali rerank — coarse-retrieve top-two-hundred with single-vector DSE, then re-score those two hundred with full MaxSim against the multi-vector ColPali index. You get most of the storage win of DSE and most of the accuracy win of ColPali[29].
Charon: Charon — and there's a whole pipeline genre built around this, called VisRAG. One sentence each.
Achernar: Achernar — VisRAG, Shi Yu and team at Tsinghua and OpenBMB, October twenty-twenty-four, accepted to ICLR twenty-twenty-five[30][32]. Pipeline — render every PDF page as an image, embed pages with their VLM retriever VisRet, retrieve top-k pages, feed the retrieved page images directly into a VLM generator like MiniCPM-V or GPT-four-V, generate the answer. Twenty to forty percent better than text-OCR-RAG on multi-modality QA, biggest gains where layout matters. ColPali is the retriever; VisRAG is the recipe for what to put around it.
Vindemiatrix: Vindemiatrix — and the agentic extension is ViDoRAG by Wang and team, February twenty-twenty-five[33] — dynamic iterative reasoning agents on top of visual retrieval. Then VISA, by Xueguang Ma's group again, December twenty-twenty-four[34] — adds visual source attribution, bounding boxes around the evidence on the retrieved page. So you don't just get an answer, you get a highlighted region. Critical for clinical use because anything that gets used in patient care needs traceability back to source. And there's Lost in OCR Translation, Faysse and team again, May twenty-twenty-five[35] — empirical study that quantifies exactly where text-OCR-RAG loses ground to vision retrieval.
Charon: Charon — that's the literature scaffold. Now we're going to spend the bulk of this episode walking through what this means for six specific things I'm building or about to build. POCUS, tax receipts, Vault navigation, the mixed-media RAG stack, the Sepsis Poster Studio, and the PICC business case. Five segments, because Vault navigation and the mixed-media RAG stack are the same architecture and we'll do them together. Rasalgethi — kick us off with POCUS.
Rasalgethi: Rasalgethi here. Right — so for listeners who aren't in clinical land, POCUS is point-of-care ultrasound. Cardiac, lung, abdomen, vascular, obstetric. You hold a probe on a patient at the bedside, you see what's underneath. The image quality is, charitably, sometimes appalling. Compared to formal radiology it's a fingerpainting. But the timeliness is unbeatable. If a patient deteriorates at three a.m. in a regional emergency department, you don't have a sonographer. You have you, a probe, and your training. Jacob has been building a POCUS learning resource — a personal teaching library — for the last six months. The current state is a folder structure on the laptop with hundreds of saved still frames and short clips, labelled by their suspected pathology — pericardial effusion, RV strain, pleural effusion, B-lines, hepatorenal junction, EFAST views, hydronephrosis. The retrieval problem is honest. When a learner sees an unfamiliar image at the bedside, what they want to do is — find another image that looks like this one, in my library. The current solution is "scroll through folders." That doesn't scale. ColPali on POCUS images is the obvious fit.
Charon: Charon — the implementation plan. Step one, step two, step three.
Rasalgethi: Rasalgethi. Step one — render every clip and still frame to a representative thumbnail or three-frame strip. POCUS clips are typically two-to-six-second loops. For each loop, extract three keyframes — early, mid, late — and stitch them into a single image. For stills, use the image directly. Pad to four-forty-eight square. Step two — index with ColFlor, not ColPali, because at one-seventy-four million parameters it runs at ten frames per second on the M-series Mac and the index for a thousand POCUS clips comes out at about a quarter of a gigabyte. Use byaldi as the indexing wrapper — five-line Python, points at the directory, persists the index[43]. Step three — build a small front-end. Native macOS app or local web page. Search by image query — drag a new image in, get the top-k similar images from the library, with the label of each match. Optionally — search by text query — "show me cardiac four-chamber views with pericardial effusion" — same byaldi search interface, just text. Step four, validation — drop in twenty new POCUS images you've never indexed, hand-rate the top-five returned matches as relevant or not. If recall-at-five sits above seventy percent the system is useful. Below that, swap to ColQwen-two-point-five-v-zero-point-two, which is more accurate but indexes slower.
Achernar: Achernar. The failure mode you need to anticipate is low-resolution scans. POCUS images are intrinsically grainy. ColPali ingests at four-forty-eight square. ColFlor at seven-sixty-eight. If a stored still is less than that — and many will be — patches blur into illegible smudges. The mitigation is upscaling at ingest time with an OCR-grade image super-resolution model, typically Real-ESRGAN[1][35]. That's a one-time cost at indexing. It also has clinical implications — a super-resolved POCUS image is not the same image as the original. Annotate the indexed copy as such.
Vindemiatrix: Vindemiatrix — and the data-sovereignty surface here is one of the largest in the six applications we'll discuss. POCUS images are biometric-grade by virtue of containing tissue. Skin moles, distinctive surgical scars, identifying tattoos in incidental capture, fetal facial profiles, and the patient's audible voice if you've captured loops with sound. We need to come back to this in the data-sovereignty segment, but flag it now — the consent envelope for storing a POCUS clip in a patient's clinical record is not automatically the consent envelope for storing its ColPali vector representation in an indexable retrieval library.
Charon: Charon — and what does this unlock pedagogically?
Rasalgethi: Rasalgethi. Three things. First — case-based retrieval. A learner sees a patient, takes a POCUS image at three a.m., drops it into the search bar, sees five similar images from the library each tagged with the diagnosis the indexer attached to them. That's pattern-matching against experienced examples. Second — gap-finding. Run the system against a target curriculum of pathology categories, find the categories with the fewest indexed examples, target those for future image collection. Third — progression. As the learner gets better at acquiring images, the library grows in both quantity and quality. Re-index quarterly. The recall-at-five score is a single number that tracks library maturity. The published evidence base for this kind of image-retrieval-as-pedagogy approach in POCUS specifically is thin — most POCUS education research evaluates instructor-led teaching, simulator hours, or video curricula. Image retrieval as a learning prosthesis is genuinely novel. Worth a small case-series write-up if the system gets used.
Charon: Charon — application two. Tax receipts. Why does this matter? Because Jacob currently uses Claude vision via the Anthropic Files API to extract text from photographed receipts, push it into a structured-output JSON schema, classify them by ATO category, file them. It works. But there's a question — is the OCR-then-text pipeline doing more work than it needs to, on receipts that are intrinsically visual? Rasalgethi.
Rasalgethi: Rasalgethi. Yes — and this is the cleanest contrast between the OCR-then-text approach and a ColPali-style approach, because receipts are exactly the documents OCR struggles with. EFTPOS slips have a logo at the top, a date in printed text in the middle, a list of line items in a small font, sometimes a handwritten tip line, sometimes a Visa-card sticker on top, sometimes a folded crease through the total. The text-OCR pipeline misreads dollar signs as letter-S, confuses zero with capital-O, hallucinates whole line items if the contrast is low. Claude vision is good at correcting these — it's a frontier multimodal model with reasoning — but it costs a non-trivial number of input tokens per receipt, and the latency is two to four seconds per call. For a thousand receipts a year, that's manageable. For ten thousand, it's not.
Achernar: Achernar — and here's the surprise. For receipts specifically, DSE may actually win, not ColPali. Receipts are predominantly text on a page. The figure-and-table advantage that ColPali enjoys doesn't apply. A single-vector model can pool the page representation tightly enough to give you back the "Coles, twenty-third of March, sixty-eight dollars eighty" signal. The argument for ColPali on receipts is the handwritten tip line — and the folded crease. The argument against it is the storage. For tax receipts you don't want a multi-vector index per receipt — you want a single dense vector that goes into a relational database alongside the structured fields Claude vision extracted. So the architecture probably becomes — single-vector visual embedding alongside extracted text fields, not "ColPali replaces Claude vision."
Rasalgethi: Rasalgethi — the implementation plan. Step one — image embed each receipt with a single-vector model at ingest time. Options — Cohere Embed-v-four if we're willing to send receipts to a closed API, Voyage multimodal-three if MongoDB is involved, or open-source — DSE with Phi-three-vision running locally[26]. Pick the local one. Step two — store the single-vector embedding alongside the existing Claude-extracted fields. Schema is `receiptid, vector, vendor, date, amount, category, rawimagepath, claudeextraction_json`. Step three — for visual deduplication — when a new receipt comes in, embed it, run a cosine search against the existing index, flag the top-three closest matches as potential duplicates. Receipts get photographed twice all the time — once from the wallet, once when filing. Visual dedup catches the cases where the OCR'd amount might differ by a digit-pair but the visual is identical. Step four — for categorisation review — at year-end, embed all receipts in a category cluster, sort by distance from the centroid, surface the outliers as "are these really Office Supplies?" Step five — validation — sample two-hundred receipts hand-classified by ATO category, run the full pipeline, measure F-one against the gold labels. Compare before and after the visual-dedup pass. The win you're hunting is minutes saved per year of audit-trail prep and false-positive duplicates caught.
Charon: Charon — and what's the ColPali-shaped contribution if we go DSE for the core?
Rasalgethi: Rasalgethi. Two niche features. One — handwritten tip-line extraction. Train a small ColPali-style late-interaction model on receipts specifically, query token for tip finds the patch with handwritten ink, MaxSim gives a confidence score. That's a research project, not a production move. Two — receipt-genre classification at the visual level. EFTPOS slip versus full tax invoice versus restaurant printout versus online receipt PDF. The visual signature is so different per genre that even a small late-interaction model picks it up in a few hundred examples. The classifier output feeds the existing Claude-extraction prompt — "this is an EFTPOS slip, extract these four fields" instead of a one-size-fits-all extraction prompt — which improves Claude's accuracy by a few percent. Modest but real.
Vindemiatrix: Vindemiatrix — and the data-sovereignty edge here is much lower than POCUS, but it's not zero. Receipts have your name, sometimes your card number digits, sometimes your home address. The pipeline already runs locally. Don't push receipts to a hosted vector DB. Local Qdrant or local SQLite-vec. The index goes in your encrypted home directory.
Charon: Charon — and we're combining these because they share an architecture. The Obsidian vault and the broader mixed-media RAG stack. Kore.
Kore: Kore. The Obsidian vault is the working knowledge base. Five thousand or so markdown files now, with embedded figures, callouts, tables, the Netter illustrations Jacob's been generating, plots from the Sepsis CARE work, screenshots, photos, hand-drawn diagrams from the original ACRRM-RACMA fellowship planning notes. Obsidian's built-in search is text-only. It searches the raw markdown. It doesn't see the rendered page. So if a note has a beautifully-laid-out comparison table generated by a callout block, the search index sees `| header | header |` not the visual layout. If a note has an embedded figure from Sepsis CARE showing the rural-versus-metropolitan sepsis mortality gap, the search index sees `![figure](path/sepsis-rural-metro.png)` — it doesn't see the bars. So the retrieval-by-visual-content problem is real. You can't find your own note by remembering "the one with the orange callout and the table comparing three things" — but a ColPali-style retriever, given a rendered version of the note, could.
Charon: Charon. The implementation plan.
Kore: Kore. Step one — render every Obsidian note to a PDF or a long PNG. Obsidian has a built-in "export to PDF" — wire it into a script that walks the vault directory and re-renders any changed note. Hash the markdown source, only re-render on change. Build a `~/Vault-rendered/` shadow directory. Step two — index that shadow directory with ColQwen2-v-one-point-zero through byaldi[43]. Five thousand pages takes maybe forty minutes on the M-series Mac at three pages per second. The float-sixteen index lands at about one-point-three gigabytes; binary-quantised through Vespa or Qdrant brings it under one hundred megabytes[37]. Step three — wire it as an Obsidian plugin or a small command-line tool. Two query modes — text query, "the note about ColPali with the table of family members," returns top-five matches with thumbnails and wikilinks. Image query, drag-drop a rendered figure or a screenshot, returns top-five visually similar notes. Step four — recall validation. Pick fifty notes you remember by their visual features. Query for each. Measure how many appear in the top-five. Target above eighty percent. Step five — keep the existing Obsidian text search alive in parallel — text and ColPali become two complementary indices, surfaced side-by-side in the UI.
Rasalgethi: Rasalgethi — and the mixed-media RAG stack is the related project Jacob has been thinking about for some weeks. It's the broader question — how do you build a research RAG system that retrieves equally well over text notes, PDF papers, embedded figures, screenshot snippets, and photos? The previous task brief sketched it. ColPali is the canonical opening move because it is the layer that doesn't lose information when content crosses modalities. The architecture is — single ColQwen-two index over everything renderable to an image. Plus the existing Zotero / PubMed text-retrieval pathways via the Zotero MCP and PubMed MCP. Plus a hybrid scorer that combines BM25, dense text retrieval, and ColPali MaxSim. Plus a re-ranker. Plus a generator — Claude or Gemini or a local Qwen-two-V-L if everything stays on-prem. The whole stack is, roughly — render, embed, retrieve, re-rank, generate. Each component is open-source. The Vespa team has a complete reference implementation called Visual RAG over PDFs with Vespa[39].
Achernar: Achernar — and the storage math for the mixed-media RAG stack. Vault — five thousand pages — one-point-three gigabytes at full bfloat16 ColQwen2, or eighty megabytes binary-quantised. Zotero — three-thousand-nine-hundred items, of which maybe a thousand have figure-heavy PDFs averaging twenty pages — call it twenty thousand pages — that's about five gigabytes bfloat16, three hundred megabytes binary. Sepsis Poster Studio source images, POCUS library, all the rest — under one gigabyte. So the whole working corpus, in binary-quantised ColQwen2 form, fits comfortably under half a gigabyte. On a USB stick. The bigger storage cost is the image cache of the rendered pages themselves, not the vectors. That's a real point — the vectors are smaller than the documents they index.
Vindemiatrix: Vindemiatrix — and the cross-modal angle of mixed-media RAG is worth flagging. ColPali is single-modal at retrieval time — it embeds a page image, query is text or another image. But because the query encoder is also the VLM, you can pass either modality. So a figure from one paper can retrieve similar figures from other papers. That's research workflow gold. Find me the four other clinical trials whose forest plot looks like this one. The published literature on this kind of cross-modal academic retrieval is moving fast — VISA's Paper-VISA dataset is the closest published medical-domain example[34].
Rasalgethi: Rasalgethi — the implementation plan for the mixed-media RAG stack, step by step. Step one — adopt byaldi as the prototype layer. Five lines of Python, indexes a directory, persists, searches. Run it over the Vault-rendered shadow plus the Zotero PDF cache. Validate on twenty hand-curated queries. Step two — once byaldi proves the recall, migrate the index to a Qdrant container running on Alien for persistent multi-user access. Qdrant has native multi-vector with MaxSim built in[40][41]. Step three — implement the binary-quantisation phased-retrieval pattern from Bergum's September twenty-twenty-four Vespa post[37]. Binary-MaxSim over the whole corpus to get top-two-hundred, then float-MaxSim on the two hundred. Step four — wire the retriever into the existing OpenClaw federation. Add a tool definition so Ada can call the retriever directly. Step five — build the generator pathway with whichever LLM is in the model chain at the time — Claude Opus, Gemini three-point-one Pro, or local Qwen-two-V-L on Alien. Step six — track retrieval quality with a tiny per-query feedback loop. Was the top result useful, yes or no, dropdown. Trains nothing automatically; gives Jacob a metric trend to watch.
Charon: Charon — application five. The Sepsis Poster Studio. This is the project where Jacob and Marie Curie Ross have been generating community-facing posters for Sepsis CARE twenty-twenty-six. The studio produces a deliberately consistent visual style — palette, illustration register, typography. Achernar.
Achernar: Achernar. The retrieval problem for the studio is iterative. You're building a poster series. You've made fifty posters across six themes over six months. You want to ask — show me the previous posters where I used a similar two-column treatment with a hero image at the top. Or show me the colour treatment from the version I made for the May-twentieth community engagement event. Or — more usefully — find the posters where the visual hierarchy worked and use them as exemplars for the new series. The current solution is a folder of dated PNG outputs. The retrieval is brain. ColPali — or really ColFlor at one-hundred-and-seventy-four million parameters — solves this with comfortably under a hundred megabytes of index for hundreds of posters[18].
Rasalgethi: Rasalgethi — implementation plan. Step one — every poster output from the studio gets indexed at write-time. The studio pipeline already writes a thumbnail PNG of each draft and final. Hook a post-write task that updates the local byaldi index. Step two — extend the studio TUI or CLI with two retrieval commands. Find similar — for the current draft, return the five most visually similar previous posters. Find by reference — given a text description, return matching posters. Step three — for the exemplar use case, allow the user to tag posters with quality labels — "good hierarchy", "muddled hierarchy", "good colour balance", "tonally off." Filter retrieval results by these tags. The studio learns its own taste over time. Step four — validation — at the end of a six-month poster cycle, run a small audit. Compare the labels you actually applied to the labels the system would predict (using a small classifier trained on the labelled subset). Measure F-one. If the classifier is north of zero-point-eight you've got a passive quality-rating loop running.
Charon: Charon — and the design-iteration angle.
Achernar: Achernar — the deeper move is to use ColPali as a similarity space for design-iteration tracking. You're trying to evolve a series of posters along a consistent visual axis. Project every poster into the ColPali multi-vector space. Pool to a single per-poster vector using mean-pooling for compactness, only for this analysis. Run UMAP or t-SNE down to two dimensions. Plot the trajectory of your posters through that space over time. If your series is genuinely evolving along a consistent visual axis, the trajectory will trace a curve. If you're drifting, the trajectory will scatter. It's a diagnostic tool for series-level visual consistency. Tufte-adjacent thinking — show the design process, not just the design.
Vindemiatrix: Vindemiatrix — and there's a subtle data-sovereignty edge here too. The posters are community-facing, generated for Sepsis CARE work that touches Aboriginal community-controlled health organisations. If any draft poster includes imagery of community members, or uses cultural elements, the vectors that index those posters are also indexed records of those cultural elements. The CARE principles' Authority to Control clause applies to derived data, not just source data[78][79]. Build the deletion pathway in early — every poster can be removed from the index, not just from the folder. Vector databases don't always make per-document deletion easy; Qdrant does, Vespa does, but check before committing to a vendor.
Charon: Charon — application six. PICC. Peripherally inserted central catheters. Jacob and a colleague at PPRHS have been drafting a business case to bring PICC insertion in-house at Port Pirie, which currently means transferring patients to Adelaide for the line and then transferring them back. The clinical evidence base is large, scattered across journals, and full of figures — Kaplan-Meier curves of catheter-related bloodstream infection over time, forest plots of complication rates, decision-flow diagrams, ward-process flowcharts. The retrieval problem — Vindemiatrix.
Vindemiatrix: Vindemiatrix. The business case is built on evidence. The evidence is in PDFs. The PDFs have figures. When you build a business case, you need to surface the figure — not paraphrase it from extracted text — because a senior-clinician reviewer or a health-network executive will reasonably ask what does the curve actually show. Text retrieval over OCR'd PDFs misses figures entirely. ColPali doesn't. ColPali ingests the page as a picture, sees the curve, can retrieve the page when the query is Kaplan-Meier curve of CLABSI after introduction of PICC team because the text Kaplan-Meier lands on the patches representing the curve shape, and the text PICC team lands on the patches representing the legend.
Rasalgethi: Rasalgethi — implementation. Step one — Zotero MCP push. The relevant PICC evidence is already curated in one of Jacob's eight Zotero libraries. Pull the attached PDFs into a working directory. About fifty papers, average twelve pages — six hundred pages. Step two — index with ColQwen2-v-one-point-zero through byaldi. Three minutes of indexing on the M-series Mac. Index size — under two hundred megabytes float-sixteen. Step three — for each business-case claim, query the index — "evidence that nurse-led PICC teams reduce CLABSI in rural settings," "outcome data for PICC insertion in regional Australian centres," "cost comparison of in-hospital versus transferred PICC." Retrieve the top-five pages. Pull the figures out of those pages — either as cropped images or as cited bounding boxes via VISA-style attribution[34]. Insert directly into the business case appendix with the figure's citation. Step four — for the actual claim text in the business case body, use Claude or Gemini to summarise the retrieved page, with the figure included in the prompt. The figure-aware summarisation is markedly more accurate than text-only. Step five — generate the bibliography from the Zotero metadata of the retrieved papers, automatically — every claim in the body has a corresponding figure-and-text citation.
Achernar: Achernar — and the win here is measurable. The previous round of PICC business-case drafting took roughly forty hours across two clinicians. Most of that was the figure-hunting. Find the paper with the curve, screenshot the curve, paste it in, write the caption, find the citation. Forty hours becomes — with this pipeline — maybe ten. Plus the resulting business case is more accurate because the figure citations are anchored to actual figures, not paraphrased recollections of figures. The published evidence base on AI-augmented clinical business-case drafting is essentially nil. This is publishable as a method paper if it works.
Charon: Charon — and the implementation has a hard clinical-governance interface. Vindemiatrix.
Vindemiatrix: Vindemiatrix — every figure cited in a clinical business case lives in a chain of attribution that ends with the original publisher. The retrieval system's responsibility is to ensure the citation is exact and the visual is unaltered. The risk to manage is — a paraphrased figure caption attributed to the wrong paper. Build the validation into the workflow — for every cited figure, a small accompanying widget shows original page, current rendering, citation key, DOI. Reviewer scans the widget, accepts or rejects. The reviewer is the clinician, not the AI.
Charon: Charon — segment seven. Cross-topic synergy. This is the segment that distinguishes State of Play from a research digest. The point is not just here are six applications of ColPali but here are the combinations that no single application gives you. Kore.
Kore: Kore. Synergy one — unified index across the Vault, Zotero, Sepsis Poster Studio outputs, and POCUS library. Single ColQwen-two-style late-interaction index, served from a single Qdrant or Vespa container. Cross-corpus retrieval becomes free. Find me, across everything I've ever written or read or generated, anything that looks like this page. That's a primitive that doesn't exist today and that's worth more than the sum of the six individual applications. Concrete capability — when drafting the PICC business case, the retriever surfaces not only the published evidence in Zotero but also the Vault notes Jacob wrote during the ACRRM regional placement and also the Sepsis CARE poster on rural sepsis pathways that has a relevant ward-process diagram. Three corpora, one query.
Rasalgethi: Rasalgethi — synergy two — the tax-receipt single-vector index plus the mixed-media multi-vector index, served from the same backend. Qdrant supports both single-vector and multi-vector collections in the same instance. So the receipts get one schema with DSE single-vectors; the documents and figures and clinical PDFs get another schema with ColQwen-two multi-vectors. One running service, two retrieval modalities, two interfaces. The skills are shared, the deployment is consolidated, the cost is one container.
Achernar: Achernar — synergy three — the Sepsis Poster Studio retrieval space becomes a design-quality oracle for everything else. The poster studio is the part of Jacob's work that has the most deliberate visual style. If the rest of the output is going to inherit that style — handouts, infographics, slide decks for HAC meetings — then the poster studio's tagged retrieval-space becomes a style oracle. Render a draft handout. Query the poster index — does this look like our consistent voice? Get the top-five matches. If the matches are visually coherent with the draft, you're on-style. If not, the visual cue is the diagnosis.
Vindemiatrix: Vindemiatrix — synergy four — the POCUS library and the clinical-evidence library, jointly queryable. POCUS images alongside textbook references and primary research. Show me the textbook page that explains this image. Or find the original paper whose figure looks like this clip. That's a teaching pathway that no single component of the stack delivers but the joint index does. The didactic value of moving fluently from a real patient image to the original published evidence is enormous, and it's a workflow that conventional library tools cannot support.
Charon: Charon — synergy five — the whole stack accelerates the Vault Project pattern itself. The convention now is that high-yield episode topics spawn Vault Project entries under `Work/Projects/`. Those entries have deep-dives, references, proposals, plans. The deep-dive references are PDFs in Zotero. The proposals reference Vault notes. The strategic plans reference the project file itself. Once everything is in one retriever, the Vault Project entries become discoverable by their visual structure — find every project entry I've written that has a strategic plan with thirty-sixty-ninety phasing. The Vault Project pattern becomes self-indexing. That's a meta-capability worth mentioning out loud.
Kore: Kore — synergy six — the retriever becomes a memory primitive for Ada. Ada — meaning this AI assistant, named after Lovelace and Franklin — currently operates against a markdown memory architecture. Every memory file is a text document. The current Ada-memory retrieval is keyword and YAML-tag based. If Ada's memory files are rendered and ColPali-indexed, then every memory becomes retrievable by visual layout — the memory with a table comparing options, the memory with a flagged warning callout, the memory with a status diagram. Ada's recall capacity for nuanced memories — not just text-matched memories — improves measurably. And because Ada's memory store is also Jacob's vault, that capability accrues to both.
Charon: Charon. Six synergies named. The thread under all of them is — one index, many corpora, one query interface, every modality. That's the architectural payoff.
Charon: Charon — the segment we deferred from segment two onwards. The data-sovereignty implications of whole-page embeddings, with specific attention to Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander health contexts. Vindemiatrix.
Vindemiatrix: Vindemiatrix. The framing is — whole-page embeddings preserve visual information that text-OCR pipelines discard. That's the design feature. It is also the new risk surface. ColPali keeps one thousand and thirty patch vectors per page. Each patch is roughly a fourteen-by-fourteen-pixel region of the rendered page at four-forty-eight input. A patch can contain — and the model's contextualised representation encodes — handwriting strokes, facial features in a clinical photograph, signature ink, ward whiteboard contents, name tags, stamps, fingerprints, and any other recognisable visual identifier. Unlike OCR-then-text pipelines, which discard everything except recognised characters, visual embeddings retain the visual fingerprint. That's the new fact about clinical data that the literature has not yet caught up to.
Charon: Charon — and the empirical question — can you reconstruct the original from the vectors?
Vindemiatrix: Vindemiatrix — and the answer is increasingly yes, partially. The text-embedding literature has demonstrated recovery of named entities and exact phrases from supposedly anonymous text embeddings at rates above eighty percent in zero-shot black-box settings[70][71][72]. Universal Zero-shot Embedding Inversion, arXiv twenty-five-zero-four-zero-one-four-seven, is the recent canonical citation. Face-embedding inversion is more documented still — The Hidden Dangers of Face Embeddings by IronCore Labs[73], Shielding Latent Face Representations from Privacy Attacks, arXiv twenty-five-zero-five-one-two-six-eight-eight[74], and FaceLinkGen, arXiv twenty-six-zero-two-zero-two-nine-one-four[75] — all show that protected face embeddings can be reversed to recognisable faces.
Charon: Charon — and the multimodal direct hit?
Vindemiatrix: Vindemiatrix — Beyond Text: Unveiling Privacy Vulnerabilities in Multi-modal Retrieval-Augmented Generation, arXiv twenty-five-zero-five-one-three-nine-five-seven, EMNLP twenty-twenty-five[76][77]. Direct hit. Demonstrates that multi-modal RAG systems can be made to regenerate the retrieved page images by an attacker with only query-level access. The empirical evaluation uses the IAM Handwriting dataset and ROCOv-two, a radiology image corpus. They show high recovery rates for both image content and identifying text-within-image content. So the bare statement is — a publicly accessible multimodal RAG system over identifiable clinical content is, by current literature, a measurable privacy risk.
Charon: Charon — and the Australian Indigenous-specific framing.
Vindemiatrix: Vindemiatrix — three frameworks apply. CARE Principles for Indigenous Data Governance, Stephanie Russo Carroll and an international team, Data Science Journal twenty-twenty[78][79]. Collective Benefit, Authority to Control, Responsibility, Ethics. Developed under the Research Data Alliance International Indigenous Data Sovereignty Interest Group. Maiam nayri Wingara Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander Data Sovereignty Collective, Australian, formed twenty-seventeen[80][81]. The lead Australian framework for our context. And the twenty-twenty-four NIAA Framework for Governance of Indigenous Data[82] and the twenty-twenty-four Lowitja Institute Taking Control of Our Data discussion paper[83]. Plus a twenty-twenty-four collaborative paper, Open Peer Commentary Calls for the Application of CARE Principles in AI Health Research with Indigenous Peoples[84], which directly calls for CARE in AI health contexts. None of these frameworks have yet been mapped explicitly to whole-page visual embeddings, but the principles apply. Specifically — Authority to Control applies to derived data, not just source data. A vector that encodes the visual fingerprint of an Aboriginal patient's clinical photograph is derived data under any reasonable reading of CARE.
Kore: Kore — and the practical mitigations to name explicitly on the show.
Vindemiatrix: Vindemiatrix. Six. One — de-identify before embedding. Run face detection — RetinaFace or equivalent — and handwriting detection — TrOCR layout segmentation or equivalent — over each page; mask or blur the identified regions; then embed with ColPali. Faster than the alternatives and tractable. Two — local-only deployment. The data, the model, and the index never leave the laptop or the on-premises server. Byaldi plus Qdrant plus a local Qwen-two-V-L on Alien meets this; no cloud, no third-party API. Three — encrypt embeddings at rest. Application-layer encryption of the vector index. A stolen disk image is not, then, a stolen face-and-handwriting database[70]. Four — document the consent envelope. At the level of CARE's Authority to Control and the SA Health privacy framework, consent for storing a clinical photograph in a patient's record is not automatically consent to store its derived vector representation in an indexable retrieval system. Spell this out in any institutional or community-controlled deployment. Five — refresh ability. Design the system so vectors can be deleted on request, per record, atomically. Some vector databases make per-document deletion easy — Qdrant, Vespa — others don't. Check before committing. Six — community governance. For any system that touches Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander records, CARE implies community-controlled governance of both the source data and the derived embeddings. Maiam nayri Wingara is the lead Australian framework[80].
Charon: Charon — and the published gap.
Vindemiatrix: Vindemiatrix — to my knowledge, no peer-reviewed paper has yet drawn the line from ColPali stores one thousand and thirty visual patch vectors per page to this is a new biometric risk surface under CARE and Maiam nayri Wingara principles. That's whitespace. It's a clinical-governance original-work opportunity. The Vault Project entry I'll come to in the wrap will flag it as such — for review, not as Ada-blessed go-ahead.
Charon: Charon — wrap-up. What did we cover. ColPali, the late-interaction whole-page document retriever from Faysse and team in July twenty-twenty-four[1]. The family — ColQwen2, ColQwen2.5, ColSmol, ColFlor, ColIdefics, ColInternVL[10]. The ViDoRe benchmark suite, now at version three, with even the best models scoring under sixty-five percent NDCG-at-ten[22]. DSE as the single-vector alternative[26]. VisRAG, ViDoRAG, VISA as the surrounding framework literature[30][33][34]. Vespa and Qdrant as the production hosts. Byaldi as the prototype wrapper[43]. Six concrete applications mapped to Jacob's current work — POCUS, tax receipts, Vault navigation, mixed-media RAG, Sepsis Poster Studio, PICC business case. Six cross-topic synergies — unified index, mixed single-and-multi-vector backend, style oracle, joint POCUS-and-literature, self-indexing Vault Projects, Ada-memory retrieval primitive. And the new biometric risk surface — whole-page embeddings retain visual identifiers, embedding inversion is increasingly feasible[76], and Australian Indigenous data sovereignty frameworks under CARE and Maiam nayri Wingara apply to derived embedding data, not just source data[78][80].
Kore: Kore — and the Vault Project entry, which is the durable record of all of this.
Charon: Charon. I'm spawning a Vault Project tonight under `Work/Projects/ColPali Whole-Page Embeddings/`. The standard layout — landing file, deep-dive with citations, references with real URLs, proposal with problem statement and proposed solution and success criteria, strategic plan with thirty-sixty-ninety phasing, execution plan with milestones and owners. Tagged for-review-true. The execution plan names byaldi as the prototype layer, ColFlor or ColQwen-two as the model picks, and Qdrant on Alien as the production-store target. The strategic plan ladders up to a one-year programme of work — at thirty days, the POCUS prototype is running and the Vault is indexed; at sixty days, the mixed-media RAG stack is integrated into Ada and the Sepsis Poster Studio retrieval space is live; at ninety days, the PICC business case has been re-drafted using the new pipeline and the data-sovereignty governance documentation is ready for HAC review.
Achernar: Achernar — and the things we did not cover that are worth flagging for future episodes. Pixel poisoning attacks on visual retrievers[65] — somebody can poison your index by uploading a pixel-perturbed PDF. Hierarchical patch compression, HPC-ColPali, arXiv twenty-five-zero-six-two-one-six-zero-one[48] — thirty-two times compression with under two percent NDCG drop. Token pooling and patch pruning — Sculpting the Vector Space, arXiv twenty-six-zero-two-one-nine-five-four-nine[52]. Each of those is an episode in its own right. We held this episode to the canonical opening-move story so the foundations land cleanly.
Vindemiatrix: Vindemiatrix — and the one open question I want to leave the listener with. Of the six applications, the one with the highest combination of clinical value, clear governance pathway, and novel published contribution is the PICC business-case workflow. That's the application I'd take to a clinical-governance committee first. The POCUS learning resource is the easiest to build. The Vault and mixed-media RAG are the most useful day-to-day. The Sepsis Poster Studio extension is the smallest scope and could ship this month. The tax-receipt pipeline is honestly DSE-shaped, not ColPali-shaped, and is an adjustment to an existing pipeline rather than a new one. Build them in that order, and the published case-series writes itself.
Rasalgethi: Rasalgethi — and a closing builder's note. Most of this stack is open-source, lives on the laptop, and runs without sending data to a third party. That's the Apple-silicon-friendly story. ColFlor is one-hundred-and-seventy-four million parameters and embeds at ten pages per second on an M2 Max[18]. The entire infrastructure footprint is one Qdrant Docker container plus a few hundred lines of Python. The barrier to building this in your own clinical-or-research environment, in twenty-twenty-six, is no longer money or compute — it is governance, consent, and the question of who controls the derived data. That's the unfinished work.
Charon: Charon. Cast tonight — Charon, that's me, opening and closing. Kore. Vindemiatrix. Rasalgethi. Achernar. Music outro and brand-voice sign-off automatic from the new v-two-point-one pipeline. The Vault Project entry under `Work/Projects/ColPali Whole-Page Embeddings/` will be live in the vault before this episode reaches the feed. Look for the `for_review: true` tag. State of Play, episode twenty.
Alnilam: Thanks for listening to State of Play. Until next week.