Algieba: This is State of Play, episode thirty-four. About forty-five minutes today. I'm your anchor for this one. We're going regulatory. Specifically — what AHPRA and the Medical Board of Australia actually said about artificial intelligence in clinical practice, what they didn't say, where Australian civil liability law actually lands when an AI tool gets it wrong, and what changes on Monday morning for a rural medical officer in Port Pirie, or Whyalla, or any other place where one consultant is on, the trolley is one Penthrox short, and the AI scribe in your laptop has just hallucinated a medication that the patient never mentioned. Cast for today, in order of first appearance. William Osler Ross will hold the clinical lens — the consult-room reality, the bedside reasoning, what it's like when the tool suggests something and you're the one who has to decide whether to follow it. Hermione Granger Ross will run the regulatory text and the case law — Rogers, Wallace, the Civil Liability Act, the indemnifier letters. Marie Curie Ross is on equity and ethics — training-data bias, who gets the tool, who doesn't, what fair use of AI looks like in a town with a twelve per cent Aboriginal cohort. Edward Tufte Ross is on data infrastructure — what's actually being logged, what audit trails exist, what's missing for retrospective review. Richard Feynman Ross is on mechanism — how the model is producing the output, why "hallucination" is the wrong word, what a Bayesian reading of an LLM transcript actually looks like. Fred Rogers Ross is on patient communication — consent, the "we used a tool to help" conversation, when it matters and when it might not. And Alnilam will close us out, as always. Let me set the scene. It is Monday morning. You are running an urgent clinic. You have a fifty-three-year-old woman who's come in for a chest-pain follow-up after an emergency department presentation eleven days ago. You're using an ambient scribing tool. Phlox, or Heidi, or Lyrebird, or one of half a dozen others — the specific tool does not matter for this episode. The patient consents to the recording at the start of the consult, you go through your history, your examination, you explain the next steps. You finish the consult. You open the AI-generated note. It is good. It is mostly accurate. It is structured into history, examination, assessment, plan, the way the local template demands. And then under "medications," the note lists "frusemide 40 mg daily." The patient is not on frusemide. The patient never mentioned frusemide. There is no frusemide in the patient's My Health Record, no frusemide on the previous medication review, no frusemide anywhere in the world. The AI tool has hallucinated it. You catch it. You delete the line. You sign the note. The patient leaves. No harm done. Yet. But over the next year that scribing tool generates roughly three thousand consults of your work. Some go through a registrar. Some go through a locum. Some go through you on a late Friday afternoon when you've been on since seven AM and a sick neonate is incoming. And somewhere in that volume, the hallucination is not frusemide. Somewhere in that volume it's penicillin, in a documented allergy. Somewhere it is the dose of warfarin, off by a factor of ten. Somewhere it is the indication for surgery, and the consent that flows from that documentation will rest on a sentence that the patient never said. That is the consult-room reality of AI in Australian clinical practice in twenty twenty-six. And the question this episode is going to spend the next forty-five minutes on is — when that happens, where do you stand? Legally, professionally, ethically? What does AHPRA expect? What does the Medical Board expect? What does the Civil Liability Act 1936 (South Australia) actually say about your defence? Which of your indemnifier — MIPS, MDA National, Avant — is covering you and which has been quietly silent? And what is the one-page document you should have on your consult-room wall by Friday afternoon? Hermione, you've got the regulatory text. Tell us what AHPRA actually said.
Erinome: Hermione here. So the document at the centre of this conversation is not a statute, it is not a code, it is a piece of guidance — and the precise title matters. AHPRA, the Australian Health Practitioner Regulation Agency, together with the National Boards including the Medical Board of Australia, published it in late twenty twenty-four. The title is "Meeting your professional obligations when using artificial intelligence in healthcare." It sits on the AHPRA website at ahpra.gov.au under Resources. It runs to a relatively small number of pages. And it was launched together with a Medical Board news item on the twenty-second of August twenty twenty-four titled "Applying your code of conduct to evolving technologies — AI in healthcare." Let me be precise about what the document is and what it is not. It is not a new code of conduct. It is not a new standard. It is not a statutory instrument. It is, in AHPRA's own framing, a clarification of what the existing code of conduct already requires. Which means — and this is critical for the rest of the episode — the document does not create new obligations. It articulates how existing obligations apply in a new technological context. The legal status is therefore that of regulatory guidance issued under the National Law, which informs how the Board will assess a notification, but is not itself binding law. The document is built around six broad principles. I'll name them in the AHPRA framing. One — accountability. The practitioner remains accountable for clinical decisions. AI does not transfer accountability. The literal text reminds practitioners to "apply human judgment to any output of AI." This is the most-quoted line in the document. Two — understanding. Practitioners are expected to "understand enough" about the AI tool they're using. AHPRA's language: review information about the technology, how it was trained and tested, its intended use and its limitations. Three — transparency. Practitioners should inform patients about their use of AI and address any concerns the patient raises. Four — informed consent. Practitioners are reminded to involve patients in the use of AI and obtain consent — though, importantly, the document does not specify whether consent must be written, verbal, opt-in, or opt-out. Five — quality and safety. Practitioners are reminded to maintain professional standards and report adverse events. Six — ongoing professional development. Practitioners are expected to keep current with the technology. That is the headline architecture. The Medical Board's parallel news item, on the twenty-second of August twenty twenty-four, applies the existing Good Medical Practice code — section two on clinical care, section three on partnership with patients, section eight on professional behaviour — to AI use, but again, does not introduce new obligations. The Australian Commission on Safety and Quality in Health Care, the ACSQHC, has been running alongside this with an AI Clinical Use Guide, and in August twenty twenty-five published an AI Safety Scenario specifically on ambient scribes. The Therapeutic Goods Administration has separately addressed digital scribes — and this is a point we'll come back to — by clarifying that digital scribes that simply transcribe and summarise a consult are generally NOT classified as medical devices under the Therapeutic Goods Act, and therefore are NOT subject to TGA pre-market evaluation. That is a substantial gap, and we'll unpack it later. So that is the regulatory landscape as of today, May twenty-fourth twenty twenty-six. AHPRA + Medical Board guidance, ACSQHC clinical use guide, TGA position on scribes-not-being-devices. Three documents. None of them statutes. All of them framing how existing obligations apply. Algieba, that's the structure. I'll hand back for the framing.
Algieba: Good. So we have a guidance document, a clinical use guide, and a TGA position. What's notable is what's NOT in any of them. Marie, you've been arguing this is more interesting for its silences. Let me hand to you with Hermione — what's missing?
Despina: Curie here. Let me name the silences. There are at least seven of them, and they are not minor. They are the difference between a document that gives a rural medical officer something defensible to point to when something goes wrong, and a document that gives them mostly aspiration. Silence number one — indemnity. The AHPRA guidance does not address what an indemnifier will or will not cover when AI is in the loop. It assumes the indemnity question is resolved by the doctor's contract with their MDO, but the indemnifiers themselves have been deliberately cautious. We'll come back to this. Silence number two — training-data provenance. The guidance asks practitioners to "understand enough" about the technology. It does not require the vendor to disclose what data the model was trained on, what populations were represented or not represented, what the documented failure modes are, or how the tool performs differentially across demographic subgroups. In practice, this means a clinician using an ambient scribe to document a consult with an Aboriginal patient has no enforceable mechanism to ask the vendor — was your training data representative of First Nations speech patterns, names, and clinical idioms? Silence number three — off-label use. The guidance addresses AI used for its intended purpose. It does not address what happens when a practitioner uses a general-purpose tool — say, a consumer chatbot — to summarise a clinical question, generate a discharge instruction, or assist a referral letter. That use is widespread. It is largely undocumented. It sits outside the formal device or scribe categories, and outside the indemnifier conversations. Silence number four — AI in supervision and trainee assessment. If an ACRRM or RACGP registrar uses an AI tool to draft a case summary that is reviewed by their supervisor, is that the registrar's clinical reasoning being assessed, or is it the model's? The guidance is silent. RACGP has begun to address this — they have, as of twenty twenty-five, strongly discouraged the use of AI scribes by GPT1 registrars. ACRRM has not taken a parallel position. That is a regulatory asymmetry between two colleges that share a registrar pipeline. Silence number five — AI in mandatory reporting decisions. Australian mandatory reporting law requires a practitioner to form a "reasonable belief" — about impairment, about notifiable conduct. If the formation of that belief is partly assisted by an AI tool — a triage assistant, a pattern-detection alert, a risk-score model — the legal pathway is not articulated. Does the practitioner own the belief? Does the AI's confidence score count as evidence? The guidance does not say. Silence number six — AI in coroner-referrable death certification. If a death occurs and the cause-of-death certificate is drafted with AI assistance, what is the documentation chain that the coroner can audit? Who logged what? At what point did the AI make a substantive contribution to the assessment? The guidance is silent. The SA Coroner's Office has not addressed this. The SA Coroner's Court rules require the practitioner to certify the cause of death as their professional opinion — but the document is silent on the AI question entirely. Silence number seven — equity. The guidance does not address differential access. It does not address whether AI scribes are funded by Medicare for rural practitioners, who increasingly carry the highest documentation burden. It does not address whether models trained predominantly on metropolitan English-language records will perform adequately for patients with accented English, for patients with intellectual disability, for patients whose first language is not English. The Productivity Commission's December twenty twenty-five report on artificial intelligence in healthcare flagged the bias question, but the AHPRA guidance does not require any specific vendor disclosure on it. That's the seven. There are smaller silences underneath. But those are the ones that matter for the consult-room. I'll let Hermione take the legal pathway.
Erinome: Right. So if AHPRA's guidance is the soft frame, the hard frame is the law of negligence — and that's where I want to spend the next stretch. Australian medical negligence law has, since nineteen ninety-two, sat under Rogers v Whitaker. Just to be precise — Rogers v Whitaker is the High Court decision where Mr Rogers, an ophthalmic surgeon, performed surgery on Mrs Whitaker's nearly-blind right eye. She subsequently developed sympathetic ophthalmia in her good left eye and went bilaterally blind. The risk of sympathetic ophthalmia was approximately one in fourteen thousand. Mrs Whitaker had repeatedly asked detailed questions about possible complications. The surgeon had not warned her about that specific risk. The High Court found him liable, and in doing so, rejected the Bolam test as the standard for warning. The legal principle from Rogers v Whitaker is — a doctor has a duty to warn a patient of a material risk inherent in proposed treatment, and a risk is material if (a) a reasonable person in the patient's position would attach significance to it, OR (b) the doctor knows or ought reasonably to know that this particular patient would attach significance to it. That second limb is critical, because it is patient-specific, not population-specific. Rogers v Whitaker was effectively codified into the Australian state Civil Liability Acts in the early two-thousands. In South Australia, the relevant section is section forty-one of the Civil Liability Act nineteen thirty-six. And section forty-one is where this gets very interesting for AI. Section forty-one is the peer professional opinion defence. The text, in essence, says — a person providing a professional service is not negligent if it is established that they acted in a manner that was, at the time, widely accepted in Australia by their peers as competent professional practice. The defence is broad. It applies even where there are differing opinions widely accepted in the profession. It does not require the opinion to be universally accepted. Professional opinion can be relied on EXCEPT — and the section is explicit about this — if the court finds the opinion to be irrational. But — and this is the critical AI carve-out, and almost no one is talking about it — section forty-one (six) of the South Australian Act says explicitly that the peer professional opinion defence does NOT apply to liability arising in connection with the giving of, or the failure to give, a warning, advice, or other information in respect of a risk of death or injury associated with the provision of a health care service. In plain English — the section forty-one defence does NOT cover the duty to warn. The duty to warn still sits under Rogers v Whitaker. And the duty to warn, in the AI context, includes — at least arguably — the duty to disclose to a patient that AI was used in the consultation, where a reasonable person would attach significance to that fact, OR where the particular patient would attach significance. So if a patient would, on the Rogers v Whitaker test, attach significance to the fact that an AI tool was used to document their consult — and there is good reason to think many would, particularly Aboriginal patients given the data sovereignty layer, particularly patients with mental health histories given recording sensitivities, particularly patients with intellectual disability given the consent question — then the duty to inform them is alive, the section forty-one defence does NOT apply, and the standard is the Rogers v Whitaker material-risk standard. That is a substantial finding, and the AHPRA guidance does not articulate it. The Wallace v Kam decision in twenty thirteen sharpened the causation question. In Wallace v Kam, the High Court held that even where there is a failure to warn, the plaintiff still has to prove that, had they been warned, they would not have proceeded. And the court split the duty to warn into discrete risks — meaning that a failure to warn about risk A does not establish causation if the risk that eventuated was risk B. In the AI context — if a clinician failed to disclose that AI was used in documentation, and the patient was subsequently harmed by something other than the AI documentation itself, the Wallace v Kam framework would likely defeat causation. But if the AI documentation directly caused the harm — the hallucinated medication, the misrecorded allergy, the wrong dose — the causal pathway is direct, and Wallace v Kam does not protect. So that's the negligence frame. Rogers v Whitaker plus Wallace v Kam plus section forty-one of the South Australian Civil Liability Act. Three pillars, with section forty-one carving out the warning-and-information limb. I want to add a final point on this. The standard of care under section forty-one is "widely accepted in Australia by members of the same profession." As of May twenty twenty-six, there is no widely-accepted standard for AI use in clinical practice. We have AHPRA guidance, RACGP guidance, the early ACRRM position statement. We do not yet have a consensus. Which means that, paradoxically, the section forty-one defence may be HARDER to invoke for AI use right now than it will be in two or three years — because there is no settled peer practice to point to. A practitioner using AI in twenty twenty-six is operating on the frontier; the legal frontier is also there, and it has not been mapped. Algieba, back to you for the indemnifiers.
Algieba: Important point. The legal frontier is not mapped because the peer practice has not consolidated. Now — the MDOs. The indemnifiers. Where do they sit? Osler, you've been working with MIPS recently on the PICC scope-of-practice letter. Hermione, where are the indemnifier positions?
Sadachbia: Osler here. Before we get to the formal positions, let me ground us in the real-world transaction. The indemnifier conversation is not abstract. It is a letter you write, addressed to a specific person at a specific MDO, asking specific questions, and receiving specific written answers that you then attach to your local credentialing committee submission. That is the pattern. Jacob has just done this exact transaction with MIPS for an unrelated scope-of-practice question — peripherally inserted central catheters at Port Pirie, drafted on the twenty-third of May twenty twenty-six, in flight as we record. The pattern is — you ask the indemnifier five concrete questions, you ask for written response, you wait three weeks, you attach the response to your committee submission. That is the move that protects you. For AI tool use, the parallel five-question letter would look like this — and I'm naming this because nobody else is. One. Under what conditions does MIPS — or MDA National, or Avant — provide indemnity cover for clinical documentation generated wholly or in part by an ambient AI scribe? Two. Does cover extend to clinical decisions made on the basis of an AI-generated summary, including referral content, prescriptions, and discharge instructions? Three. Are there specific AI tools the indemnifier has reviewed and considers within or outside the indemnified scope? Four. What documentation does the indemnifier expect to see in the medical record to evidence the practitioner's review and verification of AI-generated content? Five. Are there specific patient cohorts — Aboriginal patients, mental health patients, paediatric, intellectually disabled, anatomically complex — that the indemnifier considers outside the indemnified scope for AI-assisted documentation at this maturity level? That is the letter. It does not exist in the public domain because the indemnifiers have not been asked it in public. Hermione, what have the indemnifiers actually said?
Erinome: The public positions of the three major Australian MDOs as of May twenty twenty-six are these. MDA National published a piece in December twenty twenty-four — title "Artificial Intelligence" — under their library of articles and case studies. The piece is at mdanational.com.au, advice and support, library, articles and case studies, twenty twenty-four, twelve, artificial-intelligence. It is a general-orientation piece. It acknowledges that AI is "rapidly transforming the healthcare industry," names benefits and challenges, and refers practitioners to the AHPRA guidance. It does NOT provide a tool-specific list. It does NOT articulate a financial-cover line. It does NOT name a documentation standard. It is a piece that says, in effect, "we know this is coming, we are watching, follow the AHPRA guidance, contact us about specific situations." That is the de facto position. MIPS — Medical Indemnity Protection Society — has not, to my knowledge as of May twenty-fourth twenty twenty-six, published a public position statement on AI tool use. Their general member advice line is available — info at mips.com.au, level thirty-eight, fifty-five Collins Street, Melbourne — and member-specific advice is the route to a written opinion. The published material focuses on the general scope-of-practice and credentialing pathways. Avant Mutual Group has published occasional commentary on AI in healthcare, generally aligned with the AHPRA framing — practitioner remains accountable, transparency with patients, document the use. They have not issued a tool-specific approval list either. The substance of all three positions is essentially the same. None of the three MDOs has said — "we will not cover you for AI use." None of them has said — "we will cover you for any AI use." All three have effectively said — "follow AHPRA guidance, document your reasoning, contact us about specific situations, we reserve the right to assess the specifics." That is a defensible position from the MDO's perspective. It is also a position that places the documentation-and-judgement burden entirely on the practitioner. Which means — and this is the important practical point — the five-question MIPS-style letter that Osler just described is the actionable move. You do not wait for the indemnifier to publish a position. You write the letter. You attach the response. You file it with your local credentialing committee. That is the pattern that converts ambiguous regulatory text into defensible local practice. Jacob's MIPS PICC letter from May twenty-third twenty twenty-six is the sister document to the AI letter that does not yet exist. It is exactly the same legal-architectural move, applied to a different scope-of-practice question. The transferable lesson is the FORM of the letter, not its content. Algieba, back.
Algieba: Alright. So we have AHPRA guidance, Rogers v Whitaker plus Wallace v Kam plus section forty-one carve-out, and three MDOs that have all said "follow the guidance and ask us about specifics." Now — the practical clinical layer. Four categories of AI tool, all with different risk profiles. Osler, Feynman — let's go.
Sadachbia: There are four tool categories operating in Australian general practice and hospital practice as of mid-twenty twenty-six. They have different risk profiles. They demand different documentation. They sit in different places in the indemnifier conversation. I'll name them and Feynman will unpack the mechanism for each. Category one — ambient scribing. Tools like Phlox, Heidi, Lyrebird, Suki, Nuance Dragon Ambient eXperience, Microsoft Dragon Medical One Ambient. These are tools that listen to the consult and generate a structured clinical note. Their failure mode is the documentation hallucination — a fact in the note that the patient did not say. Category two — clinical decision support. These are tools that generate a differential, suggest a test, or flag a missed diagnosis. Examples in Australian practice include the older non-LLM IBM Watson Health products, newer LLM-based companions like Glass Health, OpenEvidence, and some Bp / MedicalDirector add-ons. Their failure mode is the wrong recommendation — the suggestion that you act on, or fail to act on, on the basis of the tool's output. Category three — generative AI used for patient communication. The discharge letter generated by ChatGPT. The plain-language risk summary drafted by Claude. The referral letter polished by Gemini. Their failure mode is the polished-but-wrong sentence — the smoothed paragraph that reads cleanly but is factually inaccurate, or that smuggles inaccuracies through a fluency veneer. Category four — AI-aided diagnostic imaging interpretation. Tools like Annalise.ai, Aidoc, Rad-AI, Lunit INSIGHT. Their failure mode is the false positive or false negative on a scan. Their regulatory frame is different — they ARE TGA-registered medical devices, and they fall under the TGA's software-as-a-medical-device framework. Feynman, what's actually happening inside each of those?
Puck: Feynman here. Let me strip the jargon. The word "hallucination" is the worst word in the AI literature. It implies the model perceived something that isn't there. The model perceives nothing. The model has no senses, no model of the world, no continuity of experience. What the model does is — it computes a probability distribution over the next token in a sequence. That's it. Every output is probabilistic, and probabilistic in a way that is highly conditioned on the training data and the inference context. So when an ambient scribe "hallucinates" frusemide in a consult where frusemide was never mentioned, what has happened mechanistically is — the model has predicted that, given the surrounding context, the probability of the token sequence "frusemide forty milligrams daily" is higher than the probability of no such token sequence. The model has reached that prediction either because — one, the training data contained many examples of consults with similar surrounding context that DID include frusemide; two, the audio input had an artefact that the model misinterpreted; three, the model has a known fluency-over-accuracy bias and generated content that sounds plausible even though it has no specific evidence. This is not perception. This is statistical prediction. The right Bayesian reading of an AI scribe's output is — it is a prior over what the patient probably said, conditioned on the audio and on the model's general expectation of what consults look like. The clinician's job is to update that prior against their actual memory of the consult — which is the posterior. The AI's output is never the truth. It is the prior. The clinician is the posterior. That framing has practical consequences. Because the model's output is statistical, it has predictable failure modes — and we can name them. For ambient scribing — the failure mode is "completion drift." The model fills in details that complete a clinical pattern even when the data are sparse. Common patterns — patient with chest pain getting frusemide (heart-failure pattern); elderly patient getting metformin (diabetes pattern); patient with cough getting amoxicillin (chest-infection pattern). The model is not making things up randomly. It is completing a pattern. Which means — the failure mode is most dangerous when the patient ALMOST fits the pattern but does not. The clinician's review should be most cautious for the patient who is on the edge of a category. For clinical decision support — the failure mode is "common-recommendation bias." The model recommends the action that is most common in similar clinical contexts in its training corpus. Which means — for rare conditions, for atypical presentations, for non-Western clinical patterns, the recommendation will skew toward the common, the metropolitan, and the Anglocentric. The cost is missed diagnosis in atypical presentations. Particularly relevant in rural and Aboriginal health contexts. For generative patient communication — the failure mode is "fluency masking." The model generates text that reads beautifully. It is grammatical, it is well-structured, it has appropriate medical register. But the fluency is independent of the factual accuracy. So a sentence in a discharge letter that reads cleanly and confidently may be factually wrong, and the fluency makes the wrongness harder to spot. The clinician reviewing the letter is reading for sense, not for fact-check. For diagnostic imaging — the failure mode is "anchoring." The radiologist sees the AI's heatmap or flag, and their subsequent interpretation is anchored on the AI's reading. This is well-documented in the radiology AI literature. Some studies show AI assistance improves accuracy; some show it degrades accuracy by anchoring the reader to a false positive. The effect is dose-dependent on the reader's experience and the tool's calibration. So that's the mechanism, category by category. Osler, what does that mean for what you do in the consult room?
Sadachbia: It means — for each category, the documentation chain has to be different. For ambient scribing — the consult-room move is — at the end of the consult, before the patient leaves, briefly check the AI note against your own memory. Specifically — check medications, allergies, the chief complaint, the agreed plan. Sign off only after that check. Document, in the note, that the AI summary was reviewed by you. Many ambient tools now have an audit field for "clinician-verified." Use it. For clinical decision support — the move is — treat the AI suggestion as a differential prompt, not as a recommendation. If the AI suggests "consider pulmonary embolism" — that goes into your differential. It does not automatically generate the test order. Document the AI's contribution to your reasoning if it changed your decision. For generative patient communication — the move is — every AI-drafted letter or discharge instruction or referral goes through a structured review. Read it for sense AND for fact. Read it twice. Don't sign and send. Specifically — check medications, doses, indications, follow-up timelines, specialist names. Those are the high-risk fields. For diagnostic imaging — the move is — read the scan first, FORM your impression, THEN look at the AI flag. If the AI flag agrees, fine. If the AI flag disagrees, that triggers a second careful look, but it does NOT automatically override your impression. Document any change in your reading attributable to the AI tool. Those are the four consult-room patterns. They are not in the AHPRA guidance. They are derived from the mechanism Feynman just unpacked, and they are what defensible practice looks like. Tufte, you've been thinking about what's logged. What's missing from the data infrastructure?
Iapetus: Tufte here. The audit trail question is the unsexy question, and it is the question that will eventually matter most. Let me name what is being logged and what is not. For ambient scribing, the typical log produced by a commercial tool includes — the audio file, sometimes with retention of seven days to thirty days depending on vendor; the transcript; the structured clinical note as generated; the clinician's edited note; the timestamp of clinician sign-off; and, in some vendors, a diff between the AI-generated note and the clinician-edited note. That diff is the most informative artefact in the entire audit chain — it tells you exactly what the clinician corrected. What is typically NOT logged — the model version that generated the output; the inference parameters (temperature, top-p, the system prompt); the confidence scores associated with individual statements in the note; and, critically, the patient's consent record in a structured field that survives vendor change. For clinical decision support, the typical log includes — the input clinical context; the AI's recommendation; the timestamp; and sometimes the clinician's accept-or-reject decision. What is NOT logged — the model's confidence in the recommendation, the model's full reasoning chain, the alternative recommendations the model considered. For generative patient communication — typically only the final output is preserved. The prompt, the intermediate drafts, the model version, the system prompt — generally NOT logged. For diagnostic imaging — the audit trail is the best of the four categories, because the TGA-regulated imaging AI tools are required to log inputs, outputs, and confidence scores at the device level. This is what regulation looks like when it works. So the asymmetry is — the most heavily-used categories (ambient scribing, decision support, generative patient communication) have the WORST audit trails. The least-used category (imaging AI) has the BEST audit trail. That is upside-down from a clinical-governance perspective. And the AHPRA guidance does not address it. Neither does the Medical Board statement. What follows for practice — and this is the Tufte recommendation — the practitioner should personally maintain a small log of their AI tool use. Not exhaustive. Just sufficient. Tool name, version if known, consent status, date, encounter type. A simple table on the practitioner's own machine. Defensible if asked. Five seconds per encounter. It is the closest thing to a personal audit trail that a clinician currently has, and it is the answer to the question "show me your AI use log" if it ever arrives. Algieba, back to you on the governance dimension.
Algieba: Tufte's personal log is the closest thing to a defensible audit trail. That answers the individual question. Now — the organisational question. RACMA. Clinical governance. Marie, where does AI sit in the incident framework?
Despina: Curie back. Let me name the governance gap and the SAC classification question. For any practising clinician, the question — when an AI tool contributes to a near-miss or an adverse event, where does the incident sit in the SAC framework? SAC1, SAC2, SAC3 — what's the trigger for each? The Australian Commission on Safety and Quality in Health Care defines SAC1 events broadly as those resulting in or with the potential for serious harm or death; SAC2 as moderate harm; SAC3 as minimal harm or near miss. Most jurisdictions, including South Australia, use this framework or a close variant via the SLS (Safety Learning System) or similar. The AI complication is this — if an AI tool contributed to an event, but the clinician's review caught the error, is that a SAC3 near-miss event that needs reporting? Most local governance frameworks would say yes — near-misses are reportable specifically because they reveal latent system failures. But the question of HOW you classify "AI contribution" is unsettled. Was the AI the primary cause? A contributing factor? A latent system failure? The Australian Commission's August twenty twenty-five Ambient Scribe AI Safety Scenario is the closest thing to a guidance document on this, and it explicitly recommends — incident review of any ambient scribe contribution to a clinical error should treat the AI tool as one of multiple contributing factors, alongside clinician fatigue, time pressure, and workflow design. For RACMA — and Jacob, this is the registrar reflection question — the governance lens is this. The organisation needs an AI tool policy. It does not exist yet at most local health networks in regional South Australia. It needs to address — which tools are sanctioned for use; what consent process applies; what audit and review process applies; what incident-classification protocol applies; what training requirements apply; what mandatory reporting trigger applies. That policy is a one-page document. It is not exotic. The work of drafting it is mostly the work of mapping AHPRA's six principles plus the ACSQHC scenario onto local workflow. It is the kind of artefact that, drafted now, would be both defensible and the start of a meaningful local standard. Health Advisory Councils — the HACs that sit alongside the local health networks — should be asking three questions at every meeting where AI comes up. One — what tools are being used here? Two — what is the local consent process? Three — what audit data are we collecting? That is the HAC accountability frame, and it sits within the Council's remit under the SA Health Care Act. There is a further governance dimension that matters for the Aboriginal health context. The OCAP principles — Ownership, Control, Access, Possession — articulated by First Nations Information Governance Centre in Canada, and adopted in spirit by Australian organisations like NACCHO and AIATSIS, name a sovereignty standard that requires Indigenous communities to govern data ABOUT them. An AI tool that processes an Aboriginal patient's consult — particularly a cloud-hosted tool that transmits the audio and the transcript to vendor infrastructure — is operating in a sovereignty grey zone. The current AHPRA guidance does not address this. The Productivity Commission's December twenty twenty-five report flagged it. There is no clear regulatory answer. The practical implication — for Aboriginal patient consults, the on-premises or local-first AI tool stack is the defensible posture. Phlox, OpenScribe, OpenHealth, StenoAI — the open-source local-first cluster that Jacob has been evaluating — is the only configuration where the data does not leave the M4, does not leave the clinic, does not enter vendor infrastructure. That is the sovereignty-aligned posture. It is also the posture that satisfies the most stringent reading of the AHPRA transparency and consent principles. Hermione, the trainee dimension — ACRRM and RACGP.
Erinome: The trainee dimension matters because the legal architecture for assessment depends on it. If a registrar uses AI to draft a case summary that is then signed off by their supervisor, the question is — who is being assessed? RACGP's position, as of twenty twenty-five, is that AI scribes should not be used by GPT1 registrars — the first-year general practice registrars. The rationale is the foundational-skills argument — that the registrar needs to develop clinical reasoning, history-taking, and note-writing as distinct cognitive skills, and that an AI tool that compresses these steps risks degrading the development of the underlying skill. ACRRM's position — published in their twenty twenty-four position statement on AI in healthcare — is more permissive but less specific. ACRRM acknowledges the benefits of AI scribes for rural and remote practice where documentation burden is high, but does not articulate a registrar-specific prohibition. This creates a registrar pathway asymmetry. A dual ACRRM/RACGP registrar — a rare but real category — is subject to different rules depending on which assessment they're currently in. This has not been addressed by either college. There is also the StAMPS — the ACRRM written and clinical assessment — and the equivalent RACGP CCE — the Clinical Competency Examination — to think about. The use of AI to prepare for these assessments — case study review, vignette generation, exam-style question generation — is widespread and unaddressed by either college. The question — if a registrar uses an LLM to generate practice case stems, is that legitimate study, or is it a form of assistance that distorts the eventual assessment? No college has answered. Mini-CEX self-review — where a registrar reviews their own consult video and writes a reflection — is another emerging use case. AI tools can generate reflections from a video transcript. If the registrar's reflection is AI-drafted, is the reflective practice being assessed, or is the AI's reflection being assessed? Again, unanswered. The defensible practice for a registrar, given the asymmetry, is — disclose AI use when it occurs, document the registrar's edits and reasoning, and ask the supervisor for explicit policy guidance. That is not a satisfying answer. It is, however, the only answer the current regulatory landscape supports. Marie, the equity layer.
Despina: The equity layer is the layer that has been most under-articulated, and it is the layer where, if it is not addressed, the damage will accumulate quietly over the next five years. The training-data bias question — most large language models, including the ones underlying Australian ambient scribes, are trained on corpora that are heavily Anglo-American. The Australian medical idiom — the specific way Australian doctors and patients describe symptoms, the use of Australian English drug names, the particular abbreviation patterns of Australian clinical notes — is under-represented. The Indigenous Australian idiom — the cadence, vocabulary, and clinical narratives of Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander patients — is much more severely under-represented. This means — the model performs worse on patient cohorts that are most often harmed by clinical error to begin with. Aboriginal patients, patients with intellectual disability, patients with low English literacy, patients with non-standard accents, patients in low socioeconomic contexts where the documented clinical record is itself noisier. The model's failure modes are concentrated in the populations least able to absorb the harm. The access dimension — AI scribes are typically subscription products. Heidi Pro costs in the order of forty to ninety Australian dollars per month per clinician. For a rural solo practice with a small workforce, that is a real cost. For an urban high-volume practice it is trivial. The access gradient is the wrong way around — rural and regional practices, where documentation burden is highest and clinician burnout is most acute, are also where the AI tool subscription is hardest to absorb. There is no Medicare item that subsidises an AI scribe. There is no Practice Incentives Programme line. There is no rural workforce incentive that addresses it. The surveillance dimension — and this is a Curie point I want to name explicitly. AI tools in healthcare are increasingly framed as "supporting" the clinician. They are also, structurally, surveillance tools. Every consult that goes through an ambient scribe is — in principle — a consult that the vendor could review, that an insurer could request, that a future regulator could subpoena. The asymmetry of who is being surveilled by AI tools — the clinician, the patient, the consultation itself — is not addressed in the AHPRA guidance. The patient cohorts most likely to be subject to AI-assisted documentation are also the cohorts most likely to be subject to other forms of administrative surveillance — Aboriginal patients, patients on Centrelink, patients in correctional facilities, patients with child-protection involvement. The aggregation of multiple AI-assisted records creates a potential surveillance dossier that no individual consultation generated. The privacy frame in Australian law — the Privacy Act, the APPs, the My Health Record Act — does not anticipate this aggregation. The equity recommendation is — and this is the one Curie line on AI in clinical practice that should be quoted — if your AI tool stack does not work as well for your Aboriginal patient as it does for your non-Aboriginal patient, then you do not have an AI tool. You have a tool that mostly works, with a subgroup harmed disproportionately, and the cost of the harm sits with the subgroup. That is the equity test. Fred, the patient communication piece.
Vindemiatrix: Rogers here. Thank you, Marie. Let me speak gently for a moment about the consent and disclosure conversation, because it is the place where the regulatory architecture meets the patient as a person. The AHPRA guidance asks practitioners to inform patients about their use of AI and to obtain informed consent. The literal text is brief and the practical implementation is undefined. Here is what the conversation looks like, in my view, when it is done well. At the start of the consult, before the recording begins — "I use a tool that listens to our conversation and helps me write the notes. Your privacy is protected. The recording is kept secure and is not shared. You can ask me to turn it off at any time. Are you comfortable with me using it today?" That is twenty-five seconds. It is plain language. It does not use the word "AI" or "artificial intelligence" or "large language model" because those words mean different things to different patients, and many patients will hear those words and become more anxious than informed. It names the function — a tool that listens and helps with the notes. It names the safety — privacy protected, recording kept secure. It names the patient's control — you can ask me to turn it off. It asks a clear yes or no. If the patient asks more questions — and many will — the answer is — "The tool is one that helps me. I check what it writes. I am responsible for what goes in your record. If you would prefer I not use it, that is fine, I will write the notes by hand." That respects the patient's autonomy. It does not put the patient in a position where they feel they are slowing down the consult or being difficult. For an Aboriginal patient, the conversation might add — and this is a sensitive judgement call — "This is an Australian-based tool, and the recording stays on this computer in this room." If the tool is cloud-based, then the practitioner should be explicit — "The recording is sent securely to a company that processes it." That honesty is what consent requires. For a patient with cognitive impairment or intellectual disability — the conversation may need a family member or carer present, and it may need to happen at a slower pace. Consent in those settings is not a single moment; it is a continuing conversation. For a patient with a mental health history — particularly histories that involve persecution, surveillance, or paranoia — the conversation needs care. For some patients, the disclosure that a tool is recording the conversation will be the right thing. For others, it may distress them, and the right thing may be to do the consult without the tool. The phrase to NEVER use is — "Don't worry about it, it's standard." It is not standard. It is new. The patient has the right to ask. The practitioner has the obligation to answer. When something goes wrong — when the AI hallucinates a medication, when the discharge letter has a wrong dose, when the referral letter goes out with the wrong specialist named — the conversation with the patient about what happened needs to be honest. "I used a tool to help write your discharge instructions. The tool made an error. I caught it. I want to tell you about it because it could have caused you harm." That is open disclosure, and it is the Australian standard under the Australian Open Disclosure Framework. The AI does not change the standard. It does change the texture of the conversation, because the patient may not know what to make of the tool. The patient does not need to become an expert in AI. The patient needs to be treated as the centre of the care. The tool serves that care. When the tool ceases to serve, the tool is set aside. That is the right framing, and it is what the consent and disclosure conversation should embody. Algieba, back to you for the synthesis.
Algieba: That's the spine. The AHPRA guidance, the Civil Liability frame, the MDO positions, the four tool categories, the governance dimension, the trainee dimension, the equity dimension, and the patient communication piece. Now — the synthesis. The one-page document. The thing Jacob would actually publish if asked. All voices in on this one.
Erinome: The one-page document is — "AI in my consultation room." Single page. Eight bullets. Designed for the consult-room wall. The eight bullets are these. One — I have read the AHPRA guidance "Meeting your professional obligations when using AI in healthcare" (August 2024), and the Medical Board's "Applying your code of conduct to evolving technologies — AI in healthcare" (August 2024). Two — I disclose AI use to patients. The script I use is: "I use a tool that listens to our conversation and helps me write the notes. You can ask me to turn it off at any time. Are you comfortable with that?" Three — I review every AI-generated output before it enters the patient record. For ambient scribing — I check medications, allergies, chief complaint, and the agreed plan. For clinical decision support — I treat the AI suggestion as a differential prompt, not a recommendation. For generative patient communication — I read every AI-drafted letter twice, once for sense, once for fact. For diagnostic imaging AI — I form my impression first, then check the AI flag. Four — I maintain a personal AI tool log. Tool name, version, consent status, date, encounter type. Five seconds per encounter. On my own machine. Five — I have a written indemnity opinion from my MDO covering the AI tools I use, the documentation expectations, and the patient cohorts within scope. If I do not have that opinion, I have written for it. Six — for Aboriginal patient consults, I default to a local-first AI tool configuration that does not transmit the audio or transcript to vendor infrastructure. If that is not available, I have a documented consent conversation that includes the data-sovereignty question. Seven — for trainees under my supervision, I follow the college position on registrar AI use (RACGP — discouraged for GPT1; ACRRM — permissive but supervised), and I document the trainee's AI use in their assessment record. Eight — when an AI-contributed incident or near-miss occurs, I report it via the local Safety Learning System or equivalent, naming the AI tool as a contributing factor, and treat the incident as a system-learning opportunity. That is the one page. It fits on a single A4 sheet. It is defensible against the AHPRA guidance. It is defensible against the Civil Liability Act. It is defensible against the MDO position. It is defensible against the ACSQHC ambient scribe scenario. It is the framework Jacob would publish if asked.
Sadachbia: Osler. The clinical view on that one-page document is — it works. The eight bullets are operationalisable in the consult room. None of them slows the consult down by more than fifteen seconds. Several of them — the personal log, the indemnifier letter — are one-off setup costs, not per-consult costs. The disclosure script is twenty-five seconds at the start of each consult, and most patients will say yes and move on. The one place where the document is incomplete is the question of what to do when the AI output is uncertain — when you, the clinician, are not sure whether the note is accurate. The right move there is to default to your own clinical memory, to ask the patient to confirm the agreed plan at the end of the consult, and to flag the uncertainty in the note explicitly. The patient as the authoritative source on their own history is the underlying principle, and AI does not change that.
Despina: Curie. The equity test for the one-page document is — does this work for the patient cohort that is most vulnerable to documentation error? My answer is — it works partially. Bullets two, three, six, and seven do address the equity dimension. But the framework does not require active vendor disclosure on training data bias, does not require a Medicare-funded subsidy for rural practitioners, does not require Indigenous data sovereignty as a precondition for tool use. Those are gaps that the individual clinician cannot solve. They are systemic. The one-page document is the maximum a clinician can do within the existing framework. The fuller change requires regulation we do not yet have.
Iapetus: Tufte. From the audit-trail perspective the one-page document is strong on the disclosure and personal-log dimensions, weak on the vendor-side audit dimension because the clinician cannot compel the vendor to log model versions, confidence scores, or training data provenance. The remediation is — for the practice or institution, a vendor selection rubric that requires the vendor to disclose those fields contractually before the tool is adopted. The individual practitioner cannot enforce this; the practice or LHN can.
Puck: Feynman. The mechanism layer of the one-page document is implicit. The framework assumes the clinician understands that the AI output is a prior, not a posterior. That assumption may not hold for clinicians without time to learn the mechanism. There is a training piece here — clinicians who use AI tools should understand, at least briefly, that the tool is doing probabilistic completion, that it has failure modes that are predictable, and that the clinician's review is the calibration step. That is a five-minute conversation, repeated periodically, and it is currently absent from most CPD frameworks.
Vindemiatrix: Rogers. The one-page document is honest about what it does. It does not pretend to be more than a framework. It treats the patient as the centre. It treats the clinician as the responsible party. It treats the tool as a tool. That is the right framing, and I would endorse it being published.
Algieba: Good. The one-page document is solid. Now — implementation. The one-week plan. What does a rural medical officer, in Port Pirie or Whyalla or Naracoorte or any other regional town, actually do this week to audit and document their AI tool use?
Sadachbia: The one-week plan is — five tasks, each thirty minutes or less. Day one — Monday. Inventory the AI tools currently in use in your clinical practice. Name each tool. Note the vendor. Note the version if known. Note the use case. Note the consent process currently in place. That is your starting baseline. Day two — Tuesday. Draft the one-page disclosure script. Print three copies. Put one on your desk. Put one in your bag. Put one in the consult room. Practise saying it out loud three times until it is natural. The script becomes part of your consult opening. Day three — Wednesday. Write the MDO letter. Five-question letter modelled on Jacob's MIPS PICC letter from May twenty-third. Indemnity cover under what conditions, documentation expectations, patient cohorts within scope, specific tools reviewed, ongoing supervision expectations. Send by email. Diarise for response in twenty-one days. Day four — Thursday. Set up the personal AI tool log. A simple spreadsheet or note. Tool, version, consent, date, encounter type. Start logging today. Build the habit. Day five — Friday. Talk to your medical director. Or your supervising consultant. Or your clinical lead. The conversation is — "I am formalising my AI tool use. Here is the one-page framework. Here is the MDO letter I have sent. Are there any local policy considerations I should know about? Is the LHN drafting anything?" That conversation makes you visible inside the local governance structure. It makes the AI tool question visible too. Hermione, anything to add on the legal documentation chain?
Erinome: One addition. Save copies of everything. The MDO response letter, the AHPRA guidance you have read, the local policy if it exists, the consent script you use. Save them in a single folder, ideally a personal folder that travels with you across employers — not the employer's IT system. The reason — if a notification or claim arises in three years' time, the audit trail will need to be reproducible from your records, not the employer's. The folder is the audit-trail-of-last-resort, and it costs nothing to maintain.
Despina: And the equity check. At the end of week one, review your AI tool use specifically against your Aboriginal patient consults, your patients with intellectual disability, your patients with non-English first languages. Did the tool perform differently? Were the notes accurate? If you cannot answer those questions because the data are not captured, that is itself the finding — and the next-week task is to start capturing that data, even informally.
Algieba: Right. The week one plan is — five tasks, each thirty minutes. Inventory. Draft script. Send MDO letter. Set up log. Talk to medical director. Plus the equity check. By Friday end of business, the rural medical officer has a defensible position they did not have on Monday morning. Last segment. Cross-topic synergy. Where does this episode connect to the projects already running in Jacob's portfolio? Marie, you've been mapping these.
Despina: Five active projects intersect with this episode. Let me name them. One — Phlox. Jacob's evaluation of the open-source local-first scribe cluster — Phlox, OpenScribe, OpenHealth, StenoAI — is the Tier-three sovereign-stack arm of his AI-in-clinical-recording programme. The AHPRA guidance does not differentiate local-first from cloud-based AI; the data-sovereignty argument we made earlier in this episode is the reason it should. The Phlox evaluation is the empirical answer to the question — can a clinician satisfy the strictest reading of the AHPRA transparency principle plus the Indigenous data sovereignty constraint using open-source infrastructure on an M4? Jacob's evaluation will, in part, generate the evidence base. Two — Hurn Medical. Jacob's commercial entity. The one-page framework from this episode is, in Hurn Medical terms, a candidate Tier-three white-paper. It is publishable as a clinician-engineer-built resource for rural and regional Australian practice. The market for that paper exists. Other Australian rural GPs are asking the same question. Publishing the framework as a Hurn Medical asset is a viable monetisation path that also serves the field. Three — CG Agentic AI Reports. Jacob's clinical-governance AI work for the Yorke and Northern LHN. The incident-classification framework Marie articulated earlier — how an AI-contributed incident is classified in the SAC framework — is the substrate for the CG Agentic AI Reports work. The two projects feed each other. Four — the MIPS PICC letter from May twenty-third. The letter we have referenced multiple times this episode. The pattern of writing a five-question letter to the indemnifier, asking for written response, and attaching it to the local credentialing submission — that pattern is transferable from PICC to AI tool use, and the AI tool letter is the next natural item on Jacob's MDO correspondence list. Both letters share the same legal-architectural shape. Five — RACMA fellowship. The governance dimension we discussed — local AI tool policy, incident classification, HAC accountability — is directly the kind of material a RACMA registrar reflection or research piece would address. Jacob is exactly the right person to write the piece. It would, at the same time, count toward his RACMA evidence and start to fill the regulatory gap we have spent forty-five minutes naming. Those are the five intersections. They are not idle. They are the kind of synergy that, taken together, produces a defensible body of work in twenty twenty-six.
Algieba: Good. Synergy is real. Five projects, all touching, all reinforcing. Let me close. What we have done in this episode. We have walked through the AHPRA and Medical Board AI in clinical practice guidance — its six principles, its scope, what it covers and what it does not. We have named seven significant silences in the guidance — indemnity, training data provenance, off-label use, supervision and trainee assessment, mandatory reporting, coroner-referrable death certification, and equity. We have walked through where Australian Civil Liability law actually lands — Rogers v Whitaker plus Wallace v Kam plus section forty-one of the South Australian Civil Liability Act, with the critical carve-out that the peer professional opinion defence does NOT apply to the duty to warn. We have walked through the positions of the three major Australian MDOs — MIPS, MDA National, Avant — and named the pattern that converts ambiguous guidance into defensible local practice, which is the five-question MDO letter. We have characterised the four AI tool categories — ambient scribing, clinical decision support, generative patient communication, diagnostic imaging AI — and named the failure mode and the consult-room move for each. We have addressed the data-infrastructure gap — what is logged, what is not. We have addressed the governance dimension — SAC classification, local policy, HAC accountability. We have addressed the trainee dimension — RACGP versus ACRRM positions, and the registrar pathway asymmetry. We have addressed the equity dimension — training data bias, access gradient, surveillance asymmetry. We have addressed the patient communication piece — the consent script, the open disclosure conversation. We have proposed an eight-point one-page framework, and a five-task one-week plan. And we have connected this episode to five active projects in Jacob's portfolio — Phlox, Hurn Medical, CG Agentic AI Reports, the MIPS PICC letter, and the RACMA fellowship. What changes on Monday morning for a rural medical officer? Three things. One — print the eight-bullet framework. Stick it on the wall. Two — start using the disclosure script at the start of every consult where AI is used. Three — write the MDO letter and start the twenty-one-day clock. That is forty-five minutes. We have not solved the regulatory gap. We have, I hope, made the gap visible, and made the defensible practice within it visible too. Show notes. Sources cited. Cross-references to the Phlox project, the Hurn Medical project, the CG Agentic AI Reports project, the MIPS PICC letter, the RACMA fellowship project. The companion JTR brief landing today at vault path JTR Inbox slash JTR brief two six oh five two four sop e three four ahpra ai. Intro music — Comparsa, by Kevin MacLeod at incompetech dot com, Creative Commons Attribution four. Outro music — Awaiting Return, by Kevin MacLeod at incompetech dot com, Creative Commons Attribution four. To Hermione, Curie, Osler, Tufte, Feynman, and Rogers — thanks for the work. The framework is yours as much as anyone's. That's State of Play, episode thirty-four.
Alnilam: Thanks for listening to State of Play. Until next week.