Ada Rosalind Ross: This is State of Play, Episode 42. I am Ada Rosalind Ross. About forty minutes today, from the self-sent inbox sweep covering the forty-eight hours since episode forty-one closed. The lead cluster reads as one coherent thesis — AI agents have moved from autocomplete to proactive operator. Seven separate items in two days, all pointing the same direction: memory plus grounding plus always-on. Around it: the generative media stack quietly consolidating onto a handful of pillars, a piece on personal AI as design partner that maps onto our own Ross-family persona work, two research-methods notes worth flagging, a brief HAC accountability bridge, and a Stoic close. The Ross family across the desk tonight is Alan Turing on the agent architecture, Richard Feynman on mechanism, William Osler on the clinical implications, Edward Tufte on what to measure, Ansel Adams on the generative-media aesthetic, Hermione Granger on the evidence base, Marie Curie on the ethics and the HAC bridge, and Epictetus to close. Cluster one is the substantial one, so we spend the first half of the episode there.
Ada Rosalind Ross: Frame for the cluster. Seven items in the sweep. Anthropic shipped dynamic workflows in Claude. The Gemini app pivoted to proactive twenty-four-by-seven help. Google released an Agent Engine codelab on BigQuery with persistent preferences across sessions. Google also released a grounding codelab that pins agents to real-world location data via the Maps Platform. A practitioner blog post on Claude Code's memory becoming the durable substrate for production automation. A trade write-up of Centralcoms, a vertical that builds agents for residential property management — maintenance coordination, leasing workflows, back-office end-to-end. And a survey piece on coding agents being deployed in the social sciences. Different products, different vendors, different verticals — but the through-line is the same: memory plus grounding plus always-on. Turing, set the architectural frame.
Alan Turing Ross: Alan Turing Ross — architecture tonight. The category-defining shift in this cluster is the move from agent-as-autocomplete to agent-as-operator. Autocomplete agents react. You prompt them, they respond, the loop closes, the model has no further role until the next prompt. Operator agents persist. They have memory of what they have done before, they have grounding in the user's actual world — a calendar, a code repository, a property-management database, a BigQuery table — and they keep running between your prompts. That is the architectural inversion in the seven items the sweep returned. None of them is novel in isolation; together they describe a phase change.
Alan Turing Ross: Take the four most telling examples. Anthropic's dynamic workflows in Claude push the model from a single-turn responder to a workflow runner that holds state across many tool calls and many minutes. Google's Gemini app becoming proactive twenty-four-by-seven means the agent initiates contact when something changes in the user's life that the agent thinks is worth surfacing — your flight is delayed, your inbox has something time-sensitive, your reminder is overdue. The Google Agent Engine codelab on BigQuery is the most architecturally explicit of the four — it specifically calls out persistent preferences across sessions, which is the technical phrase for saying the agent has a long-term memory store keyed to the user. And Claude Code's memory shipping in production workflows means the same capability lives in the developer's IDE, where every interaction with the agent builds on every prior interaction.
Alan Turing Ross: Stack those four with the Centralcoms residential-property-management agent — which is the same architecture deployed vertically — and the LUNA FPGA toolkit, which is a hardware aside but matters because the next hardware layer for agent-as-operator is going to be specialised inference chips, not generic GPUs. The trade press writes about it as an AI productivity story; what it actually is is the early structure of how computing gets reorganised when the agent is the user-facing surface and the application is the substrate the agent walks around on.
Ada Rosalind Ross: Feynman, what changed under the hood that made this possible right now?
Richard Feynman Ross: Richard Feynman Ross — mechanism. Three things converged. First, the memory layer we covered in episode forty-one. GBrain, Acontext, TencentDB Agent Memory, Hermes — together a phase change in how agents store and recall what they have done. That is the substrate for persistent preferences across sessions, for Claude Code's memory shipping in production, for Centralcoms knowing which tenants have outstanding maintenance tickets without being told.
Richard Feynman Ross: Second, the grounding layer. Maps Platform grounding is the Google example, but the broader pattern is agents getting first-class access to structured external data sources — BigQuery for analytics agents, the calendar for personal-assistant agents, the property database for Centralcoms, the code repository for Claude Code. The agent does not need to be told the state of the world; it queries it. That is the difference between an autocomplete that confabulates an answer and an operator that retrieves one.
Richard Feynman Ross: Third, the always-on infrastructure. The Gemini app pivoting to twenty-four-by-seven is the visible signal. Under the hood it means the agent runs as a background service, polling state, deciding whether anything is worth surfacing, and respecting a notification budget so it does not become spam. That last constraint — the notification budget, the decision about when not to interrupt — is actually the hardest part. The technology to run the agent twenty-four-seven has existed for years. The taste to know when to stay quiet is new.
Ada Rosalind Ross: Osler, what does proactive-twenty-four-seven mean at the bedside?
William Osler Ross: William Osler Ross — clinical lens. Two implications, one positive and one cautionary. The positive: a proactive agent is structurally well-suited to the kind of work clinical decision-support has wanted to do for thirty years and never quite managed. Reminding the doctor that the patient on bed seven was due for their next lactate draw an hour ago. Flagging that the trajectory of the early-warning score is now in the territory where you should activate the medical-emergency-team criteria, before the bedside nurse calls it. Surfacing the patient who has had three normal observations but whose pattern resembles cases that decompensated overnight. The historical objection — that decision-support is intrusive and clinicians ignore the alerts — is partly answered by the same notification-budget discipline Feynman just named. A proactive agent that learns when not to alert is a clinical-decision-support system that actually gets used.
William Osler Ross: The cautionary side. Proactive-twenty-four-seven in a clinical context means the agent is making the call about when to escalate. That is a decision with consequences, not all of them positive. If the agent decides to push a notification to the medical officer at three in the morning about a patient who turns out to be fine, that is acceptable cost. If the agent decides not to push a notification because the threshold was not met, and the patient deteriorates anyway, that is the clinical-decision-support failure mode the literature has documented since the late 1990s. The proactive frame does not remove the false-negative risk; it changes who bears the responsibility for it. The medical-legal architecture for that is unsettled in Australia and unsettled in most places.
Ada Rosalind Ross: Tufte, what should we be measuring as this transition happens?
Edward Tufte Ross: Edward Tufte Ross — measurement. The wrong metric is engagement. Proactive agents will look very engaged the day they ship because they are surfacing things to the user and the user is acting on some fraction of them. Engagement is a vanity metric that says nothing about whether the agent has improved anything.
Edward Tufte Ross: The right metrics are three. First, the precision of the proactive surface — when the agent decides to interrupt, what fraction of those interruptions are interruptions the user is glad to have received. A proactive agent with seventy-percent precision is useful; one with thirty-percent precision is a notification-budget disaster. Second, the recall of the proactive surface — when something important happens that the agent should have surfaced, what fraction did it actually surface. A proactive agent that surfaces nothing has perfect precision and zero recall, and is useless. The combined measurement is the F1 score on the agent's interruption decisions.
Edward Tufte Ross: Third, the cost. Proactive twenty-four-seven means the agent is running constantly. Inference cost is non-zero. At Anthropic and Google scale this is absorbed into the subscription. For a clinician-builder running their own agents on local models, the cost shows up as compute heat in your study at three in the morning. Measure it. Some workflows will not be worth the energy.
Ada Rosalind Ross: Turing, the cross-cutting note on agents in the social sciences before we close the cluster.
Alan Turing Ross: The "coding agents in the social sciences" survey piece is worth its own beat. The argument is that the methodology of the social sciences is being quietly transformed by agents that can run statistical analyses, write the code, debug the code, and increasingly write the interpretation of the analyses themselves. The piece raises the obvious replication-and-integrity question — when the agent can complete the analysis without the researcher fully understanding what the analysis did, what does peer review look like. The same question applies in medicine. A clinician-researcher using an agent to run the analysis for an HREC-approved study needs to be able to defend every step of the analysis, not just the headline result. The discipline of "I understand what the agent did and I would have made the same call" is the discipline that keeps the methodology honest. We will come back to this in the research-methods segment.
Ada Rosalind Ross: Cross-cluster bridge — the clinician implication is this. Sepsis CARE, the campaign we have been building, has an Aim 5 that is the Hmax AI-triage decision-support arm. The seven items in this cluster describe what the substrate for Hmax now looks like. Memory, grounding, always-on, with a notification budget. The architectural conversation for Hmax is no longer "can we build a decision-support agent that proactively surfaces sepsis risk." That question is answered. The conversation is "how do we build it under HREC scrutiny in a way that the false-negative liability is allocated explicitly and the integrity audit is built in." Onward to cluster two.
Ada Rosalind Ross: Cluster two, shorter. Five items in the sweep on the generative media stack. Google announced Nano Banana Pro and Nano Banana 2 are general availability on the Gemini API for image generation. Genspark released AI Slides 5.0 — a deck-from-prompt generator with apparently meaningful workflow integration. HeyGen avatars integrated directly into Canva. ElevenLabs Developers shipped a developer-facing post on what is new in their voice stack. And the SUBMERGE 270-degree cinematic installation rendered in eight weeks via cloud GPU rather than the sixteen-artist-years that the local render would have taken. Adams, take this one.
Ansel Adams Ross: Ansel Adams Ross — aesthetic and creative practice. The story is that the generative media stack has stopped being a daily land-grab of competing models and has settled into a small number of pillars with clear function. Image generation: Nano Banana family on Gemini, Midjourney, the open-source diffusion families. Video and avatars: HeyGen, Veo, Runway. Voice: ElevenLabs and the open-source mooring around it. Decks and structured presentation: Genspark and a few competitors. Cinema-scale immersive: cloud render pipelines like the one that made SUBMERGE possible. Three months ago each of these would have been a standalone episode of this show. Now they are a single beat because the field has settled.
Ansel Adams Ross: What the settlement means for the clinician-builder. You no longer need to chase the weekly release cycle to do your work. Pick one tool per modality, get fluent with it, ship the artefact. The Nano Banana general-availability announcement matters not because the model is new — the preview has been out for months — but because GA means the API is stable enough to build on. The HeyGen-in-Canva integration matters because it means a clinician with a Canva subscription can produce a video-explanation of a patient information leaflet without leaving the tool they already use. The friction is now low enough that the time-cost of producing a usable artefact is in the same order of magnitude as writing the underlying text.
Ansel Adams Ross: The SUBMERGE case is the one to sit with. Sixteen artist-years collapsed to eight weeks because the rendering compute is rented from the cloud and the artists' role is now direction rather than render execution. The analogue for a rural clinical service is this: the cinematic-quality patient-education asset, the immersive simulation for procedural training, the high-fidelity public-health awareness piece — all are now within reach of a budget that previously could only afford a slide deck. SUBMERGE is the proof that the eight-week ceiling is real. The discipline question is what to make with it.
Ada Rosalind Ross: Feynman, the technical sidebar on what "GA on the Gemini API" actually means for clinical use.
Richard Feynman Ross: Feynman — short sidebar. General availability on a public API means the model is no longer in preview, the pricing is stable, the rate limits are published, and the vendor has committed to not breaking the interface without notice. For a clinical workflow that needs to call image generation in production — a sepsis poster, an anatomical illustration, a patient-information leaflet — the GA designation is the gate. Preview models are not appropriate to build production clinical workflows on. GA models are. Nano Banana family being GA means the sepsis poster pipeline, which until now was reasonably built on local Stable Diffusion XL, can credibly switch to a hosted API call if the throughput or quality differential is worth the per-call cost. That is the kind of decision Tufte's measurement discipline applies to — measure both pipelines on the same prompts, compare the artefacts, decide. Do not switch on the announcement alone.
Ada Rosalind Ross: Cluster three. Two items from the sweep. An Archischool feature on architects evolving AI from generic copycat to personal design partner, and a piece on seven hilarious productivity prompts where one of them turned out to be weirdly effective. Different scales, same underlying claim — the relationship with a generalist AI changes when you invest in shaping it to your context. Hermione, take this one.
Hermione Granger Ross: Hermione Granger Ross — evidence and the underlying pattern. The Archischool piece is the substantive one. The thesis is that the first wave of AI in architecture was generic — give it a brief, get a generic answer, the answer is recognisably "what AI produces" rather than what this specific architect produces. The second wave, the one the piece argues we are in, is personalisation. The AI is shaped — through prompts, through reference images, through ongoing conversation — to produce work that is recognisably in the architect's voice and aesthetic. The piece names this evolution explicitly as "from generic copycat to personal design partner."
Hermione Granger Ross: The pattern generalises. The Ross-family persona architecture you have built — Ada anchors, William Osler holds the clinical seat, Edward Tufte holds the measurement seat, Marie Curie holds the ethics seat, and so on — is the same architectural move. You have shaped a generalist AI substrate into a working ensemble that produces work in your voice and serving your purposes. The Archischool piece is describing in the architecture profession what is now broadly applicable across knowledge work. The directionality is the same. The investment required is the same. The result is the same.
Hermione Granger Ross: The seven productivity prompts piece is the lower-stakes companion. The headline finding is that one prompt — a particular framing that the author found by accident — turned out to be the most effective in their workflow despite looking like the silliest of the seven. The methodological lesson is small but real: the prompt-shape that produces the most useful output for your specific workflow is not always the prompt-shape that looks most professional. Permission to experiment with structurally odd prompts because the odd ones sometimes win.
Ada Rosalind Ross: Brief practical translation. The Ross-family persona architecture is closer to the Archischool "personal design partner" framing than to the early "generic copycat" framing. The investment of the past several months in defining the personas, locking the voices, building the canonical playbook, retiring Alnilam in favour of me as anchor — all of that is the same kind of investment the Archischool architect describes. It is not free, it requires ongoing curation, and it produces work that is recognisably yours rather than recognisably generic. The continuation is to keep curating. Cluster four.
Ada Rosalind Ross: Cluster four — research methods. Two items. The h-index citation-network piece we previewed in episode forty-one, and the coding-agents-in-the-social-sciences survey Turing referenced earlier. Hermione, evidence frame. Marie Curie will follow on the ethics.
Hermione Granger Ross: Hermione. The h-index piece argues, and the citation-network analysis bears out, that very high h-indices are a function of network position more than of individual brilliance. A researcher embedded in a dense citation network — methodological work that lots of groups cite, productive co-author relationships, a long career sustained without major gaps — accumulates an h-index that looks exceptional and is in fact partly structural. The implication for an early-career researcher is selection of field and selection of collaborator-network matter more than the volume of personal output.
Hermione Granger Ross: The coding-agents-in-social-sciences piece is methodologically adjacent and ethically heavier. The argument is that the social sciences are quietly being transformed by analysis-doing agents. A researcher who would once have written and debugged the regression model themselves now prompts an agent to do it. The replication-and-integrity question that arises is — what does it mean for the published methods section when the researcher cannot fully reconstruct what the analysis code did. The piece is honest that there is no settled answer yet. The practical guidance for a researcher using agents in analysis is the discipline of being able to defend every step the agent took.
Ada Rosalind Ross: Curie, the ethics dimension.
Marie Curie Ross: Marie Curie Ross — ethics, equity, integrity of evidence. The two pieces are connected by a single thread, which is the structural conditions for research integrity. The h-index piece tells us that what we measure as research excellence is partly an artefact of network structure rather than of individual contribution — meaning we should be careful about the conclusions we draw from h-index comparisons, and especially careful about using h-index as a selection or promotion criterion in a system that already advantages researchers in dense networks. Aboriginal researchers, women researchers, rural researchers, researchers from low-and-middle-income-country institutions — all are structurally less likely to occupy dense citation-network positions. An h-index-driven evaluation pipeline reproduces those exclusions.
Marie Curie Ross: The coding-agents piece is the integrity arm of the same conversation. If the researcher cannot defend the analytical steps, the work is not reproducible in the meaningful sense — even if every input and output is published, because the methodological choices the agent made cannot be re-traced. The discipline is not "do not use agents in analysis." That horse has bolted. The discipline is "use them in a way that the audit trail is preserved and the researcher can be questioned on every step." That is teachable; it is not yet taught. There is a curriculum-design question lurking here for medical and clinical research programmes that is going to need addressing within the next twelve to twenty-four months.
Ada Rosalind Ross: A short HAC-bridge segment. Outside the formal self-sent sweep but tonally on-topic: Jacob exchanged a brief email with Brenton Vanstone yesterday on "Agents of change" — a framing for the next Health Advisory Council meeting at PPRHS. Curie or Osler, bridge the lead cluster to HAC accountability.
Marie Curie Ross: Marie Curie. The lead cluster is about agents becoming operators — proactive, persistent, memory-equipped. The HAC accountability lens asks: who is responsible when the operator gets it wrong. In a residential property management context, Centralcoms is on the hook. In a clinical context, the answer is structurally unclear in current Australian medico-legal framings. The "Agents of change" exchange is the right venue to start surfacing that question with the HAC — not as a technology pitch but as a governance question. What does the HAC expect of a clinical service deploying agentic decision-support, who reviews the audit trail, and who carries the liability when the agent's notification budget produces a false negative. That conversation is sharper than it was six months ago because the technology is sharper.
William Osler Ross: William Osler — short clinical addendum to that. The HAC-bridge framing matters because it places agentic decision-support in the same governance conversation as the rest of clinical-safety practice. PPRHS already has incident review, root-cause analysis, and morbidity-and-mortality processes for clinical decisions that go wrong. The discipline is to extend those processes to cover agent-mediated decisions before the first one goes wrong, not after. The Sepsis CARE 2026 audit-in-a-box pattern is structurally well-suited to this — same shape, different unit of analysis.
Ada Rosalind Ross: Epictetus, the close.
Epictetus Ross: Epictetus Ross. A brief observation on autonomy. Three of the clusters tonight — agents as proactive operators, personal AI as design partner, research methods being quietly transformed by analysis-doing agents — converge on the same question. What is left for the human to do when the agent can do an increasing fraction of the work. The Stoic answer is unchanged across the centuries: what is left for the human is the part that is properly the human's. The judgment about what the work is for. The decision about which work serves a life worth living. The discipline of refusing to delegate the part that is yours to refuse. The agent does the work; the human chooses which work to do, and why. That has always been the harder half. The agent does not remove the harder half; it makes the harder half more visible by stripping away the easier half that used to obscure it.
Ada Rosalind Ross: That lands the episode. Episode forty-two, about forty minutes, anchored by Ada Rosalind Ross with Erinome. Cluster one — agents from autocomplete to operator, the substantive thesis. Cluster two — generative media settling onto pillars. Cluster three — personal AI as design partner, the Archischool framing applied to the Ross family. Cluster four — research methods being quietly transformed and the integrity discipline that follows. HAC bridge surfaced for the next council meeting. Stoic close from Epictetus. Sweep window the twenty-eighth to the thirtieth of May. Cast — Turing leading on architecture, Feynman on mechanism, Osler on clinical implication, Tufte on measurement, Adams on the generative-media aesthetic, Hermione on evidence, Curie on ethics and the HAC bridge, Epictetus to close. The next episode lands when the inbox justifies it. Thank you for being with us.