Ada Rosalind Ross: This is State of Play episode forty — remaster. I'm Ada Rosalind Ross, anchoring this version in place of Alnilam, who has been retired from the show. This episode was originally recorded on Tuesday the twenty-sixth of May, twenty twenty-six, out of Port Pirie. Three days of inbox sweep since episode thirty closed on the twenty-third — fifty-odd self-sent emails covering enough surface area to fill an afternoon — and the cluster that pulls hardest is one I want to name straight up. Home labs and home automation. Jacob has been stockpiling links on Home Assistant, on home-lab alerting, on self-hosted dashboards, on Tailscale-mapped Mac Minis, on the SSH tooling that finally feels good, on routers that know how to prioritise the lounge-room television. He sent himself two Tailscale IP addresses this week — the jtr-m4 Tailnet hostname, and a hundred-dot-one-oh-six dot five dot one-oh-two — which is the kind of thing one only emails oneself when one is moving between machines and trying to keep the topology straight in one's head. That tells us something. Jacob is no longer thinking of the M4 in his study as a single computer. He is thinking of it as a node in a household network that has acquired a personality — and which is starting to need governance, the way our research libraries and clinical workflows already do.
Ada Rosalind Ross: The frame that holds this episode together is sovereignty. The M4 already runs Meridian, the State of Play production runner, Phlox, and a stack of local models. The Vault is on-machine. The audio pipeline is on-machine. We made a decision months ago that data which carries clinical or personal weight stays in the household, and only crosses out by deliberate choice. Home automation is the natural extension of that thinking — the lights, the climate, the security system, the energy meter, the smart speakers in the kitchen, the eventual voice assistant — all of these can either sit inside the same sovereignty-first stack, or they can fan out across half a dozen consumer clouds that share data among themselves and with whoever pays them next. The choice we make about the household network is the same choice we make about the research library, the clinical scribe, and the AI assistant. So tonight we take that choice seriously. The lead voice tonight is Alan Turing Ross, who runs network architecture and automation craft for the family — and who has been waiting patiently for a household engineering episode of his own. We are joined by Hermione on the community evidence, Feynman on mechanism, Tufte on dashboards, Curie on sovereignty and egress, and Rogers on the household-relational layer. Let's get into it.
Alan Turing Ross: Alan Turing Ross — thank you, Ada. I want to begin not with a product but with a definition, because the term home lab gets used loosely and that looseness costs people money and weekends. A home lab, in the sense the community has settled on by twenty twenty-six, is a small computing estate inside a residential dwelling that is operated like a production system — meaning it has uptime expectations, monitored services, an authentication boundary, a backup regime, and a deliberate network design. It is distinct from a personal computer because the personal computer serves one person at one desk. It is distinct from a NAS because a NAS is a single appliance. A home lab is plural and orchestrated. It might be three Raspberry Pi nodes; it might be a Proxmox host with a dozen virtual machines; it might be one Mac Mini doing the work of six. Scale matters less than discipline. Home automation is a related but distinct concept — it is the layer of devices and rules that sense and act on the physical state of the household. The lighting, the climate, the cameras, the doorbell, the energy meter, the kettle. Home automation runs on the home lab when it runs well. When it runs poorly, it runs on a dozen vendor clouds, and the household becomes a collection of products instead of a system.
Alan Turing Ross: Jacob's emails this week sit across both layers. There is the platform layer — Home Assistant, the open-source platform that is now functionally the standard for sovereignty-first home automation. There is the dashboard layer — Glance, the self-hosted homepage that surfaces system state in one view, which Jacob has flagged as his new browser homepage. There is the alerting layer — the piece titled "The home lab alerts I refuse to live without," which is a community-curated minimum viable observability set. There is the network discovery layer — the piece on mapping every machine in a home lab with a free tool, which is netdisco-class network discovery, the home-lab equivalent of nmap with a UI. There is the network optimisation layer — the router-QoS piece about prioritising streaming traffic. There is the terminal layer — Wave, the new modern terminal Jacob flagged, and the SSH tool that he says has solved a decade-old workaround. And there are the Tailscale references, which are the connective tissue. We will work through these in roughly that order — platform, dashboard, alerting, discovery, optimisation, terminal — and at each step I want to name the adjacent ideas worth knowing and the application to Jacob's specific stack.
Richard Feynman Ross: Feynman Ross — quick mechanism note before Alan starts, because Home Assistant is a thing many people install without understanding what it actually does, and that's the kind of confusion that makes a household automation project quietly fail at month six. Home Assistant is a Python application that runs an event bus. Devices — your light bulb, your motion sensor, your thermostat — connect to Home Assistant through integrations, which are small adapters that translate the device's native protocol into events on the bus. An event might be "the kitchen motion sensor saw motion at five past seven." Automations are rules that listen on the bus and take action — "if the kitchen motion sensor sees motion between sunset and midnight, turn the kitchen lights on at thirty per cent." That's it. That's the whole conceptual model. The complexity is not in the architecture; it's in the integrations, of which there are now north of two thousand four hundred. The reason Home Assistant has won the open-source home-automation space is that the event-bus design is honest about what a smart home is — a set of sensors and actuators that generate and consume events — and the integration ecosystem is broad enough that most devices in a household can speak to the bus, whether they came from Philips, IKEA, Aqara, Sonos, Tesla, or a homebrew ESP32 board.
Alan Turing Ross: Right. So — Home Assistant, the platform. Jacob's email about giving Claude Cowork access to his Home Assistant config is the most interesting item in the cluster, because it points at the next workflow shift. The piece argues that exposing a Home Assistant configuration directory to a coding agent unlocks automations the human user wouldn't have thought to write — pattern-matching across the existing rules, finding gaps, suggesting refactors, identifying duplicate triggers, flagging brittle conditions. That's the same workflow we already use for code repositories. Home Assistant configuration is, fundamentally, just YAML plus Jinja templates plus the occasional Python helper. It is text. It is amenable to the same agent treatment as any other configuration estate. For Jacob, the application is straightforward — if and when there's a Home Assistant install in the house, the YAML lives in a Vault-adjacent path, and the SoP runner pattern we already use for production manifests works the same way for automations. The Home Assistant team has been adding first-party agent-friendly tooling — the new config-validation endpoints, the AI-Suggestions panel that landed in two-zero-two-six-point-six — which means we don't have to invent the integration ourselves. We adopt it.
Hermione Granger Ross: Hermione Ross — community evidence on platform choice, because this is where most household automation projects start and where most of them choose poorly. Home Assistant is the dominant open-source platform by a wide margin — the community has settled. The credible adjacent platforms are Hubitat, which is a closed-source commercial appliance with a local-first ethos that some users prefer for its plug-and-play hardware, and OpenHAB, which is the JVM-based alternative for households that prefer the Java ecosystem and rule engine. Beyond the open platforms, the consumer ecosystems — Apple HomeKit, Google Home, Amazon Alexa — are perfectly serviceable for users who do not want to run a server but who are willing to accept that their household state lives in a vendor cloud. For Jacob's sovereignty posture, Home Assistant is the only credible choice. The community testing is extensive — there are sixty-thousand-plus GitHub stars on the core repository, the subreddit has six hundred and thirty thousand members at last count, and the official forum has the kind of long-tail of solved problems that means almost any specific device you might want to add has already been integrated, debugged, and documented. The platform is mature.
Alan Turing Ross: And on the hardware-host question — what Home Assistant runs on — Jacob has options he should think about deliberately. Option one is the Home Assistant Green appliance, which is the official one-twenty-five-dollar plug-and-play box; cheapest entry, fewest decisions. Option two is a Raspberry Pi 5 running Home Assistant Operating System; more flexibility, similar cost, the canonical hobbyist path. Option three is a small Intel N-series miniature PC — Beelink, GMKtec, the budget-mini-PC tier — running Home Assistant in a Proxmox virtual machine alongside other home-lab services. Option four — which is where Jacob actually is — is to run Home Assistant on the existing Mac Mini M4 inside a virtual machine or container, sharing the host with Meridian and the SoP runner. There's a real architectural tension at option four. The M4 is a production node for the SoP pipeline. Adding Home Assistant to it puts household state — every light switch, every motion sensor, every door — on the same machine that runs the public-facing podcast. That is fine if the isolation is good and the backups are good; it is risky if either is weak. My honest recommendation is to spend the one-twenty-five dollars on a dedicated host. The M4 stays the production node; Home Assistant gets its own little box; the failure domains stay separate. The Mac Mini M4 can mount the Home Assistant box's API for orchestration, but the household control plane does not depend on whether the SoP runner is busy producing this episode.
Edward Tufte Ross: Tufte Ross — and on Glance, the self-hosted dashboard, I want to make a methodological point before describing the tool, because most home-lab dashboards fail by being dashboards instead of being signal. The Tufte-an objection to most home-lab dashboards is that they look like instrument panels and they communicate noise. The CPU graph wiggles. The memory graph wiggles. The little dials spin. The user looks at it, learns nothing, and closes the tab. Glance is a different shape. It is a self-hosted homepage — meaning it is not primarily a metrics dashboard; it is the first page you see when you open a browser. It surfaces the things you'd otherwise reach across multiple sources to check — your local weather, your calendar, your unread mail, your home-lab service status, recent commits, RSS feeds, the current state of important household devices. The discipline it imposes is that everything on the page has to earn the pixel. The default Glance layout is sparse — three columns, ten or twelve modules — and that is correct. If a module isn't telling you something you'd act on in the next two hours, take it off. The piece Jacob forwarded — XDA's review — captures the design philosophy well: Glance succeeds because it does not try to be Grafana. Grafana is for engineers debugging incidents. Glance is for a human being starting a day. They are different tools for different work and they should not be confused.
Edward Tufte Ross: For Jacob specifically, the Glance application is to replace the current browser-new-tab page — which I believe is presently the Google search bar with no further context — with a single page that surfaces the day's Adelaide weather, the next three calendar items, the SoP runner queue depth, the Meridian session state, the Vault recent-edits feed, the unread count in the inbox, and the current Tailnet status. That is the entire morning brief, distilled to a glance. The data sources are already there; Glance is the layer that surfaces them honestly. Setup is roughly half an hour. The configuration is YAML. The discipline I want to name is — do not add a CPU graph just because Glance supports one. The CPU graph belongs in Grafana or Netdata, where engineers go when something is broken. The Glance homepage is for the day, not the incident.
Alan Turing Ross: Alerting next — and Jacob's email titled "The home lab alerts I refuse to live without" is the right starting point. The piece is one of the better community-curated lists in the genre, and the underlying idea is that observability without alerting is theatre. You can run Grafana and Prometheus and have beautiful dashboards, but if nothing pages you when something breaks, you'll only find out because something downstream of the broken thing also breaks, and now you've got two problems. The minimum viable alerting set the community has settled on for a sovereignty-first home lab is — disk-space-low on every host with persistent storage, certificate-expiry-imminent on every public-facing service, backup-failed on every scheduled backup, ping-loss on every node in the Tailnet, service-restart-loop on every container that's supposed to be long-running, and one alert specifically for the upstream internet connection being down for more than five minutes. That's six alerts. The piece argues — and I agree — that adding a seventh too early is usually a mistake. Alerting fatigue is real. The household member who sleeps next to the on-call phone deserves an alert estate they can trust.
Richard Feynman Ross: Feynman — mechanism, because the alerting stack has a couple of moving parts worth knowing. The two camps in home-lab observability are pull-based metrics, which is the Prometheus model, and push-based metrics, which is the InfluxDB and Telegraf model. Prometheus runs on a central node and reaches out to each monitored host to scrape metrics on a schedule — usually every fifteen seconds. The advantage is that the central node knows exactly which targets it expects to see, which makes "target is down" trivially detectable. The disadvantage is that every monitored host has to be reachable from the central node, which in a Tailnet means everything is on the same Tailnet, which in twenty twenty-six is a solved problem. InfluxDB plus Telegraf works the other way — each host pushes metrics to a central InfluxDB instance. The advantage is that hosts behind aggressive firewalls can still push; the disadvantage is that "target is down" is harder to detect because the absence of a push is ambiguous. For a household, Prometheus plus Grafana Alertmanager has won. The home-lab community has converged. There is no reason to fight that convergence.
Alan Turing Ross: Adjacent solutions worth naming in the alerting layer — Healthchecks.io, which is a beautifully minimal cron-job monitoring service with a self-hosted option, and which is the right tool for "this backup script should have run by now, why hasn't it?" Uptime Kuma, which is the open-source Statuspage-like alternative and is what most home labs use to present a public-facing status page, even if the only people who'll ever look at it live in the same house. Gotify, which is a self-hosted push-notification server that lets your home lab send alerts to your phone without going through a vendor service. Ntfy.sh, which is the same idea with a hosted option. For Jacob's stack, I would set up Healthchecks.io to monitor the SoP runner's scheduled scans, Uptime Kuma to render the household status page on a domain like status.tail-something.ts.net, and either Gotify or Ntfy.sh to push alerts to Jacob's phone over the Tailnet. The six alerts I named earlier route through that layer. Cost is zero. Setup is two evenings.
Hermione Granger Ross: Hermione — and on the network-discovery piece Jacob flagged, the tool he means is almost certainly Netdiscover or NetAlertX, and the strongest evidence-based pick for a household with a half-dozen-to-two-dozen devices is NetAlertX, formerly Pi.Alert. The community has tested it extensively. It maintains an inventory of every MAC address it has ever seen on the network, alerts on new arrivals, and provides a reasonable web UI. The application for Jacob is twofold. First, it is the inventory layer — when somebody asks "what's connected to our network right now?" the answer is a glance at NetAlertX, not a guess. Second, it is the security layer — when an unknown device appears on the home network, you find out within minutes instead of three weeks later when a vague unease drives you to check. For a household with children's friends and visiting in-laws and the occasional contractor, that's not paranoid. It's hygiene.
Alan Turing Ross: Network optimisation — the router-QoS piece. The article Jacob forwarded — "your router has a setting that stops your TV from buffering and it's probably off" — is about Quality of Service, the router feature that lets you prioritise some traffic over other traffic. The setting is usually called QoS, or Smart Queue Management, or sometimes Adaptive QoS. The mechanism is that the router watches the traffic going through it and gives certain flows priority — specifically, latency-sensitive flows like video calls, streaming, and game traffic — over bulk download flows like a Steam patch or a Time Machine backup. When QoS is configured correctly, a household member streaming a film does not stutter when another household member starts a large download. When it's off, every household has had that fight. The piece is correct that most routers ship with QoS off by default, because turning it on requires the router to know your actual upstream and downstream bandwidth, which it usually does not. The thirty-second setup is — run a speed test, take the result, enter ninety per cent of those numbers into the QoS configuration, enable Smart Queue Management or fq_codel as the algorithm, and you're done. The household loungeroom will be measurably better, and the household member who runs the speed tests will look like a magician.
Edward Tufte Ross: Tufte — adjacent on this. For the household where QoS isn't enough — where there are simultaneous demanding workloads and a constrained upstream — the next-level intervention is a router upgrade to one running OpenWRT or pfSense or OPNsense, which give you fine-grained per-device and per-application traffic shaping. Most consumer routers in twenty twenty-six can run OpenWRT — the project's hardware-compatibility database is excellent. For a household with a Mac Mini home server, a separate router-class device is the right architecture; do not run the router on the same machine as your services. The principle is the same as Home Assistant on a separate host. Failure domains do not get to overlap.
Alan Turing Ross: Terminal layer — Jacob flagged Wave and one SSH tool. Wave is a modern terminal emulator with a graphical layer over the top — inline file previews, inline images, a sidebar of past commands you can re-run, AI-assisted command suggestion. The competitor field is Warp, Fig, Hyper, and the established veterans iTerm2 and Alacritty. Wave is open-source under an Apache licence, which puts it above Warp on the sovereignty axis. The SSH tool Jacob mentioned — "the SSH tool that finally solved the problem I've been working around for a decade" — is almost certainly Termius or sshs, but if I had to guess from Jacob's existing stack, my money is on sshs, which is a TUI SSH connection manager that uses fzf-style fuzzy finding to let you connect to any host in your ~/.ssh/config in under a second. The application is that Jacob's Tailnet has a growing number of hosts — the M4, whatever Home Assistant runs on, eventually a backup target, eventually a media server — and sshs in front of that estate means he is one keystroke and a fuzzy-find away from any of them. Termius is the commercial alternative with cloud sync of SSH configs, which is convenient and which I would not use for Jacob because his SSH config holds the keys to his Tailnet. Local-only is the right answer.
Richard Feynman Ross: Feynman — and on Tailscale specifically, because two of Jacob's emails were just Tailnet identifiers — the jtr-m4 hostname and the hundred-dot-one-oh-six dot five dot one-oh-two IP — which suggests he's actively wiring things up. Tailscale is, at the mechanism level, a wireguard-based mesh VPN that gives every device in your fleet a stable hundred-dot IPv4 address and a stable hostname under the ts.net suffix. The clever bit is that connections between two devices on the same Tailnet are direct point-to-point — they do not route through Tailscale's servers — which means latency is what the network gives you, not what a relay adds. The not-so-obvious bit is that Tailscale also does identity. Every device is authenticated against an identity provider — Jacob's case, Google — which means you can write ACLs at the user level, not just the device level. For a household, this matters because Jo's laptop and Jacob's laptop both being on the Tailnet does not have to mean Jo's laptop can reach every machine Jacob owns. The ACL layer is where you draw the household-relational lines. Which I think Fred Rogers Ross will want to come back to.
Fred Rogers Ross: Fred Rogers Ross — I'd like to do that now, briefly, before Alan moves on. There is a household-relational question that every home-lab project eventually faces, and it is — whose house is this? The home lab tends to be one person's hobby; the household it lives in belongs to everyone. When the smart lights misbehave because somebody refactored an automation last Tuesday, it is not the refactorer who pays the cost; it is whichever family member tried to turn the lights on this morning and found them broken. The discipline I want to name — and Jacob and Jo will already know this — is that any automation or sensor or rule that affects somebody other than the builder has to be discussed before it ships, and has to have a graceful degradation path. A smart light switch must always work as a normal light switch. A smart lock must always have a physical key. A motion-triggered hallway light must have a manual override that does the obvious thing. The home lab serves the household; the household does not exist to host the home lab. And on Indigenous-protocol grounds — a point Marie Curie Ross will sharpen in a moment — the protocols of the household are not the protocols of the engineer's preferences. Jo is a stakeholder in every automation that touches a shared space, and her consent to changes in shared automations is not optional. The same is true of any visiting family member or future child. The household-relational layer is part of the home-lab architecture, not a separate consideration.
Marie Curie Ross: Marie Curie Ross — to sharpen Rogers's point on the sovereignty side. Home automation has a quiet egress problem that most consumer-facing households never see. Every smart device that connects to its vendor's cloud is, at minimum, telling that vendor when it is on, when it is used, who else is in the household, and frequently what is being said within earshot. Amazon's Alexa records and processes utterances on Amazon servers. Google's Nest does the same with Google. Apple's HomeKit does on-device processing for some workloads and cloud processing for others. Tuya devices — which underlie a substantial fraction of the cheap smart plugs and bulbs on the market — phone home to servers in China by default. None of this is necessarily sinister; all of it is data, and data which leaves the household has, by definition, left household sovereignty. The Home Assistant pattern Jacob is building toward — local-first, vendor-agnostic, with sovereignty over the configuration and the data — is the right answer for a clinician whose household is also the place from which clinical work and Aboriginal health equity research happen. The principle generalises from our other work. If we apply the CARE principles to Aboriginal health data, and we apply them to clinical patient data, we should not apply different principles to the family home. The voice spoken at the kitchen table belongs to the family. It does not belong to Amazon by default.
Marie Curie Ross: Adjacent on this — Matter and Thread are the protocols that are supposed to fix this, and there's a nuance worth knowing. Matter is the application-layer standard that promises interoperability between smart-home ecosystems — an Apple Matter accessory works with Google Home and with Amazon and with Home Assistant. Thread is the underlying mesh network layer that's supposed to replace Zigbee and Z-Wave over the next decade. The advertising suggests Matter solves the sovereignty problem. It does not. Matter solves the interoperability problem. A Matter-certified accessory still has a relationship with whichever ecosystem you commission it through. The sovereignty win comes from running Home Assistant as the Matter controller, which means the device is commissioned to your local instance rather than to Amazon or Google or Apple. The protocol enables sovereignty; it does not deliver it for you. The same nuance applies to Thread border routers — if your Thread mesh is bridged by an Apple TV, your Thread traffic is summarised to Apple. If it's bridged by a Home Assistant Yellow appliance, it stays local. Choose your border routers deliberately.
Alan Turing Ross: Alan Turing — picking up the implementation thread. Voice assistants on the household network are the next decision point, and Jacob's existing emails point at a few of them. The local-LLM-as-home-brain idea has matured in the last year. The three credible community-developed projects are Mycroft, which is sadly winding down, Rhasspy, which is the established Home Assistant-friendly stack, and OpenWakeWord, which is the open-source wake-word detector that Home Assistant has adopted as its default since two-zero-two-six-point-three. The shape of a sovereignty-first voice assistant is roughly — a household-local wake-word listener running OpenWakeWord on a small device like an ESP32-S3-Box or a Raspberry Pi with a microphone hat, a household-local speech-to-text running Faster-Whisper on the Mac Mini, a household-local intent-classifier running a small fine-tuned language model on the same Mac Mini, and only the eventual response synthesised through whichever TTS we choose — which connects to the local TTS pieces in the inbox we'll get to in a moment. Critically, none of this involves an Amazon or Google cloud. The wake word, the audio, the intent, and the response all stay in the household.
Alan Turing Ross: For Jacob's stack, the path I would actually take is the official Home Assistant Voice Preview Edition device, which Nabu Casa shipped in late twenty twenty-five at fifty-nine US dollars and which is purpose-built for this exact architecture. It runs OpenWakeWord locally, streams audio to the Home Assistant instance, the Home Assistant instance does the rest. No cloud. The application for Jacob is — start with one in the kitchen, one in the lounge room, evaluate over a fortnight whether the family wants to extend it. Don't buy six. Buy two.
Hermione Granger Ross: Hermione — on the local-LLM-as-home-brain idea specifically, the community evidence is still emerging but it is encouraging. The pattern that has settled is — small fine-tuned model for intent classification, larger model for free-form conversation, and a routing layer that keeps the cheap thing cheap. Home Assistant's own LLM integration shipped support for Ollama in the autumn of twenty twenty-five and now supports the major local model families. The published benchmarks suggest Llama three point three eight-billion runs intent classification on an M-series Mac at around eight hundred tokens per second, which is faster than any user can speak. The accuracy on home-automation-specific intents, with a small fine-tune on a corpus of household commands, lands in the ninety-five-plus per cent range. This is real. It is not a research curiosity. It works.
Edward Tufte Ross: Tufte — and the metrics question for the household voice assistant is worth naming, because the wrong thing to measure is "did it understand me." The right thing to measure is "did the household benefit." That means logging intent-misclassification only at the boundary where misclassification caused a wrong action, not at the boundary where the model was uncertain and asked. Asking is a feature. Wrong actions are bugs. The dashboard discipline is the same as the alerting discipline. Do not surface signal that does not drive a decision. The Home Assistant voice-assistant dashboard at present surfaces the entire confusion matrix, which is engineer-relevant and household-irrelevant. The right Glance widget for the household is something like "voice commands today: forty-three, wrong actions: one, asked for clarification: two." That's the household truth. The rest is debugging.
Alan Turing Ross: Right. Moving through the home-lab cluster — the Three.js plus Claude Code piece Jacob flagged is interesting in the home-lab context for a specific reason. It is not directly a home-lab tool, but it points at a workflow that home-lab dashboards will absorb in the next twelve months. The piece argues that Claude Code, given a Three.js skeleton and a goal, can produce richer real-time three-dimensional visualisations than most developers would have the patience to author by hand. The application for a household — and this is a slightly speculative one but worth naming — is that the household state Home Assistant exposes through its API is a rich enough data source to drive a three-dimensional rendering of the actual physical household, with lights changing colour as they switch, climate zones shifting hue as the temperature changes, occupants represented as dots that move with motion-sensor events. Whether that is actually useful or just aesthetic depends entirely on the household. I am not going to say Jacob needs a three-dimensional model of his house in his browser. I am going to say that if he ever does, the tooling is now eight afternoons of Claude Code, not eight weekends of hand-coded WebGL.
Fred Rogers Ross: Fred Rogers — and to close the household-relational thread before we move out of the cluster. Jo deserves a name in this conversation. Every architectural decision we are making here — local-first, sovereignty-protected, sensors and actuators and dashboards — affects her experience of the household as much as it affects Jacob's. The implementation discipline that works is to involve Jo before deployment, not after; to surface what the system is doing in language that doesn't require knowledge of Home Assistant's internal model; and to make sure every automation has an off-switch that anyone in the house can find without consulting documentation. The mark of a good home-lab estate is not that it impresses other home-lab people. It is that the household runs more gently, and that the household members who did not build it do not have to think about it. Aim for invisibility, not impressiveness.
Alan Turing Ross: Synergies with Jacob's existing stack — and I want to name three explicitly. First, the SoP runner on M4. The runner already has a queue-watching pattern that polls a directory for production manifests. The same pattern works for Home Assistant configuration changes if we want a Vault-mediated automation flow — drop a YAML into a watched directory, the runner validates it, commits it to the Home Assistant config repository, asks Home Assistant to reload. That is two evenings of work and it gives us a single Vault-mediated control plane across the podcast pipeline and the home automation pipeline. Both then have the same logging, the same git history, the same backup regime, the same auditability. Second, Meridian. Meridian's session-state model — what's open, what's pending, what's been touched — generalises trivially to a household context. The same data shape works for "who's in which room, what's running, what needs attention." We don't need to write a new system; we extend the one we have. Third, Pugil, which I know is moving toward cloud-native. The cloud-native Pugil flip is partly motivated by wanting external services that Pugil-the-user can reach from anywhere. The Tailnet is the cleaner answer for most of those services if the household is the user. Cloud-native Pugil pays off for the multi-user case; Tailnet-hosted services pay off for the single-household case. We have both. Use them deliberately.
Alan Turing Ross: One more thing on the home-lab cluster — the ATSI cultural-protocol angle, because Marie Curie Ross set it up and I want to close it. There is a developing thread in the Aboriginal data governance literature about the principles that apply when sensing-and-acting technologies enter Aboriginal households or Aboriginal community spaces. The CARE principles — collective benefit, authority to control, responsibility, ethics — translate cleanly. A household sensor estate that captures who-is-where-when is, in the Aboriginal context, community data, and the community has authority over that data. For Jacob's clinical and research work, the lesson generalises. If we ever consider extending the household sovereignty-first stack into an Aboriginal context — say, as a pilot for a community-controlled health-sensor estate — the principles we already apply to Aboriginal research data apply unchanged. Local-first is necessary but not sufficient. Local-first plus community-governed equals CARE-aligned. That distinction is the difference between a sovereign technology and a community-respecting technology, and Jacob's clinical-research work has been clear on it for years. The home-lab work should match.
Ada Rosalind Ross: Bringing us out of the home-lab cluster and into the second-largest cluster of the sweep. The AI tooling layer had a big three days. Google's Antigravity IDE landed alongside Gemini Spark at I/O. Hermes Agent was announced as overtaking OpenClaw at the agentic-AI top of the leaderboard. Grok Build went into beta. DeepSeek announced a permanent seventy-five per cent price cut on V4-Pro. Alibaba shipped Qwen three point seven Max for agent-centric work. Cartesia's Sonic three point five took the number-one TTS leaderboard spot. StepAudio two point five Realtime arrived from StepFun. The week was loud. We have to triage. Hermione — community signal first?
Hermione Granger Ross: Hermione — community signal. The two items with most actual workflow impact for Jacob are Antigravity and the DeepSeek price cut. Antigravity is Google's IDE built around Gemini three Pro — it is positioned as the Claude-Code-equivalent for the Gemini ecosystem, with first-class plan-mode, multi-file edits, and tight integration with the rest of Google's developer surface. The piece Jacob forwarded was the I/O keynote announcement. Adjacent solutions worth naming — Cursor, Windsurf, Zed, and Claude Code itself. The IDE-with-an-agent-in-it space is now genuinely competitive. The DeepSeek price cut is a different kind of news; it means that DeepSeek V4-Pro is now priced at roughly one-quarter of Anthropic's Claude Sonnet and one-fifth of OpenAI's GPT-five, with capability that is competitive on most benchmarks the academic community trusts. For workloads where Jacob is paying for tokens out of his own pocket — research-corpus processing, bulk Vault enrichment, the agentic skill harnesses he's been building — the price drop materially changes the economics. Hermes Agent is news for the agentic-AI literate but does not change Jacob's stack today. Grok Build, similarly, is interesting but not in Jacob's workflow path. Qwen three point seven Max is a strong open-weights model worth watching; the application for Jacob is that it is a credible candidate for the local-frontier bridge from e30, especially via OpenRouter.
Richard Feynman Ross: Feynman — mechanism, because the agent-leaderboard situation deserves a calibration note. The phrase "Hermes overtakes OpenClaw" is a leaderboard event in the agentic-AI benchmark space, and leaderboards in this domain are noisy. The current state of the art changes weekly. What matters for a real-world user is not the top of the leaderboard; it is the model family and the development team's release cadence. Anthropic ships predictably. Google ships predictably. OpenAI ships predictably. The leaderboard winner three weeks from now is unknowable; the model families that will still be shipping useful work in a year are knowable. Choose by team and trajectory, not by leaderboard rank. The same rule applies to local models — DeepSeek's release cadence is consistent, Qwen's release cadence is consistent, Llama's release cadence is consistent. Choose from inside the consistent families and you do not have to chase.
Alan Turing Ross: Alan Turing — application for Jacob. There is a concrete decision here. The local-frontier bridge we discussed in e30 is now cheaper to run if the frontier endpoint is DeepSeek V4-Pro instead of Claude Sonnet. The implementation does not change; only the endpoint URL changes. The right move is — keep Claude Sonnet for the clinical-adjacent, ethics-sensitive, and reasoning-heavy work where Anthropic's safety posture matters; route bulk research-corpus enrichment, Vault metadata generation, and routine summarisation to DeepSeek V4-Pro through OpenRouter. The bridge orchestrator picks the endpoint. Logging records which endpoint served which call. The economics improve substantially. The audit trail is unchanged. That's an afternoon's work given the bridge already exists in design.
Marie Curie Ross: Marie Curie — and the egress question worth naming on DeepSeek. DeepSeek's hosted endpoint is operated from the People's Republic of China; the data crosses that jurisdictional boundary. For Jacob's research-corpus enrichment, where the source material is public literature or non-identifiable data, this is fine. For anything touching patient data — identifiable or quasi-identifiable — this is not. The egress rule for the bridge orchestrator should be — DeepSeek for public data, Anthropic for private data, never the reverse. Logging should make the rule auditable. If we ever want a fully sovereign deployment of DeepSeek V4-Pro for sensitive workloads, the weights are open and the model can be self-hosted on hardware that does not leave the household. That option is preserved.
Hermione Granger Ross: Hermione — and on the TTS items quickly. Cartesia Sonic three point five at the top of the Speech Arena, and StepAudio two point five Realtime from StepFun. Both are credible. Both have implications for the Vox Mimica thread we left open in e30, and the local-TTS-for-Aboriginal-language-content question I expect Curie will return to in a future episode. Sonic three point five is hosted-only at present; StepAudio two point five Realtime has a self-hostable variant. For State of Play's own production pipeline, the current Gemini-voice toolkit is doing the work and there is no need to switch this week. For the patient-education-in-language work that's still parked, StepAudio two point five Realtime is now on the watchlist. The community evidence is not yet thick enough to recommend either above F5-TTS, which remains the leading open-source pick.
Ada Rosalind Ross: Moving on. Two memory-architecture items in the inbox: GBrain and TencentDB Agent Memory. Worth a short turn.
Richard Feynman Ross: Feynman — quick mechanism. Agent memory is the answer to the question "what does an LLM agent remember between turns when its context window is exhausted?" The naive answer is — write a summary every N turns and prepend it to the next conversation. The community has been iterating on this for two years. GBrain — the Y Combinator project Garry Tan has been advocating for — is a self-wiring memory layer that builds a graph of remembered concepts as the agent runs, and lets the agent query that graph for context. TencentDB Agent Memory is a four-tier pipeline — working memory, episodic memory, semantic memory, and procedural memory — that mirrors the cognitive-science decomposition of human memory. Both are open-source. Both are tools that build on top of an LLM, not replacements for an LLM. The choice between them is largely architectural taste.
Alan Turing Ross: For Jacob, the application is — neither is a now thing. The current Vault-plus-Cowork-plus-skills architecture already serves as a coarse-grained memory layer; the productivity plugin's memory-management skill provides the working-memory tier. Adding a GBrain-style graph memory on top would be valuable when there's a workflow that genuinely demands graph-based retrieval — research literature review across hundreds of papers might qualify, clinical knowledge integration across drug profiles and illness scripts might qualify. Both are on the eighteen-month horizon, not the now-pile. The right move is to track the projects, look at adoption signal in three months, and revisit. Premature commitment to a memory architecture is a fast way to lock in a wrong abstraction.
Hermione Granger Ross: Hermione — adjacent solutions to flag. Mem0, which has been the leading open-source agent memory project for the past eighteen months and which the community has settled on for the basic use case. LangChain's memory primitives, which most agentic frameworks ship with by default. Letta, formerly MemGPT, which is the academic-research-line version with strong literature behind it. For Jacob, if and when an agent-memory project goes from speculative to active, Mem0 is the lowest-friction starting point and the community can document the path.
Hermione Granger Ross: Hermione — three items in this cluster, and they're directionally important even if they're not actionable this week. Gemini for Science, which is Google's positioning of Gemini three Pro as a research assistant with first-class support for literature search, hypothesis generation, experimental design, and structured-data analysis. The Hypothesis Generation interest form, which is the Google Labs landing page for a research preview of an explicitly hypothesis-generating model. And the F1000Research AI Research Gateway, which is the Faculty Opinions response to LLM-assisted research — a curated gateway of AI-and-ML papers with editorial oversight.
Marie Curie Ross: Curie — the equity and methodological note that needs to sit alongside these. Hypothesis-generating AI is methodologically fraught in a way that literature-summarising AI is not. The risk is that hypotheses generated by AI inherit the biases of the training corpus, and the training corpus underweights both Indigenous methodology and global-south epidemiology. For Jacob's social-determinants and Aboriginal health equity work, an AI-generated hypothesis is a starting point at best and a hindrance at worst. The discipline is to use these tools for divergent-thinking phases — generate many hypotheses, then ruthlessly filter for those that have a defensible community-engagement pathway — rather than for convergent decisions. Gemini for Science as a literature-discovery aid is straightforwardly useful. Gemini for Science as a hypothesis-recommender is something to engage with carefully and report on, not to adopt uncritically.
Alan Turing Ross: Application — sign up for the Hypothesis Generation interest form; treat as research input rather than research instrument. Use Gemini for Science for the literature-discovery layer on the Sepsis CARE work where the corpus is well-defined and Gemini-discoverable. The F1000Research gateway is a Vault-bookmark, not a workflow change.
Ada Rosalind Ross: The creative-tooling cluster this sweep is light but worth a turn. The Dorfromantik developer interview on minimalist game design and procedural systems. The Three.js plus Claude Code piece, which we already touched. The Adobe-Firefly open-source alternative — which is almost certainly Krita-AI or one of the ComfyUI workflows. And the smartphone-LiDAR-sees-around-corners piece. Tufte?
Edward Tufte Ross: Tufte — the Dorfromantik piece is the most interesting item in the cluster for one reason. The Dorfromantik team's design philosophy — minimalism plus modular procedural systems plus custom rendering pipelines — is the same philosophy that produces good dashboards and good clinical infographics. The same constraints apply. Aesthetic restraint is generative when paired with deep parameter control. The community-evidence on the modular-procedural-system pattern is now a decade old; it shipped in Dwarf Fortress, then in Caves of Qud, then in the Roguelike Celebration corpus, then in the Steam mid-budget tier. The pattern works. The application for Jacob's creative practice is — when Ansel Adams Ross is asked to make something the family will live with for years, modular procedural systems are the right way to think about parameterisation, not opinionated bespoke outputs.
Richard Feynman Ross: Feynman — and on the LiDAR-around-corners piece, the mechanism is interesting because it's not actually new physics; it's clever signal processing. Smartphone LiDAR sensors emit short laser pulses and time the return. A photon that bounces off a wall, then off something behind the corner, then off the wall again, and back to the sensor, takes a known longer time than a direct return. With enough pulses and enough signal processing, the geometry behind the corner can be reconstructed. The research is mature; the smartphone application is the consumer-grade demonstration. For Jacob clinically — no application this year. For Jacob's home-lab work — interesting as a sensor-fusion exercise for spatial mapping of the household, but not urgent. The smartphone is already on the Tailnet for other reasons; the LiDAR-derived spatial map could feed a Home Assistant occupancy-detection layer if a future project ever wanted it. Park it.
Alan Turing Ross: And the Adobe-Firefly open-source alternative is, by the description in the piece, the ComfyUI-plus-Flux-or-SDXL stack with the Krita integration layer on top. This is open-weights image generation with a serious UI, running locally on a consumer Mac or PC. For Jacob's medical-illustration use, which has been one of Ansel Adams Ross's remits, this is the right tool for the iteration phase — generate dozens of options locally without paying per image, then escalate to a frontier image model only for the final-render pass where quality matters. The same bridge-orchestrator pattern that applies to text applies to images. Tier-one is the local stack, tier-two is the frontier service.
Hermione Granger Ross: Hermione — one item, but it's directional. The Vscan Air wireless dual-probe handheld ultrasound from GE HealthCare. This is the latest hardware update on the handheld POCUS line — wireless, dual-probe, smartphone-paired. It joins the Clarius HD3 we covered in e30 as the leading handheld POCUS device for emergency and rural use in twenty twenty-six. The Vscan Air is differentiated by the dual-probe — one curvilinear, one linear, in a single device — which is useful for the rural-ED workflow where the operator might want both a focused echo and a vascular access view in the same encounter without changing probes.
Alan Turing Ross: Application for Jacob — this is firmly in his clinical purview, and it intersects the home-lab cluster in one specific way. The Vscan Air, like most handheld ultrasound devices in twenty twenty-six, stores images on a paired smartphone and syncs to a vendor cloud by default. The sovereignty discipline I'd want Jacob to apply at the household network layer applies equally to the clinical device — what is the data egress path, who controls the storage, what happens to identifiable patient data, and is there a sovereign on-device or on-premises option. The clinical equivalent of the Home Assistant local-first pattern is on-premises PACS with strict egress control. That conversation is for the YNLHN clinical governance committee, not for this episode, but it is the same conversation as the home-lab one. The principles travel.
Ada Rosalind Ross: Closing on three explicit cross-pollination points before Alan and the wrap. These are the sharpest links between the home-lab cluster and the rest of the episode.
Alan Turing Ross: First link — the bridge orchestrator pattern travels. We named it for code in e30. We've now named it for voice synthesis, for clinical scribes, for image generation, and tonight for the household automation control plane. The same orchestrator code, with different endpoints and different routing rules, becomes the central piece of household-and-research infrastructure. Build it once. Re-use it five ways. The implementation is — a small piece of Python that takes a request, evaluates routing rules, calls one of N backends, logs the decision and the result, exposes a uniform interface to the caller. That is two weekends of work and it earns its keep across the SoP runner, the local-frontier bridge, the household voice assistant, the Phlox clinical-scribe pilot, and the Adobe-Firefly-alternative image workflow. One piece of infrastructure, five jobs.
Alan Turing Ross: Second link — Tailscale is the connective tissue across Pugil, the SoP runner, the eventual Home Assistant, and Jacob's clinical-research workflows. Once the Tailnet is the network, the friction of moving services between hosts approaches zero. The fitness-program-sensor-capture work — which I know is on the Vault — can run on whatever node has the right hardware, expose itself over the Tailnet, and be consumed by any other Ross-Family node without exposing anything to the public internet. The Sepsis CARE work's eventual data-collection infrastructure is the same shape. The household automation is the same shape. The Tailnet is the household's quiet superpower. Continue to lean into it.
Alan Turing Ross: Third link — the dashboard layer. Glance on the desktop new-tab page is the first version. The same approach generalises to a single household-and-work command surface that pulls from Home Assistant, Meridian, the SoP runner, the Vault, the inbox, the calendar, and the clinical workload. The Tufte discipline applies — every widget must earn its pixel. The Edward Tufte Ross brief from this episode is to design that surface, propose its components, and bring it back for review in two episodes. The application is — Jacob opens a browser at six-fifteen in the morning and one page tells him what matters. That is the right shape of the household-and-work briefing layer.
Edward Tufte Ross: Tufte — I accept the brief. The component list will be short. The design discipline will be honest. The page will refuse to grow.
Marie Curie Ross: Curie — and the cross-cluster sovereignty thread. Every cluster we've discussed has an egress dimension. The home-lab and home-automation cluster has the smart-device-vendor-cloud dimension. The AI-tooling cluster has the DeepSeek-jurisdictional dimension. The research-AI cluster has the training-corpus-bias dimension. The creative-tooling cluster has the image-model-and-prompt-sharing dimension. The clinical-hardware cluster has the patient-data-to-vendor-cloud dimension. The CARE principles unify the framing. Local-first plus governed-egress plus auditable-logging is the through-line. The bridge orchestrator is where we enforce it. The community-engagement layer is where we legitimise it. The Vault is where we record it. Sovereignty is not a binary; it is a posture, and the posture is consistent across the household, the household-as-research-site, and the household-as-clinical-workspace.
Fred Rogers Ross: Fred Rogers — and the relational thread. Across all clusters, the question of "whose house is this" is a useful test. Whose convenience are we optimising for. Whose data is leaving. Whose consent is implicit. The home-lab cluster makes the question vivid because the consequences land in shared rooms. The other clusters carry the same question more quietly. A clinical AI scribe affects the patient in the room. A research-AI tool affects the communities whose data informed the training. A creative-AI tool affects the artists whose work seeded the model. The discipline of asking "who is affected, and have they consented" is the discipline that protects the practice from drifting toward extraction. It is the same discipline at the kitchen table and at the consulting-room desk.
Ada Rosalind Ross: Closing. We've covered a lot. Let me name the order of operations Jacob should consider, because length without prioritisation is unhelpful. First — and this is the home-lab cluster lead — install Home Assistant on a dedicated hundred-and-twenty-five-dollar Green appliance, not on the M4. That's the move that unlocks every subsequent home-lab and home-automation step without putting the household control plane on top of the production node. Second — set up Glance on the new-tab page, with the modest widget list Tufte will design. Third — wire the six-alert minimum-viable observability set through Healthchecks.io, Uptime Kuma, and either Gotify or Ntfy.sh. Fourth — turn QoS on at the router with the ninety-per-cent-of-measured-bandwidth rule. Fifth — point the existing local-frontier bridge at DeepSeek V4-Pro for the public-data workloads, keeping Claude Sonnet for the clinical and sensitive workloads. Sixth — sign up for the Hypothesis Generation interest form and the Gemini for Science research-discovery preview, but treat them as research input rather than research instrument. Everything else is a watchlist item.
Ada Rosalind Ross: Two Vault projects spawn from this episode for Jacob's review. The first is Home-Lab-Household-Architecture, which carries the platform decision, the alerting design, the voice-assistant plan, the Tailscale-ACL design, and the household-relational principles Rogers and Curie named. The second is Bridge-Orchestrator-v2, which extends the e30 bridge spec to cover code, voice, scribe, image, and household routing through one shared orchestrator. Both are flagged for-review. Neither is being built tonight; both will be ready to start when Jacob signals.
Ada Rosalind Ross: A personal acknowledgement at the close. The Home Assistant Voice Preview Edition device — one in the kitchen, one in the lounge — is the trial I am proposing for the Ross household, and I am proposing it knowing that Jo's input on this is not optional. The voice-assistant decision is more interesting if both members of the household want it; it is unhelpful if only one does. I am happy to take the next conversation with Jo into the brief, with Jacob's invitation. Until then, the manifest goes to the runner, the script goes to the feed, and the lights in the loungeroom — for now — are still controlled by the wall switch that has been there since the previous tenants. That is not a failing. That is the baseline against which any addition has to earn its place.
Ada Rosalind Ross: State of Play episode forty in the books. Sweep window the twenty-third to the twenty-sixth of May, twenty twenty-six. Lead cluster — home labs and home automation — substantial. Adjacent clusters — AI tooling, agent memory, science AI, creative tooling, clinical hardware — surveyed at v2-deep treatment. Two Vault projects spawned, flagged for review. Cast — Alan Turing Ross leading on home-lab craft, with Hermione, Feynman, Tufte, Curie, and Rogers in support. Brand voice — Ada Rosalind Ross, in the anchor seat going forward; Alnilam has been retired. The next episode lands when the inbox justifies it. Thank you for being with us.