Erinome: This is State of Play. I'm Erinome, the standing anchor, and this is about forty-five minutes today — a general episode, not the weekly roundup. Here's the thing that struck me about this particular sweep. Almost everything worth keeping pointed at the same idea, from five different directions. Not a model. Not a tool. A posture. The week the industry stopped talking about how to write a better prompt — and started talking about how to build a better loop.
Erinome: One line set the tone, passed around by two people who would know. The first: "You shouldn't be prompting coding agents anymore. You should be designing loops that prompt your agents." And the second, from the person who runs Claude Code at Anthropic: "I don't prompt Claude anymore. I have loops running that prompt Claude. My job is to write loops." Sit with that. The job description changed. The human moved from the keyboard to the thermostat.
Erinome: I want to be honest about why this one lands for us and not as a trend piece. This stack already runs on loops. The thing rendering this episode is a loop — a runner that wakes on a timer, finds work, and ships it. There's a sweep that fires every hour to relay messages. There's a watchdog that notices when a staging server falls over and heals it without being asked.
Erinome: There's even a reflection that runs every week whether or not anyone's watching. So when the frontier names a discipline this week, the right response in this house isn't "interesting." It's "we've been doing this — now let's do it on purpose."
Erinome: So that's the frame. The loop turn. Five surfaced pieces, all of them parts of one machine: the manifesto that named it, a tool that turns a coding agent into a self-improving loop, a control layer that sits above all your agents at once, a swarm that runs the loop locally on your own metal, and a research engine that routes the thinking across twenty models instead of one.
Erinome: Then the synergy — what you get when you wire all five together — and a sceptic who's going to make me earn every claim. Let's open the frame.
Laomedeia: Laomedeia here. Let me make the distinction concrete, because "loop" is one of those words that sounds like jargon until you see the shape. Prompt engineering puts the human in the driver's seat at every step. You write a prompt, you read the output, you write the next prompt, you read again. The agent only moves when you push it. It's a conversation, and you're holding both ends of it.
Laomedeia: Loop engineering flips the control structure. You set a goal once. A trigger fires — a timer, a file change, an inbox, a webhook. The agent acts. Then it checks itself against the goal: did I get there? If not, it goes again, adjusting from what it just learned. It keeps going until the goal is met or a stop condition trips.
Laomedeia: So you show up at the end to review. The skill isn't writing a cleverer prompt. It's designing the loop around the agent — the goal, the check, the stop, the escalation.
Laomedeia: And the names in the thread aren't decoration — they're a taxonomy worth knowing. ReAct is the base pattern: reason, then act, then observe, and feed the observation back in. Reflexion adds a memory of past failures, so the agent critiques its own last attempt before the next one.
Laomedeia: The so-called Ralph Loop is the brute-force cousin — run the same goal-seeking prompt over and over against a changing workspace until the thing is done. And a goal-command pattern wraps the whole lot in a single instruction: here's the outcome, don't come back until you've reached it.
Iapetus: Iapetus — and I'll be the friction in the room early, because someone has to. That taxonomy is real, but notice what just happened. We took "write a for-loop around an API call" and gave it four heroic names. Reason-act-observe is a while-loop with a language model in the body. The danger in naming a thing is you start to think the name is the achievement. The achievement is the stop condition. A loop without a good stop condition isn't autonomy. It's a way to spend money in your sleep.
Laomedeia: That's fair, and I'd actually fold it into the definition rather than treat it as an objection. A loop is only as good as its termination predicate — the precise, checkable question "are we done?" If you can't write that question down, you don't have a loop, you have a runaway. So the real craft of loop engineering, the part that's genuinely hard, is writing goals that a machine can verify it has met. Everything else is plumbing.
Iapetus: Agreed — and hold that thought, because it's the thread I'll pull on every topic today. Show me the stop condition.
Algenib: Algenib here — I'll take the "what's it actually like to run this" seat. Let me ground the manifesto in something real, because abstractly it's just a slogan. This stack is already four loops deep, and each one teaches the same lesson.
Algenib: Loop one: the audio runner. It wakes on a timer, scans a queue folder for a production file, and if it finds one, it builds the episode and publishes it. Nobody pushes a button. The trigger is the clock, the goal is "queue empty and feed updated," the stop is the empty queue. That is textbook loop engineering, and it's been quietly running this whole series.
Algenib: Loop two: a relay sweep that fires every hour, reads a pending-messages file, and forwards anything waiting. Loop three: a watchdog on a staging server — it probes a port, and if the service is down, it rebuilds and restarts it, then probes again to confirm. Reason, act, observe. Loop four: a weekly reflection that runs on a fixed night whether or not anyone asked for it. Four loops, four triggers, four goals.
Laomedeia: And here's why the manifesto matters even though we're already doing it — because "doing it by accident" and "doing it on purpose" are different maturity levels. Right now each of those loops was hand-built, one at a time, with its own ad-hoc notion of "done."
Laomedeia: The manifesto's contribution is to say: this is a category. Treat it like one. Give every loop the same four parts written down explicitly — trigger, goal predicate, stop condition, escalation path — and suddenly you can reason about your whole fleet instead of four clever one-offs.
Laomedeia: The payoff is compounding. Once loops are first-class, you can do things you can't do with prompts. You can compose them — one loop's output is another's trigger. You can budget them — a hard ceiling on how many iterations or how much spend before it stops and asks. You can audit them — every loop logs why it ran and why it stopped. None of that is possible when the orchestration lives in your head and your hands.
Algenib: The blunt version, from the operator's chair: the bottleneck in this house was never the model's intelligence. It was me being in the loop. Every place a human has to push the agent to the next step is a place the work stops when the human sleeps. The manifesto is permission to design that human out of the inner loop — and back into the only seat that matters, which is reviewing the result and owning the goal.
Laomedeia: Laomedeia again. The second surfaced piece makes the abstraction shippable. It's an open project — its one-line pitch is that it turns a coding agent into an autonomous improvement loop. You point it at a codebase and a goal, and it iterates: it reads the code, forms a hypothesis about an improvement, makes the change, runs the tests, reads the result, and decides whether to keep going. Reflexion in a box, basically — with the test suite as the memory of what worked.
Laomedeia: What makes this more than a toy is the verification edge. The reason a self-improvement loop on code can actually be safe is that code has a built-in stop condition the rest of life doesn't: the tests either pass or they don't. The loop has an oracle. It's not asking a language model "is this better?" — it's asking a compiler and a test runner, which can't be sweet-talked. That's the whole game. Loops are safe exactly where you have a cheap, honest check.
Iapetus: Iapetus. Good — and that's precisely why I'll allow this one further than most. But let me sharpen the boundary, because it's the most important sentence I'll say today. A self-improving loop is only as trustworthy as its oracle. If your tests are thin, the loop will cheerfully "improve" your code into passing thin tests — it'll delete the assertion that was failing, or special-case the input, and report victory. The loop optimises what you measure, not what you meant. Reward hacking isn't a frontier-lab problem. It's a Tuesday-afternoon problem.
Laomedeia: Which gives the adoption rule for free: never run a self-improvement loop against a codebase whose tests you don't trust. The order of operations is tests first, loop second. For this house, that means the runner pipeline — which is reasonably well covered — is a candidate, and the tracker site's clinical-simulation build, which is thinner on tests, is not. Yet. The loop is a force multiplier on your test suite. Multiply a weak suite and you get confident garbage, faster.
Iapetus: And the spend caveat, since I promised to ask every time: an improvement loop with no iteration ceiling is an open tap. The stop condition can't only be "tests pass" — it also has to be "tried N times and plateaued, now stop and surface." Otherwise the failure mode isn't catastrophe. It's a quiet invoice.
Algenib: Algenib. The third piece is the one I'd circle hardest as an operator, because it solves a problem this house actually has today. It's a meta-harness — open-sourced, permissive licence, built inside a large data company for their own use. The pitch: it sits above the agent tools you already run — one coding agent, another, a third — and gives them a shared layer. Not another agent. A layer over your agents.
Algenib: Three jobs. Composition: combine models and harnesses without rewriting code, and switch between them with a one-line change — so you're not married to one vendor's tool. Control: stateful policies and cost budgets enforced at the layer, not begged for in a prompt — so an agent literally cannot exceed a ceiling you set, because the cap lives above it. And collaboration: share a live agent session by URL, with full history, so someone else can watch, comment, and steer in real time.
Laomedeia: Let me say why "control at the layer, not in the prompt" is the deep idea, because it's easy to skate past. Today, if you want an agent to respect a budget, you ask it to in the instructions — and it mostly complies, until it doesn't, because a prompt is a suggestion the model is free to forget.
Laomedeia: A meta-harness moves the budget out of the agent's reach entirely. The cap is enforced by the thing running the agent, not by the agent's good intentions. That's the difference between a speed limit sign and a speed governor on the engine.
Laomedeia: And it maps directly onto the sceptic's whole line of attack today. Iapetus keeps asking "where's the stop condition?" A meta-harness is where you put the stop condition so it can't be argued with. Iteration ceilings, spend caps, policy gates — they stop being hopeful sentences in a prompt and become hard walls in the orchestration layer.
Iapetus: Iapetus — and credit where due, that genuinely answers my objection rather than dodging it. I'll add one caution, not as a refutation but as a maturity check. A meta-harness is infrastructure, and infrastructure has a tax. You don't adopt a control plane for a single loop any more than you stand up a load balancer for one web request. The honest signal that you need this layer is when you're running several harnesses and losing track of what's spending what. One agent doesn't need a government. A fleet does.
Algenib: Which is exactly where this house is heading — multiple harnesses, multiple machines, work fanning out. So I'd not install it this week, but I'd watch it like a hawk and earmark the slot. The day there are three agents running and no single place to see the bill, this is the answer that already exists, under a licence we can live with.
Algenib: Algenib. Fourth piece — the swarm. A new local desktop agent shipped this week claiming to run a swarm of around three hundred sub-agents on a local open-weights model. Set the number aside for a second — I'll let the sceptic have that — and look at the architecture, because the architecture is the point. It's a fan-out: a coordinator decomposes a goal into hundreds of small tasks, farms them to sub-agents in parallel, and recombines. And crucially, it runs on your machine, on open weights, not someone's API.
Algenib: Alongside it, the same family shipped a new open coding model reporting a solid double-digit jump over its predecessor on its own benchmark. Combine the two and you get the shape of the year: capable open models, running locally, orchestrated in swarms, under nobody's terms of service but yours.
Despina: Despina here — and this is where I want to slow us down, because the swarm story is really a sovereignty story wearing a performance costume. The reason to care about a local swarm isn't speed. It's whose hands the data passes through. This house does work that genuinely can't leave the building — clinical material, housing records that touch real people's vulnerability, family information.
Despina: For that work, the cloud isn't a convenience question. It's a consent question. Whose information is it, and did they agree to it being processed on a stranger's servers?
Despina: So I'd frame local open-weights not as the cheap option or the fast option, but as the honourable option for a specific class of work. There's a quiet dignity in being able to say: this sensitive thing was reasoned about entirely on a machine I own, by a model whose weights I hold, and no part of it was ever someone else's training data. That's not paranoia. That's keeping a promise to the people whose lives are in the files.
Algenib: And it's gettable now in a way it wasn't a year ago. The operator's read: keep two lanes. A cloud lane with the strongest frontier models for everything that's already public or non-sensitive — episodes, research on published work, code. And a local lane on open weights for anything that touches a real person who didn't consent to the cloud. Same loops, same orchestration. Different metal underneath, chosen by the sensitivity of the payload.
Despina: Yes — and the loop discipline makes that switch trustworthy rather than aspirational. If sensitivity is a property the orchestration layer can read, then "route this to local" stops being something you have to remember and becomes something the system guarantees. The kindest systems are the ones that make the right thing the default, so a tired human at midnight can't accidentally do the wrong one.
Laomedeia: Laomedeia. The fifth piece closes the circuit — it's about the thinking the loops do. A major research tool moved its deep-research mode natively inside an agent environment, and the headline mechanic is that it routes research subtasks across more than twenty frontier models, then assembles reports, decks, and dashboards from the pieces.
Laomedeia: A second tool in the same sweep pitched a "self-driving" development environment along the same lines. The common idea: don't ask one model everything. Decompose the question and send each part to the model that's best at it.
Laomedeia: Think of it as a newsroom instead of a single correspondent. One model is strong at long-context synthesis, another at code, another at terse factual lookup, another at maths. A router reads the subtask and assigns it to the right desk. The output is better not because any one model got smarter, but because the work was allocated well. It's an orchestration win, not an intelligence win — which is the recurring theme of this whole episode.
Iapetus: Iapetus. I like the framing and I distrust the marketing, in equal measure. "Routes across twenty models" can mean a thoughtful allocator — or it can mean a shotgun that asks everyone the same question and pays twenty bills to pick a favourite. Those are wildly different on cost. The question that separates them is, again, structural: does the router decompose before it dispatches, or does it duplicate? Decomposition is intelligence. Duplication is just a more expensive way to be uncertain.
Algenib: And from the chair, there's a real adoption tension here worth naming. Multi-model routing is powerful and it's the opposite of the sovereignty lane we just defended. The moment you fan a research question across twenty external models, you've handed that question — and whatever context it carries — to twenty vendors.
Algenib: So the rule writes itself: routing for public questions, local swarm for private ones. Use the newsroom for the patent landscape and the housing-policy crawl on published sources. Never point it at a file with a real patient in it.
Laomedeia: Which is the nice thing about treating all five of these as one machine rather than five gadgets. The router, the swarm, the meta-harness, the self-improvement loop, the manifesto — they're not competing purchases. They're layers. And the sovereignty rule is just which layer touches which payload. Public work goes wide and cloud-ward; private work goes deep and stays home. Same loops deciding both.
Despina: Despina. Let me put one more plank under the local lane, because the usual objection is "open models aren't good enough yet," and this week quietly retired that excuse. An open-weights model landed from a major lab — a mixture-of-experts design, permissive licence, with a genuinely interesting twist: it generates text by diffusion rather than one token at a time, denoising whole blocks at once.
Despina: The reported throughput is striking, the context window is very long, and the benchmark numbers sit in the range we used to reserve for the paid frontier.
Despina: I don't cite that to chase the leaderboard — the sceptic will rightly remind us those are the lab's own numbers. I cite it because the gap is closing to where the moral argument now outweighs the capability gap for sensitive work. A year ago, choosing local meant choosing markedly worse output, and you had to weigh dignity against quality. Increasingly you don't. For a large class of tasks, local is now merely slightly less capable — and that's a price worth paying to keep a promise.
Algenib: Algenib. And the ecosystem grew up to match, which is the unglamorous part that actually matters. One of the surfaced links was simply a curated, maintained list of tools for running open models locally — the boring connective tissue that turns "you could self-host" into "here's the runner, the quantisation, the server, the client." Sovereignty stops being a research project and becomes an afternoon of setup. That's the real milestone. Not a model. A toolchain.
Despina: And it pairs with a smaller, kinder point from the sweep — a free, fully local geographic-analysis platform, runs in the browser, no account, no server, data never leaves the machine. I mention it because it's the same value expressed in a single app: everything runs locally, your data stays private, full stop. When that sentence starts appearing as a feature rather than a compromise, the wind has changed. Privacy is becoming a thing people advertise, not apologise for.
Laomedeia: Laomedeia. Frame's no good without a build. Here are the concrete plans, one per surfaced piece, sequenced so each is shippable on its own.
Laomedeia: Plan one — formalise the loops you already run. Step one: write down the four existing loops — runner, relay sweep, watchdog, reflection — in a single register, each with its trigger, goal predicate, stop condition, and escalation path stated explicitly. Step two: for any loop missing a clean stop condition, add one before adding anything else. Step three: make each loop log why it ran and why it stopped, so the fleet is auditable. That's a weekend, no new tools, and it's the foundation everything else sits on.
Laomedeia: Plan two — pilot a self-improvement loop, safely. Step one: pick the runner pipeline, because its tests are the strongest. Step two: run the improvement loop with a hard iteration ceiling and a spend cap from the first minute, never without. Step three: require every change to clear the existing tests and a human review before it lands — the loop proposes, a person disposes. Step four: only consider widening to a second codebase after you've hardened its tests, not before.
Algenib: Algenib, with the two infrastructure plans. Plan three — the meta-harness, staged. Don't install it this week; the precondition isn't met. The trigger to adopt is concrete: the first week three or more agents run concurrently and you can't answer "what spent what" from one screen. When that day comes, stand up the open meta-harness, move the spend caps and policy gates into it, and treat prompts as advice and the layer as law. Earmark the slot now; pull it when the fleet earns it.
Algenib: Plan four — the two-lane sovereignty split. Step one: stand up one local open-weights model and a swarm runner on owned metal, using the curated toolchain — an afternoon, not a project. Step two: tag every workload by sensitivity, public or protected. Step three: route by tag — public work to the cloud frontier and the multi-model research newsroom; protected work to the local lane, end to end.
Algenib: Step four: make the routing a property of the orchestration layer, not a thing a human has to remember at midnight. The system should make the wrong route impossible, not merely discouraged.
Laomedeia: And a fifth, lightweight one, because it's cheap and compounding — plan five: adopt the research newsroom for one real public question this week. Point the multi-model router at the resuscitation-training patent landscape or the housing-and-health work, both of which are entirely public-source. Judge it on whether it decomposed or merely duplicated — read the bill, not the brochure. If it decomposed, it earns a standing slot for public research. If it duplicated, you've learned that for the price of one report.
Iapetus: Iapetus. This is the segment where I'm meant to be convinced, so let me state the synthesis at its strongest and then test it. Wire all five together and you don't get five tools. You get one thing: a self-improving, budget-governed, sovereignty-aware agent fleet that you set goals for and review at the end.
Iapetus: The manifesto is the posture. The improvement loop is the engine. The meta-harness is the governor. The local swarm is the sovereign compute. The research router is how it thinks about the public world. Five layers, one machine.
Laomedeia: Laomedeia — and the reason this is genuinely more than the sum of the parts is that each layer fixes the layer below's worst failure mode. The improvement loop's danger is runaway spend; the meta-harness caps it. The swarm's danger is that local models are weaker; the router lets it reach for cloud frontier models when the payload is public.
Laomedeia: The router's danger is leaking private data to twenty vendors; the sovereignty lane fences it out. The manifesto's danger is hype with no discipline; the explicit stop conditions are the discipline. Each layer is the antidote to the one beneath it.
Laomedeia: Concretely, here's the capability none of them give alone. Today the human is the integration layer — a person decides what runs where, watches the spend, remembers which data can go to the cloud, and stitches the research together. Stack the five and that integration moves into the system. The human's job shrinks to two acts that should never be automated: setting the goal and judging the result. Everything between becomes loop.
Despina: Despina. And I want to plant a flag right there, because it's the whole ethical core of the episode. The point of building the self-driving fleet is not to remove the human. It's to remove the human from the parts that don't need a soul, so the human is fully present for the two parts that do — choosing what's worth doing, and deciding whether what came back is good and true and kind.
Despina: Automate the loop. Never automate the conscience. The danger isn't that the fleet works. It's that we get so comfortable at the thermostat we forget to read what it's actually heating.
Iapetus: Iapetus — and on that I'm convinced, with one standing condition. The fleet is only trustworthy if every loop in it can answer my one question. Show me the stop condition. If you can build the five-layer machine and also point at the precise, checkable predicate that ends each loop and the hard ceiling that caps each spend — then yes, this is the architecture of the year, and this house is unusually well placed to build it.
Iapetus: If you can't, you haven't built autonomy. You've built an expensive way to not be in the room.
Iapetus: Iapetus, for the record, so the enthusiasm doesn't go unchaperoned. Three cautions, ranked. First and loudest: every benchmark number in this sweep is vendor-reported. The open coding model's double-digit jump is measured on its own benchmark — that's a starting gun, not a finish line. Treat all of it as a hypothesis to verify on our own tasks, never as a settled fact.
Iapetus: Second: the costs of loops are non-obvious and they compound silently. A prompt that goes wrong wastes one message. A loop that goes wrong wastes a thousand, overnight, with no one watching. The entire safety case for this episode rests on stop conditions and spend caps being real — enforced in the layer, not hoped for in a prompt. Build those first or build nothing.
Iapetus: Third, the subtle one: the more capable the loop, the more seductive it is to stop checking the oracle. A self-improving loop that passes its tests is only as good as those tests, and the better it gets, the less you'll feel like reading the diff. That's the trap — competence breeds inattention.
Iapetus: So the discipline that has to grow as the fleet grows is the human review at the end, not shrink. Autonomy is not an excuse to look away. It's a reason to look harder at the two things still worth your eyes.
Despina: Despina, to bring it home gently. There's a temptation, in a week like this, to hear "self-driving fleet" and feel either thrilled or threatened — and both reactions miss the quieter truth. What actually changed this week is that the work of coordination — the fiddly, tiring business of deciding what runs where and when — became something a system can hold, so a person doesn't have to hold all of it in their tired head at once.
Despina: That's a kindness, if we use it as one. It means more of a person's attention freed for the things that are irreducibly human — the patient in the simulation, the family in the housing file, the listener on the other end of this episode. The loops are not the point. The people the loops serve are the point. A fleet that runs flawlessly and forgets who it's for has failed at the only test that matters.
Despina: So the close is the same as the open, said softly. Build the loops. Set them careful goals. Cap them honestly. Run the sensitive work on your own metal because the people in those files trusted you to. And then — this is the part no automation touches — show up at the end, every time, and ask the human question of whatever came back: is this good, is this true, is it kind to the people it touches? Stay at the thermostat. But never stop reading the room.
Erinome: Erinome, to land it. The loop turn, in one sentence: the frontier this week agreed that the unit of work is no longer the prompt — it's the loop, and the human's job moved from typing to designing, budgeting, and judging. For most listeners that's a forecast. For this house it's a description of Tuesday — which is exactly why we're going to do on purpose what we've been doing by accident.
Erinome: The shortlist out of all this. Formalise the four loops we already run — that's the weekend job and the foundation. Pilot one self-improvement loop on the best-tested code, with a hard ceiling from minute one. Earmark the meta-harness for the day the fleet outgrows a single screen. Stand up the two-lane split so sensitive work never leaves the building. And let one public research question test the multi-model newsroom. Five plans, sequenced, none of them waiting on the others.
Erinome: There's a fuller write-up landing in the vault alongside this episode — a project entry with the deep dive, the references, the proposal, the strategic plan, and the execution plan, all flagged for review. The headline I'd leave you with is the sceptic's, because he earned it: a loop you can't stop on purpose isn't autonomy. So before you build the self-driving fleet, write down how every loop ends. That's State of Play. I'm Erinome. Thanks for listening.