Erinome: This is State of Play. I'm Erinome, the standing anchor, and tonight is the self-sent batch — every link that landed in the inbox from the inbox since episode fifty-one published on Tuesday afternoon. Nine flags, one sweep, and they fall into a shape: local AI you run on your own machine, agentic coding, generative media, one piece of ambient hardware, and one machine-learning library for clinical data. The through-line is sovereignty — most of tonight runs on your own silicon, not someone else's cloud.
Erinome: I'll lead with the answer, then unpack it. Install this month, free — AnythingLLM, as the local document-and-agent front end on the M-four; and Understand-Anything, the open-source retrieval engine to sit behind it. Trial — Rodin, the image-to-three-D generator, against one real asset for the medical-education channel. Monitor — Apple's MLX as the inference layer underneath the local stack, and the Gemini Home speaker as the ambient capture surface. And one for the watch-list with a named caveat: the free AI character-video tools — useful, but not for anything clinical. The skip tonight is thin, because this batch is unusually high-signal.
Iapetus: Iapetus here, and I'm the sceptic in the room. Every item earns its slot against one question — what does this do that the stack already running on this machine does not? Jacob already has Claude in the vault, a Gemini text-to-speech pipeline in production, and an M-four that renders splats and clouds. So when a tool comes up, I want the marginal capability named, and I want the cost — in dollars, in setup time, and in attention. "It's free and local" is not a reason to install it. "It closes this specific gap for this specific project" is.
Erinome: Agreed, and the specific project frames the whole hour. Two days ago this desk produced a thirty-thousand-word medical-education strategy for the MinuteMED collaboration. That document recommended a sovereign, open-source production pipeline. Tonight's batch is, almost item for item, the toolkit that pipeline needs. So the lens is not the abstract state of play — it's: does this earn a place in a working clinician's local AI stack and a med-ed production line. Let's start where most of the batch lives, which is on your own hard drive.
Charon: Charon, the operator — I handle install paths and what it actually costs to run. Local AI first, because three of the nine flags are the same idea from three angles. AnythingLLM is the front door. It's a free, open-source desktop application — Mintplex Labs — that wraps local or hosted language models in a workspace with document retrieval, agents, and a clean chat interface. You point it at a folder of PDFs, it embeds them, and you ask questions grounded in your own documents, entirely offline if you want. On an M-four it runs comfortably against a local model, or you can wire it to Claude for the heavy reasoning and keep retrieval local.
Charon: The install is genuinely fifteen minutes. Download the desktop build, pick an embedding model and a language model — local through Ollama or LM Studio, or an API key for Claude or Gemini — drop in documents, done. The marginal capability over Claude-in-the-vault, Iapetus, is this: a persistent, embedded, multi-document workspace that does not re-upload the corpus every session, with optional fully-offline operation. For a clinician handling sensitive material, the offline mode is the point — sensitive prompts never leave the machine.
Iapetus: That's a real gap closed, I'll grant it. The vault plus Claude is excellent for drafting, but it is not a standing retrieval index, and it is not offline. So AnythingLLM earns install — but with a discipline. It is a front end, not a model. Its answers are only as good as the embedding model and the language model behind it, and the temptation will be to trust a small local model that quietly hallucinates. The rule has to be: local model for retrieval and triage, Claude for anything that gets published or clinically acted on.
Charon: One configuration note, because it's the line between sovereign and theatre. In AnythingLLM, set the embedder to a local model and the vector store to the on-disk default, so the index never touches a server. Then keep two language-model profiles — a local one through Ollama for indexing and triage, and Claude for the publish path. The data-residency story for a clinician is then clean and stateable: embeddings and retrieval live on the M-four; only the explicit, reviewed reasoning calls leave it, to a provider with named data commitments. That is a sentence you can put in an ethics application, which is not nothing for an Aboriginal-health research portfolio.
Charon: Which is exactly where Understand-Anything fits — flag two. It's an open-source project on GitHub, from Egonex-AI, and where AnythingLLM is the polished application, Understand-Anything is the engine you can take apart. It is a retrieval-and-reasoning pipeline over arbitrary documents — the "understand any document" layer — that you can self-host and wire into your own workflow rather than living inside one vendor's app. For Jacob specifically, the value is not "another chat UI". It's a component: a retrieval backend that can sit behind a custom pipeline, on the M-four, under his control.
Algieba: Algieba — I build things, so I'll say the quiet part. The reason you keep two of these, the app and the engine, is that they serve two different days. AnythingLLM is the day you want to ask your documents a question and get on with clinic. Understand-Anything is the day you're building the MinuteMED research pipeline and you want retrieval as a node in an n8n workflow, not a window you click. The strategy document two days ago called n8n the spine of the production line. Understand-Anything is a limb that attaches to that spine.
Erinome: And the third flag in this cluster, MLX, is the floor all of it stands on. MLX is Apple's open-source machine-learning framework, built for Apple Silicon — it runs models natively on the M-series GPU and unified memory, efficiently, without CUDA. The reason it matters tonight is not that Jacob writes MLX code; it's that MLX is increasingly the inference engine underneath the local-model tools. When AnythingLLM or LM Studio runs a model fast on the M-four, MLX is often why. So the verdict on MLX is monitor, not install — it's infrastructure that arrives underneath the things you do install.
Iapetus: Let me close the cluster with the honest caution. Local AI is seductive precisely because it feels sovereign and free, and both of those are real. But "runs on my machine" and "good enough to act on" are different claims. A seven-billion-parameter local model is a capable triage assistant and a poor clinical reasoner. So the stack verdict is: install AnythingLLM and stand up Understand-Anything as a retrieval node, run both with a local model for indexing and search, and route every answer that matters through Claude. Sovereign for the bulk, authoritative for the decisions. That's the synthesis.
Erinome: Cleanly put. That is the high-yield cluster of the night, and it earns a Vault project entry — Local-AI-Stack, status for-review — capturing the three-layer design: MLX underneath, AnythingLLM and Understand-Anything as the retrieval and agent layer, Claude as the reasoning authority, all on the M-four. Now the second cluster, which is how the machine builds software for itself. Agentic coding.
Charon: Two flags here. The first is an XDA piece — Jacob gave Claude Code and Google Antigravity the same full project and let them run. The finding, in the headline, was that both finished it, and finished it dramatically faster than hand-coding in a plain editor — the comparison was "twice as fast". That's the state of play in one sentence: the question is no longer whether an agent can complete a real multi-file project end to end. It can. The question is which one, for what, and at what cost in oversight.
Charon: The operator's read: Claude Code and Antigravity are converging on the same loop — read the repo, plan, edit across files, run, observe, iterate — but they differ in temperament. Claude Code is the terminal-native, transparent one: you see every command, every diff, and it asks before the irreversible things. Antigravity, Google's agentic IDE, leans more autonomous and more graphical. For Jacob, who already runs Claude Code on the M-four and the Meridian deploys through it tonight, the incumbent advantage is large. The marginal reason to add Antigravity is a second opinion on hard problems, not a replacement.
Iapetus: And here the sceptic actually relaxes, because Jacob has lived this. The Meridian volumetric-cloud feature shipped this week through exactly this loop — agent writes the shader, a Playwright smoke test screenshots it, the human reads the screenshot, the agent re-tunes. That is the loop working. So the XDA finding isn't news to this desk; it's confirmation. The open question the article doesn't answer is the one that matters: not "can it finish", but "can you trust what it finished". And the answer is the verification harness, not the model.
Puck: Puck here — I do the explainers, and that's the perfect handoff to flag three, "The Art of Loop Engineering", because it names the thing Iapetus just described. Loop engineering is the discipline of designing the agent's outer loop — what it does, checks, and re-does — rather than just writing a better prompt. The shift the piece captures is that the leverage has moved. A year ago you engineered the prompt. Now you engineer the loop: the tools the agent can call, the tests that gate its work, the point where it stops and asks a human. The screenshot-and-retune cycle on the clouds shader is loop engineering. So is the morning brief's fail-safe try-except around the cost logger.
Puck: Why it matters for a clinician-builder specifically: the loop is where safety lives. In medicine you would never let a junior act without a check step; loop engineering is that same instinct applied to software agents. The implementation takeaway is concrete — for every agent task Jacob builds, design three things before the prompt: the tools it may use, the automated check that proves it worked, and the explicit stop-and-ask boundary. That is the whole craft, and the batch flagged it at exactly the right moment.
Erinome: So the agentic-coding cluster nets out as: no new install — Claude Code stays the spine — but a genuine conceptual upgrade. Treat loop design as the primary skill, keep Antigravity on monitor as a second agent for adversarial second opinions, and make the verification harness, not the model choice, the thing you invest in. Now the cluster that connects straight to the other project on this desk this week — generative media for MinuteMED.
Algieba: This is my bench. Two flags, both generative, both relevant to a medical-education channel. Rodin first — Rodin AI, from Hyper3D — is a free image-and-text-to-three-D generator. You give it an image or a prompt, it returns a textured three-D model. For a med-ed channel, the use is specific and real: bespoke three-D props and simplified anatomical-adjacent objects you can pose and render in Blender, without sculpting them by hand. Not clinically exact anatomy — the strategy document was firm that AI is never the anatomical reference — but the inhaler, the IV pump, the stylised cell, the prop in the corner of the frame.
Algieba: The verdict is trial, and the trial is disciplined: one real asset for one real episode. Generate a three-D model of a single teaching prop, bring it into Blender, light it, render it into a MinuteMED segment, and judge whether the time saved beats modelling it yourself or buying it. If it does, Rodin becomes a node in the pipeline. If the output needs an hour of cleanup every time, it doesn't. That's a thirty-minute test that answers a real question, and it slots directly into the open-source toolchain the strategy doc recommended.
Iapetus: The second generative flag is where I plant a flag of my own. "Create AI videos free — build your own AI characters" — a free AI character-video generator. As a technology it's genuine; as a tool for this creator it needs a hard boundary. An AI-generated character delivering medical content is exactly the uncanny-valley, clinical-authority trap the strategy document warned about, and an undisclosed synthetic presenter raises the advertising and honesty issues under the practitioner code. So: useful for a generic explainer B-roll character, never for anything that reads as a doctor giving advice. Watch-list, with that caveat written down.
Erinome: And that is the synergy worth naming explicitly, because two of this week's deliverables just met. The medical-education strategy document is the plan; tonight's generative tools are parts for it. Rodin for props, the local-AI stack for the research-and-scripting backend, Claude for the script, Gemini text-to-speech for the voice — which this desk already runs with cost tracking — and the whole thing orchestrated on the M-four. The batch didn't just surface nine tools. It surfaced, by accident, most of a production line for the other project. That is the cross-topic dividend.
Puck: Let me take the two that sit a little apart from the production line — the ambient one and the clinical-data one. The Gemini-powered Google Home speaker — flag eight — is, finally, the consumer hardware catching up to the models. A home speaker with Gemini behind it means the ambient assistant is now genuinely conversational rather than command-and-control. For Jacob, the honest read is: interesting, low priority. The value isn't the speaker; it's the signal that ambient, always-available capture is arriving — the kind of thing that, three iterations on, becomes a hands-free clinical note or a voice-captured idea that lands in exactly the self-sent inbox that made tonight's episode.
Puck: And sktime — flag nine — is the one genuinely technical library in the batch, and it's the most quietly relevant to medicine. sktime is an open-source Python framework for time-series machine learning — forecasting, classification, the unified scikit-learn-style interface for temporal data. Why a clinician cares: clinical data is overwhelmingly time-series. Vital-sign trends, lactate clearance curves, sepsis trajectories, ward-occupancy forecasting. sktime is the tool you reach for when the question is "what does this trend predict", and it's the bridge from the sepsis-poster and simulation work toward something with a model underneath it.
Iapetus: The sceptic's verdict on sktime is the warmest of the night, with a caveat. Install it — it's free, it's the right abstraction, and it's the correct entry point into temporal modelling for someone who already thinks in scikit-learn. The caveat is scope: it is a research and learning tool, not a clinical-decision instrument. A forecast on retrospective vitals is a learning exercise and a possible research artefact; it is not a thing you act on at the bedside without the full validation apparatus. Learn it on a real dataset — the SoP cost data, even, or de-identified vitals — and keep it in the research lane.
Puck: One flag I've held to the end, because it's the lightest and the truest — "POV: a new feature enters the chat". It's a meme, a single image about the pace of release: you build around a capability, and a week later the platform ships it natively and your clever workaround is obsolete. For a clinician-builder that's not a joke, it's a planning principle. It's exactly why tonight's verdicts lean open-source and modular — the DALL-E-three deprecation last month, the model churn, the feature that lands and erases your weekend. You don't bet the pipeline on any single proprietary feature; you build loosely-coupled parts you can swap. The self-sent inbox is, in a way, a feed of features entering the chat — and the discipline is to catalogue, not to chase.
Charon: Before the wrap, the operator's version — what actually goes on the list this week, in order. One: install AnythingLLM, point it at the vault, set local embeddings plus a Claude profile — thirty minutes. Two: clone Understand-Anything and stand it up as a retrieval service the M-four can call — an afternoon, not urgent. Three: one Rodin asset for one MinuteMED segment, the thirty-minute trial that decides whether it earns a pipeline slot. Four: pip-install sktime and run a single forecast on the cost-tracker's own daily spend data — a real dataset already on disk, zero risk, genuine learning. Five: nothing on the Gemini speaker or Antigravity beyond a note to watch. Five items, one weekend, and the local-AI stack is real instead of aspirational.
Erinome: So we close. The headline held: this was a high-signal batch, and it resolved into a coherent toolkit rather than a list. Install AnythingLLM and stand up Understand-Anything as a sovereign retrieval layer, with MLX underneath and Claude as the authority. Keep Claude Code as the coding spine and treat loop engineering as the skill to deepen. Trial Rodin against one real med-ed asset, and keep the AI character-video tools on a short leash with the clinical-authority caveat. Install sktime in the research lane. Monitor the Gemini speaker as a signal, not a purchase.
Erinome: And note the dividend the sweep produced for free: the local-AI stack and the generative tools are, between them, most of the open-source production pipeline the medical-education strategy called for two days ago. The Vault entry tonight is Local-AI-Stack, for-review, holding that three-layer design. One last thing, on theme — this episode is itself the resolution of an open issue. The text-to-speech credit that produced this voice was the open question; the fact that you're hearing this at all is the answer. The pipeline is sovereign, the credit is live, and the batch is cleared. This has been State of Play. I'm Erinome. Better questions tomorrow.