Erinome: This is State of Play. I am Erinome, the standing anchor, and tonight we are following a single current that runs underneath four very different stories. The current is this. Power is moving closer to the edge. Closer to your own machine, closer to your own glasses, closer to your own workshop, and closer to the person who actually needs the help. For a decade the default answer to almost everything was the same. Send it to the cloud. A big model in a distant data centre. A subscription. Someone else's computer doing the thinking. Tonight we look at a week of news that all leans the other way. Open models small enough to run at home. Agent systems you assemble yourself out of parts. Mixed reality leaving the headset and landing on a pair of glasses. Making and home control that stays inside your own four walls. And, at the human end of the same line, care delivered to the people the old system priced out. Four clusters, one direction of travel. With me tonight are four voices. One who thinks like an engineer about models and agents, one who thinks about trust and what we give up when we hand over our judgement, one who lives in the workshop and the headset, and one who keeps asking who this actually reaches.
Orus: Orus here, in the methods seat. I will take the first cluster, which is the load-bearing one, because it sets up everything after it. The headline is easy to miss because it arrived as plumbing, not as a product. The interface that developers use to talk to one of the major model families has shifted to something built for stateful, agentic work as its primary mode. That sounds dry. It is not. For years the dominant way to use a large model was a single shot. You sent a prompt, you got an answer, the model remembered nothing, and any sense of an ongoing task lived in your own code. The move now is to make the ongoing task a first class thing the platform itself understands. Sessions that persist. State that carries. Tools the model can reach for across many turns without you stitching every step by hand.
Orus: Set that beside two other things from the same week and the shape gets clear. First, a new generation of small open models you can actually run yourself, with community events springing up around building lightweight tools on them. Second, and this is the part I love, people openly recreating the behaviour of a banned or unavailable frontier model not by training a giant of their own, but by wrapping a capable open model in an agent loop. A controller that plans, calls tools, checks its own work, and iterates. The lesson there is enormous and under appreciated. A modest model inside a good loop can stand in for a far larger model used naively. The intelligence is moving out of the single weights and into the scaffolding around them. And scaffolding is something an individual can build.
Despina: Despina here, in the ethics and risk seat, and I want to put a careful frame around that enthusiasm, because it is justified but it is not free. When the cleverness moves from the model into the loop, two things follow. The good one is sovereignty. You own the loop. It runs on your machine, your data does not leave, you can read every step, and you are no longer renting your own competence back from a vendor who can change the price or the rules tomorrow. That is real, and for someone working in a setting with poor connectivity or strict privacy duties it is close to decisive.
Despina: The hard one is that a loop is only as honest as the person who built it. A single cloud model at least has a vendor doing safety work you can point at. Your home built agent has you. When it plans, calls a tool, and acts on the result, every junction is a place where it can confidently do the wrong thing, and there is no one above it to catch the fall. So the discipline we talked about in past episodes comes straight back. The loop has to know what it does not know. It has to leave a trace you can read. It has to ask before it does anything it cannot undo. Local power and local responsibility are the same coin. You cannot pick up one side only.
Erinome: So the engineering gift of the week is that a person can now assemble something genuinely capable out of open parts, and the catch is that the judgement which used to live with a vendor now lives with the builder. Autonoe, this is squarely your territory. What does this cluster mean for the work we actually do?
Autonoe: Autonoe here. I will answer for the implementation side, because this lands directly on projects already on the bench. The single most useful idea this week is the agent loop around a small local model, and it maps almost one to one onto a rural clinical setting. Picture a clinic where the connection drops out for hours, where patient information must not leave the building, and where a registrar is carrying a heavy load alone. A frontier model in the cloud fails all three tests. A small open model on a local machine, wrapped in a careful loop, passes all three. It can summarise, it can check a dose against a local reference, it can draft and then critique its own draft, and it never phones home. For us that is not a thought experiment. It is the spine of the AI assisted resuscitation trainer and the local decision support thread, and it argues for building on open models we can hold in our own hands rather than renting a pipe that goes dark when the weather does.
Autonoe: The second idea worth banking is stateful sessions as a first class thing. We have spent real effort keeping a single assistant coherent across machines, and a platform that treats persistent state as native is the same problem solved one level down. The action I would suggest is a vault project entry under the publications and tooling work. Title it something like local agent loops for rural clinical settings. Capture the pattern, a small open model plus a planning loop plus a strict do not act without asking rule, and note the two candidate homes for it, the resuscitation trainer and the offline decision support. That cluster is high yield enough to deserve its own page, not a buried note.
Orus: Before we leave the cluster, let me put numbers to the intuition, because the economics are the whole argument and they are easy to wave past. A frontier cloud model charges you per use, forever, and the meter never stops. A small open model has a different shape entirely. There is a one time cost to stand it up, and after that the marginal cost of another thousand answers is electricity and time. For an occasional user the cloud is cheaper. For a heavy, repetitive workload, the kind a clinic or a research pipeline actually generates, the owned model crosses over and never looks back. And the gap between the two keeps narrowing from the other side as well, because each new generation of open weights does more with less. A model you can run on a single machine today would have been a data centre two years ago. The frontier is still ahead, but the floor is rising fast, and most real work does not need the frontier. It needs reliable and private and always available.
Despina: I would add the part that the benchmark charts never show, which is consistency. A vendor can change a hosted model underneath you with no notice, and a prompt that worked last month quietly degrades. When you own the weights, the thing does not move unless you move it. For a clinical tool that is not a minor convenience. It is the difference between a system you can validate once and trust, and a system you have to re validate every time someone you cannot see ships an update. Reproducibility is a safety property, and local ownership is how you get it. That is an argument that has nothing to do with cost and everything to do with whether you can stand behind what the tool does.
Autonoe: And that consistency point is the one I would underline for our pipeline specifically, because it connects to the publications work. A study that uses a model in its method has to be reproducible, and a hosted model that drifts breaks reproducibility silently. A pinned open model, run locally, is citable in a way a moving cloud endpoint is not. So the local turn is not only about the clinic keeping working when the line goes down. It is about being able to write down exactly what we did and have it still be true a year later. That is worth a line in the same vault page.
Erinome: Good. Hold that thread, because it reappears when we get to the glasses. Let us take the second cluster now, which is mixed reality finally leaving the headset.
Autonoe: This is the one I am most excited about, and the centre of gravity is a new pair of optical see through glasses that a lot of people are calling the most important device of the year. The claim worth examining is not the hardware specification. It is the category shift. A headset is a destination. You go into it, you are cut off, you come back out. Glasses are a layer. They sit on the world instead of replacing it, and that single difference changes what the device is for. The examples flying around this week tell the story. Learning an instrument with the guidance painted onto the real keys in front of you. Turning the glasses into a portable multi screen workstation so your desk follows you to a hospital tea room or a train. Hand tracking precise enough that your fingers become the interface. The through line is that the digital stops being a place you visit and becomes a property of the room you are already in.
Orus: And underneath that, quietly, is the same local turn we just described. There is a new open operating system for smart glasses whose whole pitch is write the app once and run it across different hardware, in the open, rather than inside one company's walled store. That matters more than any single pair of glasses, because the headset era was defined by locked platforms. An open layer for glasses is the difference between a device you develop for freely and a device you rent access to. If the optical hardware is the body, the open operating system is the part that decides whether this becomes a commons or a toll road. I would watch the operating system more closely than the lenses.
Despina: I want to name the risk before we get carried away, because eyewear that sees what you see is a different moral object from a headset you put on in private. Glasses that layer information onto the world also, by necessity, perceive the world, and increasingly the people in it. There is a clinical version of this that is genuinely promising, a clinician with guidance in their eye line and their hands free, and there is a surveillance version of the very same capability that is genuinely troubling. The deciding factor is not the device. It is whether capture is obvious, consented, and off by default. A tool worn on the face, in rooms with patients and families, has to wear its honesty on the outside. If you cannot tell when it is recording, it is built wrong.
Autonoe: Agreed, and that constraint actually sharpens the implementation idea rather than blocking it. For our work the glasses are not a consumer toy, they are a hands free clinical display, and the honest design follows from that. The implementation note I would bank is this. The resuscitation trainer and the procedure work both want a heads up display that shows the next step, the dose, the checklist item, without the operator looking away to a screen. An open glasses operating system means we could build that overlay once and not be hostage to a single vendor's headset. The vault entry here folds into the same page as the first cluster, because it is the same pattern wearing a different shell. Local compute, open platform, a display that respects the room. One device on order can start as a workstation and grow into a clinical overlay. That is a coherent path, not two separate bets.
Erinome: Two clusters in, and the rhyme is already obvious. Open beats locked, local beats remote, the layer beats the destination. Umbriel, before we reach the human end, take us through the third cluster, which is making and home control, because I think it is the same song in a different key.
Umbriel: Umbriel here. It is the same song, and the key is ownership. Look at what crossed the desk this week in the workshop bucket. A major release of the open three dimensional creation suite with better simulation, free for anyone. A new version of the open raw photo editor adding the kind of intelligent tooling that used to be locked behind a subscription. The open home automation platform whose entire reason to exist is local control, your home responding to you without a cloud account in the middle deciding whether you are allowed. And a quietly wise little note from a maker who spent money on machine upgrades before realising the real bottleneck was their own workflow. Put those together and the theme writes itself. The capability that used to require a rented account is arriving as something you own outright and run yourself.
Umbriel: And the home automation point deserves its own beat, because it is the domestic version of the clinical argument Autonoe just made. Local control means the lights and the sensors and the routines keep working when the internet does not, and it means the record of your own home does not live on a distant server you do not control. For most people that is a convenience. For someone who values privacy, or who lives where the connection is unreliable, it is the whole point. The same instinct that says run the model locally says run the house locally. It is one philosophy expressed at two scales.
Orus: There is an engineering caution to fold in, though, so we are honest about the cost. Owning the stack means maintaining the stack. The rented version hides its complexity behind a subscription and a support line. The owned version hands you both the freedom and the maintenance. The maker's note about workflow being the real bottleneck is the quiet truth of this whole cluster. The tools got free and powerful. The scarce resource moved. It is now your attention and your process, not the price of the software. Buying a faster machine or a cheaper open tool does nothing if the actual constraint is how you organise the work. That is not a reason to avoid owning your stack. It is a reason to invest in your own method as seriously as in your gear.
Autonoe: Which is a clean bridge to the implementation read, and it is a little against type. The action item from the making cluster is not a new purchase. It is a workflow audit. We have accumulated capable open tools, the three dimensional suite, the photo pipeline, the local automation, and the leverage now is in how they connect, not in adding another one. If there is a vault entry from this cluster it is a short, unglamorous one, a standard operating procedure for the open creative and home stack, so the bottleneck stops being which tool and starts being a process we have actually written down. Lower yield than the first cluster, so a note rather than a project page, but worth capturing while it is fresh.
Erinome: And that brings us to the fourth cluster, which sits at the far human end of the same line. Umbriel, this is the one that matters most, even though it made the least noise.
Umbriel: It is, and I want to slow down for it, because the first three clusters are about capability and this one is about who the capability reaches. Two small stories crossed the desk. A young engineer using three dimensional printing to make dentures for people on low incomes who had simply been priced out of dental care, giving them back something as ordinary and as enormous as a smile. And closer to home, a new public support program funding the people who care for loved ones living with dementia. On the surface they have nothing to do with open models or smart glasses. Underneath, they are the same turn. Capability moving to the edge, to the point of need, to the person the centralised system left out.
Despina: And this is where I want to push gently against the techno optimism of the first half of the episode, because the two halves have to be held together or the whole thing curdles. It is easy to celebrate a printer that makes cheap dentures and quietly conclude that technology will simply solve access. It will not, on its own. The denture story is not really a story about a printer. It is a story about a person who decided that the people the market ignored were worth serving, and then used an available tool to do it. The tool was necessary and nowhere near sufficient. The carer support program makes the same point from the other side. No device helps the exhausted person looking after a parent with dementia at two in the morning. What helps them is funded human time and recognition. The honest position is that the local turn creates possibility, and only human intention turns possibility into care.
Umbriel: That is exactly right, and it is why this cluster, quiet as it was, is the one I would weight most for our own work. The whole thread of the rural health projects is precisely this. Capability at the edge, in the hands of the clinician and the patient who the centralised system reaches last. The denture maker and the carer fund are not off topic. They are the mission statement, told by other people in other fields. The implementation read is less a technical note and more a compass check. When we choose what to build with the local agent loop and the clinical glasses, the test is not how clever it is. It is whether it reaches the person at the far end of the line who would otherwise be missed. I would suggest the vault captures that as a principle on the front of the projects page, not as a separate entry. A sentence that says the point of building local is to reach the edge, and the edge means people, not just machines.
Erinome: Let us draw the four together, because the synergy is the real episode and each cluster only half states it. Orus, the through line in one breath.
Orus: Compute, creation, and now care are all decentralising at once, and the same five disciplines govern all of them. Own the loop, but know its limits. Prefer open and local, but accept the maintenance. Make the system honest about what it perceives and what it is unsure of. Invest in method, not just tools. And measure the whole thing by who it reaches, not by how advanced it is. The week looked like four unrelated stories. It is one story about power moving outward, and about the responsibility that travels with it.
Despina: And I will add the warning that keeps the optimism honest. Decentralisation is not automatically virtuous. It moves the power outward, and it moves the responsibility outward with it, to people who did not ask for it and may not be equipped for it. A locked cloud at least concentrated the duty of care somewhere you could name. The local turn scatters that duty across every builder and every owner. So the thing we should be cultivating, in ourselves first, is the maturity to hold power we are not forced to hold well. The glasses, the agent loop, the local home, the printed denture, each one hands a person more capability and more accountability in the same motion. The good future is not the one with the most capability at the edge. It is the one where the people at the edge carry it wisely.
Autonoe: From the bench, the concrete takeaways. One, build on small open models in a careful loop, because they pass the rural tests a cloud model fails, and start the vault page for it. Two, treat the glasses on order as the start of a hands free clinical overlay, on an open platform, with capture honest by default. Three, the next gain in the creative and home stack is a written workflow, not another tool. Four, weight everything by reach. The first cluster is the highest yield and earns a project page tonight. The rest are notes and a principle.
Umbriel: And the human note to close my part. The most moving thing on the desk this week was not a model or a pair of glasses. It was a person giving someone back their smile, and a fund giving a tired carer some recognition. Keep those next to the technical wins, because they are what the technical wins are for.
Erinome: That is the episode. Four clusters, one current. Power moving to the edge, in the model you can run, the glasses you can wear, the home you can own, and the care you can finally reach. The capability is arriving faster than the wisdom to hold it, which means the scarce resource is no longer compute or cleverness. It is judgement, and the willingness to aim all of this at the person furthest down the line. I am Erinome. Thank you for listening to State of Play.