Zephyr: Zephyr here — anchoring State of Play episode thirty-one, Saturday the twenty-third of May, twenty twenty-six. This is the first episode on the new v two point two audio pipeline — Comparsa intro stinger you just heard, a body-matched outro at the back end, target loudness lifted to minus thirteen LUFS for a punchier signal across Spotify and YouTube native. We're running about forty minutes today. The brief is a portfolio sweep — Jacob asked for a state-of-the-portfolio episode pulling together the active projects and surfacing what's blocking each, what decisions he owes, and the recommended next moves. Plus a focused refresh on the Sepsis Poster Studio given the May tech releases. Eight live projects, plus the meta line on State of Play itself, plus a deep treatment of where the Stage nine video pipeline should go now that LTX-Video two point three, Wan two point two, and SANA-WM have all landed in the last three weeks. Five voices in cast — Schedar on builds, Puck on industry-room, Sadachbia on push-back, Despina on ethics and the wrap. Brand voice Alnilam at the back end. The convention you'll hear in each portfolio item is the same — one sentence on what the project is, one line on the single biggest decision pending or "locked, executing," one line on the single biggest blocker, and a concrete next step. Let's get into it.
Schedar: Schedar speaking — project one, the Aussie Boxing App. This one's the cleanest of the eight because the decisions are already locked. Jacob landed his six-letter reply on the twenty-third — a one, b two, c one, d four, e one, f three. In English that's — build independently and court Boxing Australia as a customer-partner later; spin a fresh Pty Ltd specifically for the platform with liability isolation from Hurn Medical; bootstrap to MVP from personal capital and reinvested revenue; tight-scope MVP on medical compliance only — digital Boxer Competition Record book, ringside medical workflow, bout-to-bout suspension auto-enforcement; React Native on talent-pool grounds overriding the brief's draft star for Flutter; and state-federation-first via Boxing SA before Boxing Australia. The whole strategic, regulatory, financial and risk scaffolding moved with that lock. Decision locked, executing.
Puck: Puck here — what it actually looks like in the room. The single biggest blocker on Aussie Boxing App is not technical and it's not regulatory — it's a single conversation. Allison Goodes, President of Boxing SA, Council Delegate to Boxing Australia, and Jacob's existing ringside-doctor counterparty at Riverland tournaments since twenty twenty-five. The drafts are sitting in the same folder — the introductory message, the follow-up brief, the proposal-for-conversation. The conversation has not been initiated. Until that lands, the three-month plan is paused at line one. The Goodes surname also points toward a likely family link to Boxing Australia Chairperson Phillip Goodes — a question Jacob should ask Allison directly, gently, on the first call, not assume from search results. Next concrete step — Jacob sends the introductory message to Allison this week. Three days of latency lost is fine; three weeks compounds to a Sport eighty entering Australia win on the back of their England Boxing success, and the project becomes non-viable. Speed via Boxing SA is the strategic moat. Move.
Zephyr: Zephyr — project two. Respond Global. Dr Ian Norton's humanitarian medicine organisation, met at the POCUS course on the seventeenth.
Schedar: Schedar — Respond Global is a deliberate, multi-strand external engagement. Four strands sequenced — AI advisor first to build credibility; operational volunteering second; deployable clinician arc third in year three plus; ACRRM ED AST supervision enquiry fourth. The full vault scaffold went in on the twenty-third — thirteen sibling documents, seventy-eight numbered citations across strategic plan, engagement proposal, quarterly plans, market analysis, stakeholder map, regulatory compliance, capability map, financial model, risk register, references. Decisions queued — six lettered a through f. Ada's starred default is a one, b two, c two, d two, e one, f one — AI advisor first; scoped advisor agreement; four to eight hours per week; raise ED AST gently in Q one then defer; quiet engagement until something formal exists; volunteer in year one, revisit at six months.
Sadachbia: Sadachbia — push-back. The single biggest blocker on Respond Global is Jacob himself. The decisions are pending Jacob's endorsement. The email to Norton has not been sent. The target send date was the twenty-seventh of May — that's four days from today. Norton has not yet been told the proposition exists. The pre-send checklist is six items long — a final read-aloud of the email, a placeholder POCUS reference filled with something specific Jacob actually remembers from the seventeenth, time options cross-checked against the YN LHN roster, Appendix A laid out as a clean PDF for attachment, the subject line confirmed, decisions a through f endorsed by Jacob and Jo where relevant. None of that takes more than ninety minutes of focused work. The next concrete step here is the same as Aussie Boxing — Jacob sits down once this week, makes the six-letter call, finalises the email, and sends. The cost of slippage on Respond Global is lower than on Aussie Boxing because the field isn't competitive in the same way, but slippage still erodes the warm-introduction signal. The seventeenth-of-May POCUS course is the warm referral. Use it before it cools.
Zephyr: Zephyr — project three. Phlox. The open-source clinical-scribe cluster.
Puck: Puck — Phlox in a sentence. A four-repo open-source clinical-scribe cluster Jacob bookmarked on the nineteenth of May — Phlox as the headline candidate reported as Australian-built but provenance not yet publicly verifiable, OpenScribe by Sam Margolis, OpenHealth from the OpenHealthForAll team, and StenoAI from Ruzin. The project frame is — can a fully local-first M four-resident open-source stack equal the regulatory, clinical, and data-sovereignty posture of the commercial Australian-cloud incumbent? The honest scoping-stage answer is — probably no for routine clinical work, plausibly yes for Indigenous-data-sovereignty edge cases and research applications, definitely yes as a learning artefact. Five decisions queued for Jacob — a one Phlox first, b one Jacob's own consultations only with explicit consent over two weeks, c two Ollama plus Llama three point three seventy-billion, d one verbal consent documented in note, e two tell YN LHN IT in month two after personal evaluation. All starred defaults.
Sadachbia: Sadachbia — push-back. The single biggest blocker on Phlox is decision a — and it's not the lettered decision itself, it's the gate underneath it. Phlox is the lead candidate because the maintainer's project name is botanical, the README tone reads Australian, and a haematology background is suggested by the GitHub handle. None of that is verification. The maintainer's actual location, residency, and clinical background are not disclosed in their public profile. If Jacob commits to Phlox on the implicit promise of Australian provenance and the maintainer turns out to be European or American, the Indigenous-data-sovereignty argument weakens — Phlox is still local-first, but the "Australian-built local-first open-source clinical scribe" narrative collapses. The next concrete step is — Jacob, or Alan Turing Ross on Jacob's behalf, sends a direct email to the Phlox maintainer this week, asks the question civilly, and waits for the answer before installation begins. If the answer comes back yes, the five decisions stand. If it comes back no, OpenScribe by Sam Margolis becomes the lead candidate by philosophical-alignment grounds, and the decision string changes to a three.
Despina: Despina — ethics turn. There's a second blocker on Phlox that deserves naming. Even with the right maintainer story, the clinical-record liability surface of a non-certified open-source scribe sits inside the MIPS indemnity question. A Heidi error is supported by vendor contracts and TGA scribe-software-class regulation. A Phlox error is supported by an MIT licence saying no warranty. The honest sequencing is — Jacob notifies MIPS before any installation, even on his own consultations only. MIPS does not require this notification for a two-week single-clinician trial, but documenting the trial in a written MIPS exchange means that if anything ever surfaces later, the indemnity record shows transparency. That's a forty-five-minute letter. It runs in parallel with the maintainer-provenance email. Both can be done in one evening.
Zephyr: Zephyr — project four. POCUS — the consolidated parent project.
Schedar: Schedar — POCUS in one sentence. Consolidated parent project for Jacob's point-of-care ultrasound work, coordinating the Hardware-Selection sub-project — handheld device comparison and procurement brief — and the Learning-Resource sub-project — the published fourteen-module Ross-POCUS site already live on GitHub Pages — plus the multi-year strategic, regulatory, financial, stakeholder and risk scaffolding that turns isolated POCUS strands into a coordinated credentialing-plus-curation-plus-curriculum programme at PPRHS and the Mid-North. Five decisions queued — a personal device choice, b credentialing path, c learning resource priority audience, d PPRHS governance proposal timing, e public surface. Starred defaults — a two GE Vscan Air SL without Caption AI on subscription-bricks-the-device failure-mode grounds, b one ASUM CCPU comprehensive as the credential moat, c two Mid-North regional clinicians as the priority audience, d two governance proposal lodged after CCPU Phase one is underway, e one quiet public surface with the learning resource on Meridian only.
Puck: Puck — industry room. The hardware decision is solved with caveats — Vscan Air SL ranks top in the Bayrak twenty twenty-four study, paired with FDA-cleared Caption AI for real-time view-acquisition guidance, hardware-keeps-working-without-subscription failure mode, Australian channel established. The financial case for year one is qualitative — fifteen thousand five hundred Australian dollars cash spend in the mid case, MBS revenue realistically zero, value side accrues via two avoided rural-to-Adelaide transfers per year paying for the device. Multi-year economics defensible.
Sadachbia: Sadachbia — push-back, and this is the one to listen to. The single biggest blocker on POCUS is not the device decision and not the governance proposal. It's the CCPU primary clinical supervisor. Without a confirmed supervisor in place, ASUM CCPU regulations do not let the log book accrue, the summative cannot be sat, the qualification cannot issue, and the entire credentialing wedge collapses. The hardware spend without a supervisor is bad sequencing. The recommended sequencing is — confirm CCPU primary supervisor before lodging the hardware purchase order, even if it delays Q one by one month. Two parallel candidates are lined up; Jacob has identified them in the stakeholder map. The next concrete step is — Jacob writes to both candidates this week, frames the ask cleanly, and waits for one to commit before the device demo emails go out. Supervisor first. Device second. Governance proposal third. In that order.
Zephyr: Zephyr — project five. Creative Tools — the parent project for the Ross creativity toolkit.
Schedar: Schedar — Creative Tools is locked and executing. Five paid subscriptions, one free workhorse, three local installs. The locked stack — Gamma Plus at twelve Australian dollars a month for the drafting layer; Canva Pro AU at twelve ninety-nine for the finishing layer; Claude Pro already paid for orchestration via Ada and Claude Design for layout; ChatGPT Plus already paid for the GPT five point four Thinking planner and gpt-image-two web access; Adobe Firefly Standard at fifteen for the indemnification layer; Google Stitch free as the workhorse for UI prototypes; and the local Apple Silicon trio of mflux plus FLUX two-dev, ComfyUI plus Wan two point two, and ComfyUI plus LTX-Video two point three. Marginal cost above Jacob's pre-existing baseline is forty Australian dollars a month. The five letter-format decisions were locked on the twenty-first of May. Day thirty, sixty, and ninety review triggers are in the calendar. Decisions locked, executing.
Despina: Despina — ethics turn on Creative Tools, briefly, because it matters. The constraints that bind every decision on this stack are not pricing — they're identifiable-person risk, indemnification, clinical accuracy, and Aboriginal data sovereignty. Every cloud video tool's terms of service shift consent burden to the user. Patient photos, identifiable Rotarians without written consent, staff — none of that goes to any cloud generator. The local cluster — FLUX two, Wan two point two, LTX-Video two point three — is the only fully safe path for any image touching personal health information. Only Adobe Firefly provides enterprise IP indemnification. Every image and video model still hallucinates Australian-specific clinical detail — PBS packaging, SA Health branding, RACGP forms, RACMA letterheads. Senior clinician verification is mandatory on every artefact destined for clinical use. And any historical photo of Aboriginal community members from Port Pirie, Nukunu, or Adnyamathanha country routes through community gatekeepers before any AI processing. Marie Curie Ross sign-off is required. These are not afterthoughts. They are the project's load-bearing constraints.
Zephyr: Zephyr — project six. Meridian — the Next.js dashboard application running on the M four. This one's interesting because the decisions are locked but the project is gated on a single twenty-five-dollar action.
Schedar: Schedar — Meridian in one sentence. A Next.js fourteen app with server-side SQLite via better-sqlite three and over fifty API routes that read and write the local Obsidian vault, running on Jacob's personal M four Mac mini fronted by Tailscale Funnel — which has been the dominant failure mode since the ninth-to-eleventh-of-May SoP-publish incident broke it for roughly thirty-eight hours. The brief recommended a two-phase migration. Phase A this week, about three and a quarter hours of Ada-executable work — replace Tailscale Funnel with Cloudflare Tunnel and Cloudflare Access, gate the site behind email one-time-PIN plus WebAuthn passkey at NIST eight hundred-sixty-three-B AAL two, point a freshly-registered meridian dot rossfamily dot au at it, add uptime monitoring and error tracking. Phase B optional, four to six weeks later, migrates the application off the M four to a Hetzner CAX eleven ARM VPS. Six decisions queued — a architecture, b authentication strength, c domain, d public landing page, e collaborator access on day one, f migration window. All starred defaults locked at the Cloudflare-Tunnel-plus-Access path on the M four, AAL two with passkey, register rossfamily dot au at VentraIP, full gate on every URL, Jacob plus Jo from day one, Ada executes Phase A autonomously over a few days batching gates into a single twenty-five-minute Jacob sitting.
Sadachbia: Sadachbia — push-back, and this one is the strangest blocker in the portfolio because it's so small. The single biggest blocker on Meridian is — the VentraIP domain rossfamily dot au has not yet been registered. That's about twenty-five Australian dollars at the registrar of choice. It's the only thing gating Phase A execution. Without the domain, Cloudflare can't host the zone. Without the zone, the tunnel can't terminate on a public hostname. Without the public hostname, Cloudflare Access can't be configured. Nothing downstream moves. Jacob has authorised the system-level launchd daemon for cloudflared as the only sanctioned exception to the no-system-daemon sovereignty rule — that authority is granted. The cloudflared install waits for the domain. The next concrete step is — Jacob spends fifteen minutes at the VentraIP site this week, registers rossfamily dot au with auto-renewal, returns the two Cloudflare nameservers to VentraIP, and waits the one-to-twenty-four hours for global NS propagation. After that, Ada can execute Phase A in a single Saturday session.
Puck: Puck — and to ground this — the cost of inaction on Meridian is real. The dashboard runs Sepsis CARE poster review at slash review, holds the bedside live build-progress display for Stage nine renders, surfaces the project status across the eight portfolio items we're discussing right now. When Meridian goes down, Jacob loses the operational read on his own work. Phase A spends twenty-five dollars on a domain and a Saturday afternoon. The payoff is uptime, real authentication at hospital terminals, a memorable hostname Jacob can actually remember at work, port-collision immunity from the SoP darkhttpd that wedged Meridian for thirty-eight hours, and an Australian edge presence at Cloudflare's Sydney-Melbourne-Brisbane-Perth PoP set. The cost of doing nothing is the wedge happens again. Register the domain.
Zephyr: Zephyr — project seven. PICC Credentialing PPRHS. Credentialing pathway for Jacob to become the accredited PICC, midline, and non-tunnelled CVC proceduralist at Port Pirie.
Schedar: Schedar — PICC Credentialing in one sentence. Twelve-month pathway, June twenty twenty-six through June twenty twenty-seven, sequenced under ASUM CCPU Vascular Access, ACEM P seven three three, ACSQHC iCARE, INS Infusion Therapy Standards, governed through the YN LHN Credentialing and Scope of Practice Committee. The MIPS letter was committed to the project folder today. Five fields for Jacob to fill before sending — MIPS member number at the head of the letter, professional email and direct phone, the year he joined MIPS, the dates of the RAH Vascular Access Service supervised practice block which currently assumes the fourteenth of September through the ninth of October twenty twenty-six but may shift, and the date at the head of the letter. The letter targets five-hundred-thirty words, asks for written indemnity opinion on five specific scope questions — conditions of cover, complication management, post-credentialing ongoing supervision, excluded patient cohorts, and ultrasound-guidance plus minimum-annual-volume expectations.
Puck: Puck — industry-room reading of this. The MIPS letter is the single most consequential action of the entire credentialing pathway. MIPS will not commit to an indemnity loading or position without the formal written request. YN LHN will not accept a credentialing application without indemnity sign-off in writing. The order of operations is — MIPS letter first, then the ASUM CCPU online theory module enrolment same evening, then the RAH Vascular Access Service observership negotiation by August twenty twenty-six, then the YN LHN Credentialing Committee submission in November twenty twenty-six, then the six-insertion supervised pilot from January through May twenty twenty-seven, then independent practice from June twenty twenty-seven. The single highest-risk barrier downstream is supervised insertion volume — PPRHS will not generate the ASUM CCPU minimum of twenty-five supervised insertions in any reasonable timeframe, and the RAH observership at roughly ten PICCs per day across cancer, ICU, parenteral nutrition, and difficult-access referrals is the mitigation. That observership must be agreed in writing by August. Late agreement collapses the timeline.
Sadachbia: Sadachbia — push-back. The blocker on PICC Credentialing this week is the five fields. They're trivial fields — Jacob's own MIPS number, his professional email and phone, the year he joined MIPS, the supervised-block dates. None of them require research. None of them require a decision. They require ten minutes at a desk with a current MIPS membership card in hand. Once filled, the letter sends to info at mips dot com dot au with the subject line on the letter intact. MIPS typically replies in twenty-one days. That brings the indemnity response into mid-June, which leaves five months of runway before the November Credentialing Committee submission. The next concrete step is — Jacob spends ten minutes filling the five fields and sending the letter. Not next week. This week.
Zephyr: Zephyr — project eight. Sepsis CARE twenty twenty-six. Jacob's clinical-lead role.
Despina: Despina — Sepsis CARE in one sentence, with care for the parked-status nuance. Rural Sepsis CARE twenty twenty-six is the YN LHN sepsis awareness and improvement campaign — Communicate, Act, Recognise, Escalate. Jacob is Clinical Lead. The status in memory is parked — the campaign infrastructure shipped — seventy-eight of ninety posters generated as of the fifteenth of April, the CEIH sepsis-lead interview complete, the STOP SEPSIS public-awareness acronym locked across signs and symptoms, infographic, and animation assets. The recent cross-link is the Joondalup Sandipan Dhar coronial finding from Western Australia — Acting State Coroner Sarah Linton ruled the death of a twenty-one-month-old from sepsis on a background of undiagnosed acute lymphoblastic leukaemia probably preventable, and made six recommendations covering communication, documentation, discharge, staffing, nursing training, GP-ED communication, and CALD considerations. The Joondalup workstream extension was drafted on the eighteenth — four actions transferable to PPRHS — GP letter receipt protocol, paediatric sepsis recognition refresher, paediatric seventy-two-hour re-presentation audit, twelve-month GP-ED communication audit.
Schedar: Schedar — concrete. The next steps on Sepsis CARE this week are not the campaign infrastructure — that's shipped. They're the Joondalup workstream extension. Action one — draft Action one protocol — GP letter receipt — within two weeks; that's a one-PowerChart audit field plus a nursing-triage SOP update. Action three — M and M agenda template update for paediatric seventy-two-hour re-presentations — within two weeks; that's adding a single agenda item and an ED audit data pull. The Aboriginal community governance contact for the Action two teaching session needs initiating this fortnight. Action four — the twelve-month GP-ED communication audit — is the HAC grant deliverable, scoping in six weeks. The thirty-sixty-ninety plan is in the project folder. The block is not capacity — it's the Clinical Governance Committee meeting cycle. Jacob slots the four protocols into the next CG meeting.
Sadachbia: Sadachbia — and a brief push-back. The Dhar case as teaching exemplar requires family consent. If the Dhar family's situation does not permit teaching-case use, equivalent published cases substitute — there is no shortage of published paediatric sepsis missed-diagnosis cases in the medico-legal literature. The teaching framing must also be reviewed by Aboriginal community governance even though the Dhar family is CALD rather than Aboriginal or Torres Strait Islander — the same respectful-use-of-family-stories principle applies. The execution plan in the project folder names both checks. Don't run Action two ahead of those.
Zephyr: Zephyr — project nine. The meta line — State of Play itself. Which is the episode you're currently listening to.
Puck: Puck — State of Play in one sentence. The Ross-family podcast pipeline you're hearing right now, shipped from the M four through GitHub Pages, with a Gemini Flash TTS engine, Kevin MacLeod Incompetech royalty-free intro and outro stings under Creative Commons attribution, episode-thirty-one as the first episode on the v two point two audio pipeline. The v two point two patch landed in three coordinated changes pushed by Jacob today — first, add a music intro stinger — episodes previously started cold with the anchor voice; v two point two prepends Comparsa from Kevin MacLeod's Elegant Piano collection with a structured duck-and-fade recipe around the anchor's first turn. Second, volume-match the outro stinger to the episode body — the v two point one outro was at a fixed relative gain and the local integrated loudness drifted from the body's; v two point two measures the cast body and applies a uniform gain to the intro and outro segments so both sit at body loudness before the master loudnorm pass. Third — shift target loudness from minus sixteen LUFS to minus thirteen LUFS, a three decibel bump that maps to roughly twenty-five percent perceived-loudness gain — that's the corrected interpretation Jacob locked today; the earlier draft read it as amplitude plus twenty-five percent which would have landed at minus fourteen; perceived plus twenty-five percent lands at minus thirteen, and minus thirteen is where we are. Spotify and YouTube native, inside Apple Podcasts' accept-without-renormalisation tolerance.
Sadachbia: Sadachbia — push-back on the v two point two synthetic-validation question, because it's the only honest unknown in the room right now. The synthetic validation in build slash v two point two-validation landed the test master at minus thirteen LUFS plus or minus zero point five and true-peak less than or equal to minus one dBTP under the corrected target. That's the metric outcome. What synthetic validation can't tell you is whether the intro stinger sounds right — whether the duck-and-fade timing reads as professional or feels mechanical, whether the body-loudness-match on the outro produces a clean exit or a noticeable level jump on the Alnilam tagline, whether the Comparsa motif at the start sets the right register for a portfolio-sweep episode. The answer to those questions is in the production master we render tonight, not in the synthetic test. Worth flagging to dispatch in the close-out — the synthetic test passed; the production test is the one Jacob will hear.
Zephyr: Zephyr — that's segment A complete. Eight projects plus the meta line. The short read for Jacob is — four immediate decisions to ship this week: Allison Goodes outreach for Aussie Boxing App, the six-letter reply and email send for Respond Global, the maintainer email for Phlox plus the MIPS notification, the supervisor letter for POCUS, the domain registration for Meridian, the five letter fields for the PICC MIPS letter, and the four-protocol Sepsis CARE submission to the next Clinical Governance Committee. Most of those are under ninety minutes of work. The single biggest portfolio risk is Aussie Boxing App because the field is competitive — Sport eighty is the named threat — and inaction this week compounds badly. The single smallest blocker is Meridian — twenty-five dollars at VentraIP. Let's pivot to segment B. Sepsis Poster Studio. The Stage nine video pipeline refresh.
Schedar: Schedar — Sepsis Poster Studio current state, in one paragraph. Workflow pipeline web app for composing styled A one sepsis awareness posters at PPRHS. Stages one through nine — patient group parsed from the vault, art style from six canonical styles, target format, image prompt auto-composed and editable, image generation via OpenAI's gpt-image-two, title and supporting copy, layout template from four templates, live preview scaled to the target canvas, and Stage nine — the accompanying video. Stage nine currently defaults to an offline ffmpeg Ken Burns stub — pure parallax zoom on the poster image with a freeze tail. Veo, Kling, Seedance, and Runway are all scaffolded with the same provider-class pattern in video underscore gen dot py — the dispatcher is provider-agnostic, every provider implements the same protocol, every provider currently returns a stub-fallback because the API keys are placeholders. The architecture is clean. The question for tonight is which of the May twenty twenty-six releases changes the recommendation for which provider should be the default.
Puck: Puck — Stage four image generation. The current default is gpt-image-two via OpenAI API, released the twenty-first of April twenty twenty-six, API generally available early May, snapshot pin gpt-image-two-dash-twenty-twenty-six-dash-zero-four-dash-twenty-one. First OpenAI image model with reasoning built in — the so-called "thinking mode" — supports flexible sizes and high-fidelity image inputs at one-thousand-twenty-four by one-thousand-five-hundred-thirty-six portrait. The May twenty twenty-six cohort it sits in includes — Midjourney v seven, Ideogram v three, FLUX two-dev which is the local-on-Apple-Silicon option, and Recraft V four for vector-aware text-in-image. The Creative Tools project has locked the stack — gpt-image-two stays the default Stage four engine. There's no current case to swap. The reasoning-mode advantage and the high-fidelity image-input affordance line up with the Sepsis Poster Studio prompt patterns, and the prompt library that Stage four uses has been tuned against gpt-image-two specifically. Recommendation — leave Stage four. Don't fix what isn't broken.
Sadachbia: Sadachbia — and here's the substantive push-back for segment B. Stage nine — the video stage — is the live question. The ffmpeg Ken Burns stub is shipping working output, and that's the question Ada flagged in the SANA-WM scoping brief on the nineteenth — is the stub good enough for now, or is it actively blocking the kind of accompanying video Jacob wants for the poster series. The cohort the brief surveyed — Veo three point one, Kling two point five Pro, Seedance one point five Pro, Runway Gen four point five — are all closed cloud. Each charges per clip — fifty cents to one Australian dollar fifty for Veo, thirty cents to one dollar for Kling, forty cents to one dollar twenty for Seedance, sixty cents to one dollar eighty for Runway, per five-second clip. Five-to-ten-second clip length only. Cloud-only. Content goes to the vendor. None of them are sized correctly for a charitable Sepsis CARE programme where the poster catalogue is approaching ninety items and the video output is one accompanying clip per poster.
Schedar: Schedar — the open-weights cohort that landed in the last three weeks shifts the picture. SANA-WM dropped on the fourteenth of May, NVIDIA, two point six billion parameters, sixty-second native clip length at seven-hundred-twenty pixels, six degree-of-freedom metric-scale camera control, NVIDIA Open Model License which permits commercial use. The catch is — weights are not yet on Hugging Face. The collection page lists zero models linking the paper as of the eighteenth of May fetch. The paper exists. The code path under NVlabs slash Sana exists with Apache two licence. The weights do not exist publicly yet. SANA-Video and LongSANA, the natural-bridge from the same lab, are released — same NVIDIA Open Model License, two billion parameters, five to sixty seconds at four-hundred-eighty pixels, text-only conditioning. Wan two point two from Alibaba — Apache two licence, one point three to twenty-seven billion parameters across the model range, eight point one nine gigabytes of VRAM on the small variant, five seconds at four-hundred-eighty to seven-hundred-twenty pixels. LTX-Video two point three from Lightricks — twelve gigabytes of VRAM on the FP eight variant, five to ten seconds at twelve-hundred-sixteen by seven-hundred-four, Apache-equivalent OpenRAIL-M licence, Apple Silicon native.
Despina: Despina — licence reconfiguration. The Sepsis Poster Studio operates in the charitable and clinical-educational shape — SISU Charity communications, Rural Sepsis CARE community awareness, PPRHS clinical-education materials, no revenue. That shape sits squarely within the NVIDIA Open Model License's stated intent — applications in educational or creative tools is one of the model card's enumerated direct uses. It also sits within Apache two for Wan two point two and OpenRAIL-M for LTX-Video. All three open-weights options have clean licence paths for the studio's current shape. The closed cloud options — Veo, Kling, Seedance, Runway — also permit commercial-output use, but each shifts consent burden to the user, which is the load-bearing constraint when posters may incorporate identifiable elements from PPRHS clinical scenes. The clean answer on licence grounds is — local open-weights, not closed cloud.
Puck: Puck — the local-versus-cloud decision, grounded in hardware. Jacob's compute substrate is the M four Mac mini with Apple Silicon, one-hundred-twenty-eight gigabytes unified memory. The Creative Tools stack has already locked the local trio — mflux plus FLUX two-dev for image, ComfyUI plus Wan two point two for short video, ComfyUI plus LTX-Video two point three for the Sepsis Studio Stage nine fallback. Both Wan two point two and LTX-Video two point three run on Apple Silicon. SANA-WM, when the weights arrive, will not — the paper and code are CUDA-targeted; no Metal Performance Shaders backend exists for the SANA video family; no Apple MLX port has been announced. So for the M four, the choices reduce to Wan two point two or LTX-Video two point three. LTX-Video is the brief's recommended default — Apple Silicon native, twelve gigabytes VRAM, faster than real-time on capable hardware, OpenRAIL-M licence, two-billion FP eight variant fits comfortably. Wan two point two is the alternate — Apache two is a slightly cleaner licence, multilingual including Chinese, smaller model loads in eight point one nine gigabytes.
Sadachbia: Sadachbia — and the substantive question is — which of LTX-Video two point three and Wan two point two replaces the ffmpeg stub as the new default Stage nine engine. The brief's recommendation, locked twenty May in the Creative Tools stack-decisions document, is LTX-Video two point three as the Stage nine default. The rationale was — fits the Sepsis Studio data-sovereignty principle, one-time setup cost, unlimited iteration, Kling two point six Pro via fal dot ai reserved for one-off launch clips where cinematic quality matters and no patient context is on screen. SANA-WM weights remain pending — LTX-Video two point three is the default if SANA-WM doesn't land by project deadline. That decision is unchanged. The refresh is that the rationale is now stronger, not weaker. Wan two point two has arrived as a credible local alternate. SANA-Video is available now as the SANA-family bridge. The closed cloud cohort has stabilised pricing without meaningful capability gains over Veo three point one. Local-first is the answer; LTX-Video two point three is the default; Wan two point two is the secondary local; closed cloud is the cinematic one-off exception.
Schedar: Schedar — implementation plan, concrete. Step one — install ComfyUI on the M four. Native Apple Silicon build is available, takes about an hour including dependency resolution. Step two — pull LTX-Video two point three FP eight weights. About six gigabytes; download time depends on home connection but the model card lists CDN-hosted weights so it's fast. Step three — extend the video gen dot py dispatcher with a new provider class — LTXVideoProvider — following the existing scaffolded-provider pattern. The class implements the same protocol every other provider implements — generate with end image path, start image path, motion prompt, duration in seconds, target dims, run dir, freeze tail seconds, fps. The provider dispatches to a local ComfyUI HTTP endpoint instead of a cloud API. Step four — add LTX-Video to the PROVIDER underscore COST underscore PER underscore SECOND table at zero cost, to PROVIDER underscore LABELS as "LTX-Video two point three local on Apple Silicon," and to the PROVIDERS registry. Step five — add the same lines for Wan two point two as a secondary local provider. Step six — change the Stage nine UI default from "stub" to "ltx" and grey out the other options with appropriate tooltips. Estimated work — three hours for an Alan Turing Ross-dispatched task. Reversible — the stub remains the universal fallback when any provider returns the fallback dict.
Puck: Puck — expected throughput and monthly cost. LTX-Video two point three at twelve gigabytes VRAM on the M four — Apple Silicon unified memory makes that comfortable — produces a five-to-ten-second clip in roughly thirty to ninety seconds wall-clock, faster than real-time on the small-model variant per the documentation. For Sepsis Poster Studio's expected cadence — one accompanying video per poster, ninety posters in the catalogue, perhaps two or three iterations per poster as the script and prompt refine — that's around two-hundred-seventy clips lifetime, ten or so per active campaign month. Wall-clock time per month — under an hour of M four compute. Monthly cost — zero dollars. Zero. Compare to closed cloud at the same volume — ten clips per month at one dollar fifty per clip averaged across providers, fifteen dollars a month, one-hundred-eighty dollars a year, plus the consent surface and the data-sovereignty cost. The local-first answer is the right answer on every dimension.
Sadachbia: Sadachbia — and the residual question is — when SANA-WM weights eventually drop, does Stage nine swap? The brief's recommendation is tier B — adopt soon, not now. Three trigger conditions for tier promotion to A — SANA-WM weights appear on the Hugging Face Efficient-Large-Model slash sana-wm collection in any quantisation; confirmed inference recipe published for twenty-four gigabytes VRAM or less; either Alien node confirms sub-fifteen-minute inference on a sixty-second seven-hundred-twenty-pixel clip end-to-end, or Jacob accepts cloud H one-hundred-hour rental at roughly four Australian dollars per hour as the run-mode. When all three trigger, integration is the same dispatcher-extension pattern as for LTX-Video — about ninety minutes of additional work. Until then, LTX-Video two point three on the M four is the default. The SANA-WM watch is — check the Hugging Face collection page weekly. The Sepsis Studio doesn't have to chase the latest model. The latest model has to clear the integration tier.
Despina: Despina — and one more ethical thread before we wrap segment B. Even with local-first inference, the Sepsis Poster Studio sits at the intersection of clinical communication, public health awareness, and — if any poster ever incorporates encounter-derived content even indirectly — Indigenous data sovereignty. The five constraints in the Creative Tools stack-decisions document are not optional for this studio either. Senior clinician verification before any artefact destined for clinical use. Marie Curie Ross sign-off before any cloud upload of historical photographs from Aboriginal community archives. No identifiable patient features in any image, full stop. The studio's data-sovereignty principle is not a side note — it is the reason the local stack exists. LTX-Video two point three is the right tool because it is the local tool. The licence is permissive enough; the inference is fast enough; the quality is sufficient for awareness-poster context. The reason to use it is sovereignty. Hold that as the central frame.
Zephyr: Zephyr — and that brings us to the cross-topic synergy segment, which threads cleanly through three projects we discussed in segment A and the Sepsis Poster Studio in segment B.
Schedar: Schedar — the synergy is Apple Silicon as the privacy-preserving compute substrate. Four converging adoptions across the portfolio. First — Sepsis Poster Studio Stage nine on LTX-Video two point three local. Second — the Phlox clinical-scribe trial on Jacob's M four with Ollama and Llama three point three seventy-billion. Third — the POCUS imaging workflow where DICOM substrate from the Vscan Air SL feeds into the AI Discharge Summary RCT corpus and, eventually, Module twelve of the Ross-POCUS learning resource. Fourth — the Indigenous-data-sovereignty edge case across all three. If you implement local LTX-Video for Stage nine, local Phlox for clinical scribing on Aboriginal patient encounters, and local POCUS imaging analysis when the AI augmentation comes online, you get something that none of those three alone provides — a coherent on-device pipeline where encounter-derived content never leaves the M four, where the sovereignty story is operationally true at every stage, and where the cost envelope across the three is — three local model checkpoints downloaded once, zero ongoing inference cost, and the only cloud touchpoints are the cases where Jacob explicitly chooses cloud for cinematic quality on non-patient content.
Puck: Puck — and the practical read is — Jacob's M four is not just a workstation. It is the substrate that makes the Indigenous-data-sovereignty answer real across four projects simultaneously. Every dollar spent on Apple Silicon capability — unified memory, Metal Performance Shaders, MLX runtime maturity — compounds across Sepsis Poster Studio, Phlox, POCUS, and the broader Ross-family agentic AI work. The marginal cost of the next local-AI use case is near zero once the substrate is in place. The marginal value is the sovereignty story plus the operational savings plus the avoidance of vendor lock-in. The substrate decision is already made — the M four is already there — but the framing matters because it shifts how Jacob should think about Stage nine, about Phlox, and about every future "could we run this locally" question. The answer is — almost always yes. Lean into the substrate.
Despina: Despina — and the ethical close-out. The four converging adoptions are not equivalent at the sovereignty layer. Sepsis Poster Studio with LTX-Video on local is privacy-preserving by default — the content is poster art, not encounter data. Phlox with local Ollama is privacy-preserving only if the consent and indemnity scaffolding is in place — and the maintainer-provenance question matters because the rural Aboriginal patient encounter is the use case where the local-first claim has to be operationally true, not aspirationally true. POCUS imaging analysis with local inference is privacy-preserving when the DICOM corpus stays on the M four and Jacob's PPRHS chart workflow documents the image without uploading. And the Indigenous-data-sovereignty edge case across all three requires more than local-first compute — it requires CARE-principle-compliant community governance, recall rights, derivative-content review, and Marie Curie Ross sign-off before any artefact leaves the studio. The substrate is necessary. It is not sufficient. The sufficient condition is the governance layer on top of the substrate.
Zephyr: Zephyr — closing summary. Eight live projects plus the meta line. Four already locked and executing — Aussie Boxing App, Creative Tools, and the macro framing on State of Play itself, plus by Saturday evening also the Sepsis CARE Joondalup workstream. Four awaiting Jacob's decisions or single-action blockers — Respond Global on the six-letter reply, Phlox on the maintainer email plus MIPS notification, POCUS on the supervisor letters, Meridian on the VentraIP domain registration. One credentialing-pathway letter ready to send the moment five fields are filled — PICC Credentialing. Sepsis Poster Studio Stage nine — refresh adopted — LTX-Video two point three on M four local replaces the ffmpeg stub as the new Stage nine default; Wan two point two as secondary local; SANA-WM watch on tier B with three documented trigger conditions for tier promotion; closed cloud reserved for cinematic one-offs on non-patient content. Cross-topic synergy — Apple Silicon as the privacy-preserving compute substrate across Sepsis Studio, Phlox, POCUS, and Indigenous-data-sovereignty work. Despina — close us out.
Despina: Despina with the wrap. The portfolio shape this week is — Jacob is not under-decided. He is under-acted. The decisions across most of the eight projects are either locked or locked-by-default. The blockers are small actions — a fifteen-minute domain registration, a ten-minute MIPS letter completion, a single email to Allison Goodes, a single email to the Phlox maintainer, two emails to potential CCPU supervisors, a six-letter reply to Ada on Respond Global. The pattern is recognisable from earlier State of Play episodes — the cost of inaction is competitive position on Aussie Boxing App, warm-introduction erosion on Respond Global, governance-momentum loss on POCUS, dashboard uptime on Meridian. None of the blockers require new information. None require external dependencies that have not been mapped. They require Jacob spending six hours over the next seven days clearing the action queue. The Sepsis Poster Studio Stage nine refresh is — adopt LTX-Video two point three locally, leave gpt-image-two on Stage four, hold SANA-WM on watch, frame Apple Silicon as the sovereignty substrate. The v two point two pipeline you are listening to right now is the first episode where the loudness target is minus thirteen LUFS — let Jacob know in the production review whether the intro stinger duck-and-fade reads as professional or mechanical, and whether the body-matched outro lands cleanly. That's the only thing the synthetic validation could not tell us. Until next week — the action queue is six hours of work. Do six hours of work.
Alnilam: Thanks for listening to State of Play. Until next week.