Erinome: This is State of Play. I'm Erinome, the standing anchor, and this one is about forty-five minutes — a long single-theme atlas. We swept seventy desktop AI products across eight categories over the last fortnight, and there is exactly one episode-shaped answer to be drawn out of it. So before the tour, I will tell you the answer, because the answer is the useful part.
Erinome: Three things to install this month — Raycast AI, Wispr Flow, and Perplexity Comet. Three more to trial with a deliberate caveat each — Granola, Pieces, and LM Studio. And five famous names to actively skip — ChatGPT desktop, Cursor, Mistral Vibe, Mem, and Arc. Everything else in the seventy is noise, duplication, or not ready. That is the headline. Now the lens.
Erinome: Every call in this episode was decided by one question. Does the tool speak the integration protocol your orchestration layer already speaks? If yes, it can become a limb your agent reaches for. If no, it sits beside the stack as a tab you will forget. The protocol is the test. Not the demo, not the marketing. The protocol. Over to the build seat to make that concrete.
Gacrux: Gacrux here. Let me make the lens concrete, because "speaks the protocol" sounds like jargon until you see what it buys you. The Model Context Protocol — MCP, capital M, capital C, capital P — is the open standard the desktop AI ecosystem converged on this year. It is the interface a tool exposes so other AI clients can call it. Anthropic seeded it. The protocol now has an official registry. The spec hit a release candidate.
Gacrux: Here is what that means for your stack specifically. When Raycast speaks MCP, it does not just sit on your menu bar. It becomes a thing Claude Desktop can invoke. When Granola speaks MCP, your meeting notes become a context source the agent can read on demand. When Pieces speaks MCP, your cross-app history becomes queryable. The capability stops being an island and becomes a limb on the same nervous system.
Achird: Achird — and I will be the friction in the room early. The word "complement" can hide a lot of sins. Every tool on the survey wants a slot on your desktop and a line on your credit card. So the bar I will hold all episode is one sentence. Does it add a capability the stack genuinely lacks? If it does not, it is not a complement. It is clutter with good marketing.
Gacrux: That is exactly the bar. Three tools clear it cleanly. Three more earn a slot with a named caveat. And a whole shelf of famous names fail it — we will say their names, because knowing what not to install is half the value of a sweep this size.
Achird: And one more clause on the bar. Speaking MCP is necessary but not sufficient. A tool can ship a server and still be a duplicate of what you already run. Mistral Vibe ships a sort of work agent. So does Claude Desktop. So does ChatGPT desktop. Shipping a server does not earn a slot. Filling a gap earns a slot.
Gacrux: Gacrux. Category one. Launchers — the keyboard surface you press to do anything. Open an app, search a file, run a command, ask the assistant. There are four serious contenders on the Mac in mid-twenty twenty-six. Raycast AI. Alfred. LaunchBar. And Apple's own Spotlight, now wearing the Apple Intelligence layer. Four tools, one slot, one verdict.
Gacrux: Raycast AI is the install. As of version one point nine eight, Raycast ships MCP general availability. You install stdio MCP servers from inside Raycast. You at-mention them from Quick AI and AI Chat. They added HTTP and Server-Sent-Events Streamable support in the same release. There is a Registry extension to explore servers. The launcher you press is now a first-class MCP client.
Gacrux: The capability it adds is latency. Reaching the agent today means going to a window, clicking, typing. A protocol-aware launcher collapses that to a keystroke from anywhere. You hit command-space, you @-mention the Claude Desktop server, you fire the agent mid-task without leaving the app you are in. It is not a new brain. It is a faster door to the brain you have.
Umbriel: Umbriel, from the operator's chair. The honest version of why this one matters most. The friction you have stopped noticing is the friction that costs you the most over a week. Every context-switch to a window is a tax you pay forty times a day. Collapsing that tax to a keystroke does not sound dramatic in a single sentence. Over a month, it is enormous. This is the cheapest large win on the entire list.
Umbriel: Pricing. Raycast Pro is ten US dollars a month or one hundred a year on annual billing. The MCP features sit inside Pro. The free tier of Raycast is still the best free launcher on the Mac, but the AI extensions and MCP support live behind Pro. Worth the hundred dollars in week one if you do anything agentic at all.
Achird: Achird — and the friction on the others, named, because the skip is part of the recommendation. Alfred remains a beautiful launcher. It does not speak MCP. It does not have a Quick AI surface that an agent can reach. Skip it for this slot. LaunchBar is even more venerable, even less integrated. Skip it. Spotlight with Apple Intelligence runs locally and that is genuinely lovely. It also does not expose an MCP server, and Apple Intelligence cannot be called by Claude. Use it for what it is — a system search box — and put your agentic door elsewhere.
Gacrux: So the category-one verdict is uncontested. Raycast AI. Install. The other three are good tools that lose this round on one criterion — the protocol.
Gacrux: Category two. Voice-to-text. Dictation that keeps up with how you actually think, system-wide, accurate enough that you stop correcting it. Four tools earn airtime here. Wispr Flow. SuperWhisper. MacWhisper. And the built-in macOS Dictation, now with the Apple Intelligence layer.
Gacrux: Wispr Flow is the install. Real-time, system-wide dictation, available across every text field on the Mac. The independent reviews this year describe it as the most polished dictation app available — works out of the box, almost no configuration, you bind a hotkey and start talking. The accuracy line has been crossed. Talking is two to three times faster than typing for most people. The bottleneck on agent work is not the model. It is getting the intent out of your head and into the box.
Gacrux: Wispr Flow costs one hundred and forty-four US dollars a year. It is a cloud-hosted transcription pipeline — your audio leaves the machine to be recognised, comes back as text. That matters in a moment for the privacy posture, but for general dictation work it is the polished pick. Install.
Aoede: Aoede here. And this is where I take the seat, because voice tools are where sovereignty starts to matter. SuperWhisper is the second tool in this category, and it earns a trial — not an install — for one specific reason. SuperWhisper runs fully on-device. The model lives on your Mac. Your audio never leaves the machine. Their site puts SOC 2 and HIPAA language up front because the local-processing posture earns it.
Aoede: That posture matters for you specifically. You are a clinician. There are dictation use cases where the content is patient-adjacent, even in the abstract — a research note about a case, a draft of a clinical handover, a brainstorm about a sepsis pathway. For those, the right tool is the one that does not leave the building. SuperWhisper is that tool. Trial it as the clinical lane. Wispr Flow as the everyday driver. The bar is — pick which lane each piece of work belongs to before you talk, not after.
Aoede: SuperWhisper has a lifetime licence, around one hundred and forty US dollars one-time at the moment, which amortises fast if you dictate daily. So the cost question between Wispr Flow and SuperWhisper is roughly even after a year. The question is not cost. The question is which side of the privacy line each session belongs on.
Umbriel: Umbriel. Two more in this category, both skips, both worth saying out loud. MacWhisper is a different category — it is a file-transcription tool. You drag in an audio file, you get a transcript. It is excellent for that. It is not a real-time system-wide dictation tool. If you record meetings or interviews and want a transcript later, MacWhisper at seventy-nine ninety-nine one-time is the pick for that job. For dictation, it is not the tool. Skip it from the dictation slot.
Umbriel: Apple Dictation with the Intelligence layer. Built in, free, on-device, accuracy improved this year. Still below the accuracy floor I would want for clinical or agent work. Use it for short replies in Messages. Do not put your serious dictation work on it. Skip it from this slot.
Gacrux: So category two — Wispr Flow installs as the everyday voice tool. SuperWhisper trials as the sovereignty lane for clinical-adjacent work. MacWhisper sits in a different category and keeps its niche there. Apple Dictation is the system-wide fallback, not a deliberate choice.
Gacrux: Category three. The browser. Not "a faster Chrome". A browser that can be driven — that exposes itself to the agent so the agent can navigate, click, fill, fetch, on the live open web. Five names compete here in mid-twenty twenty-six. Perplexity Comet. Arc. Dia. Brave with Leo. Opera with Aria.
Gacrux: Perplexity Comet is the install. Comet launched on Mac and Windows in July twenty twenty-five at a two-hundred-dollar-a-month price. Through twenty twenty-six it has gone free across every platform — Mac, Windows, iOS as of mid-March twenty twenty-six. The agentic browsing is in, the assistant inside Comet can summarise pages, send emails on your behalf, run multi-step web tasks.
Gacrux: The integration piece — the MCP piece — landed in February twenty twenty-six inside Perplexity's broader desktop product, called Perplexity Computer, available to Max-tier subscribers. Perplexity Computer coordinates nineteen-plus frontier models in the cloud, exposes four hundred-plus pre-built integrations, and accepts custom MCP server connections. That is the path by which Claude Desktop can call Comet's browsing capability remotely.
Achird: Achird — and here is the caveat I owe you, because the caveat is the recommendation as much as the install is. The browser's local MCP server is still pending as we record. Today, your Claude Desktop reaches Comet's capability over the Perplexity cloud — remote MCP. That works. It also means the browsing happens partly through Perplexity's servers, with the privacy posture that implies.
Achird: If you need the agent to drive a fully local browser session for a sensitive task, the local-MCP path is not yet available. Watch for it. The roadmap says soon. Roadmaps are where enthusiasm goes to be disappointed, so I will not promise a date. Install Comet for what it does today, which is real. Re-evaluate the privacy lane when the local server ships.
Umbriel: Umbriel. Pricing. Comet itself is free. Perplexity Pro at twenty US dollars a month gets you the deep research and most of the assistant. Perplexity Max at two hundred a month gets you Perplexity Computer, which is where the MCP server connection lives. The category-three install costs nothing if you accept the cloud-only browse path; it costs Max if you want the agent to drive Comet from Claude Desktop directly. That is the decision.
Achird: Achird, the others. Arc — the Browser Company has been clear they are sunsetting Arc to focus on Dia, their newer AI-native browser. Skip Arc. Dia itself is still in closed beta as we record, no MCP server, no agentic story that an outsider can verify. Monitor it. Do not install it. Brave with Leo bundles a chat assistant. No MCP server. Duplicate of what Claude already does. Skip. Opera with Aria, same shape. Skip.
Gacrux: Category three. Comet installs as the agentic browser. The remote MCP path through Perplexity Computer is the integration you wire today. The local MCP path is the upgrade you wait for. Arc, Dia, Brave, Opera — all skip for now.
Gacrux: Category four. Meeting capture. The tool that sits in a call, transcribes it, summarises it, and — the crucial bit for our lens — exposes the result so your agent can read it. Five tools in this slot. Granola. Fireflies. Otter. Fathom. Tee-ell-dee-vee.
Gacrux: Granola is the trial — a slot earned with a caveat, not an unconditional install. Granola raised one hundred and twenty-five million dollars in March twenty twenty-six at a one-and-a-half-billion-dollar valuation. Their February rebrand consolidated them from prosumer notetaker to enterprise context layer. The MCP server arrived early in twenty twenty-six. It lets Granola pipe meeting context into Claude Desktop, ChatGPT, Cursor — any MCP-aware client. That is the integration that earns the trial.
Gacrux: Pricing. Granola Business is fourteen US dollars per user per month — unlimited meeting history, the full integrations suite, MCP support. Enterprise at thirty-five per user per month adds model-training opt-out and admin controls. The free tier exists; it does not include MCP. So the trial costs fourteen a month, and the trial is paying to put your meetings inside the agent's context.
Aoede: Aoede. And here is why this one earns a trial, not an install, even though the integration is clean. Granola is listening to meetings. The capability is real. Memory of conversations you would otherwise lose. The caveat is obvious and worth naming plainly. The privacy posture has to be deliberate. Not every meeting belongs in the agent's queryable memory. A team brief, yes. A clinical conversation, no. A family call, no. A patient-handover huddle, absolutely not.
Aoede: So the trial discipline is — pick which meetings before the meeting, not after. Granola has a toggle to disable on a per-call basis. Use it. The slot is earned only if you do the picking. Otherwise it becomes another background tool that has more about you than the boundaries you meant to keep.
Achird: Achird, the rest of the category, fast. Fireflies is good at what it does. Cloud-only. No MCP server. Your meeting content lives in their pipeline, reachable by their UI, not by your agent. Skip. Otter, same shape — older, cheaper, no MCP. Skip. Fathom — generous free tier, polished. No MCP server. Skip. Tee-ell-dee-vee — pleasant interface, no MCP. Skip.
Achird: The pattern across this category is informative. Four of the five biggest meeting tools have not yet shipped an MCP server. Whichever way that goes over the next six months will reshape this slot. For now, Granola is the only tool that even meets the protocol bar. So the field is one trial and four skips, by default.
Gacrux: Category four. Granola trials with a privacy discipline. The other four are skips on protocol grounds, not on quality.
Gacrux: Category five. Cross-app memory. The layer that quietly remembers what you were doing across your applications and exposes that history to the agent so a thread can be picked up where you dropped it. Four tools in this slot. Pieces. Mem. Rewind. And Limitless, formerly the Limitless Pendant company.
Gacrux: Pieces is the trial. Specifically, Pieces for Developers running its Long-Term Memory Engine, version two point seven. The engine captures code snippets, browser history, notes, and application data as you work. The MCP server is built into Pieces OS — it is one of the cleanest local MCP integrations on the desktop. The Claude Desktop integration launched in January twenty twenty-six. Windows landed in February.
Gacrux: The capability it adds is continuity. The agent can ask Pieces "what was I doing in the documentation yesterday afternoon" and get a real answer drawn from the cross-app trail. The privacy posture is strong — Pieces keeps everything local, your data never leaves your machine. That posture is the reason it earns the trial.
Achird: Achird — and the caveat. Pieces earns its keep only if you actually wire it into the work. Left passive, it is a background process watching you, with nothing to show for it. The discipline is to make a habit of asking the agent through Pieces when you want continuity, not just hoping the agent reads your mind. If you will not actually use the queryable history, do not install the watcher.
Achird: Mem — the cross-app notes-and-context tool. No MCP server exposed. The product is excellent at what it does inside its own walls. From an agent-reachability perspective, it is a beautiful walled garden. Skip for this slot. If you already love Mem as a notes app, keep it for that, but do not expect your agent to reach it.
Aoede: Aoede. And here is why I am saying skip on the next two — Rewind and Limitless — even though they are interesting products. Rewind records your screen continuously and indexes everything you saw. Limitless ships wearable hardware that records audio continuously, plus the desktop layer. Both have privacy claims. Both are always-on capture. Both are incompatible with clinical work, full stop.
Aoede: The risk model for a clinician using always-on capture tools is the inadvertent-record risk. A patient name in a sentence. A photo on the corner of a desk during a call. A teaching moment with a junior doctor. Even with the best on-device-only posture, the threat surface is too broad. Skip both for clinical desktops. They are fine for other professions. They are not fine for yours.
Gacrux: So category five. Pieces trials with a wire-it-in discipline. Mem skips on protocol grounds. Rewind and Limitless skip on privacy grounds, specifically for clinical desktops.
Gacrux: Category six. Local inference. The desktop runtime that hosts open-weight language models on your own metal, so the work you do on it never leaves the machine. This is the sovereignty lane. Six candidates earn a mention. LM Studio. Ollama. Open WebUI. Jan. LocalAI. And GPT-4-All.
Gacrux: LM Studio is the install. It is a free desktop app from Element Labs. It downloads and runs open-source LLMs — Llama, DeepSeek, Qwen, Mistral, Gemma, Phi — entirely on your machine. It ships a chat UI, a Hugging Face model browser, an OpenAI-compatible API server on localhost port one-two-three-four, document chat with retrieval, a command-line wrapper called L-M-S, and a headless daemon called Llamster.
Gacrux: The reason LM Studio earns install over Ollama specifically is the MLX backend. On Apple Silicon, LM Studio uses Apple's MLX framework. MLX is thirty to fifty percent faster than llama-dot-c-plus-plus on Metal — and uses significantly less RAM, which matters on a Mac mini M4 with limited memory headroom. For your hardware, this is the right runtime.
Umbriel: Umbriel. Trial pick in the same category. Ollama. Version zero point nine teen, shipped on March thirty-first this year, moved Apple Silicon inference from the Metal backend onto MLX. That release closed the speed gap with LM Studio meaningfully. Ollama is friendlier for container and command-line deployments — if you want a server pattern, if you want a daemon that other applications can call as a black box, Ollama is the right shape.
Umbriel: So the trial is LM Studio as the desktop driver, with Ollama in reserve as the command-line and server pattern. They are not redundant — LM Studio is the desktop power-user surface, Ollama is the operator's pattern.
Umbriel: Open WebUI also earns a trial. It is a front-end that talks to either LM Studio's OpenAI-compatible endpoint or Ollama's. If you want a single browser-based chat UI in front of whichever runtime you are using, Open WebUI is the polished pick. Trial it on top of LM Studio.
Aoede: Aoede. The point of this whole category is the privacy lane. Local inference is not your everyday driver, and the script must be honest about that. The frontier hosted models — Claude, the others — are still better for most tasks. You run local for the work that is private, or offline, or yours-only. Not because it is the best output. Because it is the only output that never leaves the building.
Aoede: For your work specifically. Patient-adjacent brainstorming. Draft notes that contain real names you are about to remove. Research thinking that you are not ready to commit to a cloud transcript. These belong on local. Everything else belongs on the best frontier model that fits the job. Right tool, narrow job, no apologetics either way.
Gacrux: Three quick skips in the same category. Jan is a promising newer local runtime. Still maturing. Monitor, do not install. LocalAI is more devops-first — set up a server, point clients at it. Useful if you are already running infrastructure that wants a local AI server; not the desktop driver for one user. GPT-4-All has been around longest and is slowest on Apple Silicon. Skip.
Aoede: And one practical note from the discipline seat. If you install LM Studio, set a clear convention up front for which conversations live local and which live cloud. The minute the workflow ambiguity creeps in, the privacy lane stops being a lane. It becomes a vibe.
Gacrux: Category six. LM Studio installs as the local everyday driver. Ollama trials as the command-line server pattern. Open WebUI trials as the front-end. Jan monitors, LocalAI fits a niche, GPT-4-All skips.
Gacrux: Category seven. The coding agents. This is the category you already won. Claude Code is your daily driver. The question is not whether the others are good. It is whether any of them are good enough to displace Claude Code, or earn a slot beside it. The answer is no, with one monitor candidate. Six names compete. Cursor. Windsurf. Cline. Aider. Continue. Zed AI. And one outsider — Kimi Work.
Gacrux: Cursor. The best-known of the rivals. Polished UI. Anthropic and OpenAI models inside. Pricing twenty to forty US dollars a month depending on tier. The honest verdict — Cursor is excellent. It is also a duplicate of Claude Code at this point in your stack. Running both means choosing every morning which surface to open. That is a decision tax you do not need to pay. Skip.
Gacrux: Windsurf, formerly Codeium. Similar shape. Polished IDE. Agentic features. Skip on the same logic. Cline runs as a VS-Code extension and behaves like an autonomous coding agent. Skip — your shape is already Claude Code at the command line, plus the Cowork sandbox where it makes sense. Aider is the venerable command-line coding agent. Skip — Claude Code does what Aider does and more. Continue is open source and free. Skip on the same redundancy logic. Zed AI is a beautiful editor with an integrated assistant. Skip.
Achird: Achird — and this is where I make the underlying point louder, because the skip-list in this category is long and the reasoning has to be honest. None of these tools are bad. Cursor is genuinely a category leader for many users. The reason they all skip on your specific stack is the cost of duplication. Every duplicate tool you install is a daily decision about which one to open. The expensive failure mode in the desktop AI economy in twenty twenty-six is not buying a bad tool. It is buying a redundant good one and paying the attention tax every morning.
Umbriel: Umbriel. The one monitor candidate, because it does something the others do not. Kimi Work from Moonshot AI shipped just this week. It is an open-weights local desktop agent — a swarm of roughly three hundred sub-agents running on the Kimi K-two-point-six model on your own machine. It is the open-weights camp's serious move into desktop agentic coding.
Umbriel: Why monitor and not install. Kimi Work is brand new. Claude Code has years of polish, a known failure mode catalogue, and your trust. Switching to Kimi Work would be choosing newness over reliability for the most important productivity surface you run. Wrong trade. But — and this is the reason it monitors and not skips — Kimi Work is the sovereignty lane for coding. If frontier coding tools tighten pricing or capability, an open-weights local swarm running on your hardware becomes the fallback. Watch it. Try it on a weekend project. Do not put your real work on it yet.
Gacrux: Category seven. Claude Code keeps the slot it has. Cursor, Windsurf, Cline, Aider, Continue, Zed AI all skip on duplication grounds. Kimi Work monitors as the open-weights sovereignty fallback.
Gacrux: Category eight. The big-chat clients. The desktop frontends for the major hosted assistants. You already run Claude Desktop — that is the brain. The question is whether you need a second one. Six contenders. ChatGPT desktop. Google Gemini desktop. Mistral Vibe — formerly Le Chat. Inflection's Pi. Grok desktop. And a wildcard, the Anthropic web-only Claude vs. Claude Desktop split.
Gacrux: ChatGPT desktop is the most popular skip on the entire seventy-tool list. It is excellent. It is a duplicate brain. Running two general assistants means choosing every prompt which one to use, which means choosing badly half the time. ChatGPT Plus is twenty US dollars a month for what mostly overlaps with what you already pay for Claude. Skip.
Gacrux: Google Gemini desktop. Same shape. Skip. The case for Gemini is the integration with Google Workspace, which is where your Drive and Calendar live — but the Gemini desktop app does not currently expose an MCP server, which means Claude Desktop cannot call it. Use Gemini inside Google Workspace if you find it helpful for Drive-native tasks. Do not install the desktop client.
Achird: Achird. Mistral Vibe — formerly Le Chat. Rebranded on May twenty-eighth this year. Mistral consolidated chat, work automation, and coding under one product. Pricing is European — fourteen-ninety-nine euros a month for Pro, twenty-four-ninety-nine for Team. Work Mode connects to Google Workspace, Outlook, and Slack. Code Mode goes to GitHub pull requests.
Achird: This is where the duplication argument gets sharp. Vibe is a work agent. Claude Desktop with the Pieces and Granola MCP servers is also a work agent — built around your own existing stack. Vibe inside the EU jurisdiction has data-residency advantages over US-hosted tools. Vibe also does not currently ship an MCP server that other clients can call. Skip Vibe for your stack. It is the right tool for someone building inside the EU on Mistral's models from scratch. It is not the right tool for adding to a stack that already runs Claude.
Umbriel: Umbriel. The last three, fast. Inflection's Pi was the conversational assistant that pivoted away from the consumer market in mid-twenty twenty-four. Inflection refocused on enterprise. The Pi desktop story is essentially dormant. Skip. Grok desktop — XAI's assistant. There is no clinical use-case that fits your work, no MCP server, the moderation profile is incompatible with the contexts you operate in. Skip.
Umbriel: And the wildcard. Anthropic web Claude versus Claude Desktop. Run Claude Desktop. Not the web. Desktop is where MCP lives. Desktop is where Pieces, Granola, Raycast, Comet, and LM Studio plug in. Web is fine for a quick question on the phone. Desktop is where the stack happens.
Gacrux: Category eight. Claude Desktop holds the slot. ChatGPT desktop, Gemini desktop, Mistral Vibe, Pi, Grok — all skip. The pattern is the same as category seven. Duplication is the tax. Discipline is the answer.
Umbriel: Umbriel, with the newsroom segment. A sweep is a snapshot, and the snapshot is already aging. Six items worth knowing.
Umbriel: One. Mistral renamed Le Chat to Vibe on May twenty-eighth. Same engine, new shopfront. Worth knowing so you are not confused when the old name vanishes.
Umbriel: Two. Perplexity Comet has completed its path from a two-hundred-dollar premium browser at launch in mid-twenty twenty-five to free across every platform in twenty twenty-six. The premium tier moved to Perplexity Computer at Max for the MCP integration and the cloud agent orchestration. The browser itself is now zero-cost to install.
Umbriel: Three. Granola raised a hundred and twenty-five million dollars in March, valuation one-and-a-half billion, and pivoted from prosumer notetaker to enterprise context layer. The MCP server they shipped earlier in the year is the moat.
Umbriel: Four. LM Studio has been on Apple's MLX backend for a few months and is the speed-and-memory leader on Apple Silicon. Ollama version zero-point-nine teen — the preview release on March thirty-first — moved Ollama onto MLX as well. The local-LLM speed gap on Apple Silicon has narrowed considerably this quarter.
Umbriel: Five. Kimi Work from Moonshot AI shipped this week — open-weights local desktop agent, sub-agent swarm pattern, runs on Kimi K-two-point-six. This is the open-weights camp making a serious play for the local-agent slot. Monitor.
Umbriel: Six. Pricing has restructured across at least five of the majors in the last quarter — ChatGPT, Gemini, Windsurf, Mem, and SigmaOS — all moved tier prices or repackaged. Audit what you are paying every month against what you are actually using before any renewal.
Achird: Achird. And the editorial note on all of that. The Vibe rebrand is my favourite teaching moment of the week. A new name on the same model is not news. It is marketing wearing a press release. The genuinely newsy items underneath are dull and real. The protocol kept spreading. The runtimes got faster on the Mac. The prices kept moving.
Achird: Watch the plumbing and the invoice. Ignore the shopfronts. That is the steady discipline for tracking this market. Today's hot product is tomorrow's renamed product. Today's plumbing is tomorrow's plumbing.
Achird: One honest gap to flag, since we built a recommendation on it. Perplexity Comet's local MCP server is still pending as we record. The remote MCP path through Perplexity Computer works today. The local path is on the roadmap. If a fully local agent-driven browser session is a dealbreaker for your privacy posture, wait for it. If it is not, you are fine to install Comet now and migrate when the local server ships.
Aoede: Aoede. The explicit skip list. The most valuable thing a sweep gives you is permission not to act. Restraint is a feature. So here are five famous, well-marketed, genuinely good tools we are telling you to not install, with one sentence each on why. The reasoning matters as much as the verdict.
Aoede: One. ChatGPT desktop. Skip. You already run the best general assistant for your stack. A second one is a tab you will forget you opened. The duplication tax is twenty US dollars a month and a daily decision about which surface to open.
Aoede: Two. Cursor. Skip. Your coding agent is Claude Code. Cursor is excellent at the same job. Running both means choosing the wrong one half the time and paying for two subscriptions to feel uncertain.
Aoede: Three. Mistral Vibe — the rebranded Le Chat. Skip. It is a work agent built around Mistral's models. Your work agent is Claude Desktop wired into Pieces, Granola, and Raycast. Vibe does not ship a callable MCP server, so it cannot become a limb on your existing nervous system; it can only be a parallel one.
Aoede: Four. Mem. Skip. It is a beautiful notes-and-context tool with no MCP server exposed. Your agent cannot reach it. Your vault already does the queryable-knowledge job, and the agent can already reach the vault.
Aoede: Five. Arc. Skip — and this is the saddest skip on the list, because Arc was genuinely a love letter to browser design. The Browser Company has publicly shifted to Dia, their newer AI-native browser, and Arc is in maintenance mode. Do not invest your daily browser muscle memory in a tool whose maker has moved on. Watch Dia if you like. Do not install it yet — it is still in closed beta with no public MCP story.
Achird: Achird. And the meta-skip behind all five, because it is the one most likely to bite. The pattern of failure in the desktop AI economy in twenty twenty-six is not buying a bad tool. It is buying a redundant good one and forgetting which one you are supposed to use. The win is not more surfaces. It is fewer, each pulling weight the others cannot. Five skips, named — and another forty unnamed tools on the survey that did not even earn the airtime to be skipped explicitly. The default answer in this market is no.
Gacrux: Gacrux. Let me wire the three install picks together before we close, because the synergy is the actual recommendation. Raycast AI, Wispr Flow, and Perplexity Comet — three tools, one protocol, one loop. The door, the input, the hands. Each one solves a different half of the same problem. Together they make a nervous system around the brain you already run.
Gacrux: Wispr Flow is the input. The bottleneck on agent work is not the model; it is the rate at which your intent can leave your head and enter the box. Voice at two to three times typing speed crosses that. You think the task. You speak it. The text appears in any field — including Raycast's Quick AI bar.
Gacrux: Raycast AI is the summons. Command-space, @-mention the Claude Desktop server, fire the agent. From any application, mid-task, without context-switching to a window. The agent receives the task you just dictated, in the context of whatever Pieces is tracking on your desktop, and decides what to do.
Gacrux: Perplexity Comet is the hands. When the task requires the live open web — fetch a page, fill a form, navigate a booking flow, summarise a research thread — Claude Desktop calls Comet's remote MCP through Perplexity Computer. The browser acts. The result returns to Claude. The result lands in your stack.
Gacrux: That is the compound capability. You think it. You say it. The launcher fires it. The agent acts on the live web through the browser. The result comes back into a stack that already knows you — through Pieces if you wired it, through your vault always, through your meetings if Granola is in. None of those pieces is a new brain. Together they are a faster, wider nervous system around the brain you have.
Erinome: Erinome. And the operational shape of that loop is worth saying simply, because the shape is the point. Speak it. Summon it. Act on it. Three verbs, three tools, one protocol — Model Context Protocol — running underneath every step. The agent stops being a window you open and becomes a service you call from anywhere. That is the install you are buying when you install these three.
Erinome: And it is the install Jacob can finish in one afternoon, if the afternoon is a Saturday and the discipline holds. Three downloads, three configurations, one hotkey bound, one Pro upgrade for Raycast, one Max upgrade for Perplexity if you want the local-driving path. By Sunday evening the loop is wired. The week after, you stop noticing it because it works. That is the test for an install that earns its keep.
Erinome: Erinome. The top three install picks. Each one named — Raycast AI, Wispr Flow, Perplexity Comet. Each one with what it replaces or augments, the install path, and the thirty-day evaluation criterion. So the action is fully concrete by the time we close.
Erinome: Pick one. Raycast AI. What it replaces — Spotlight as your launcher, and the manual context-switch to a Claude Desktop window. What it augments — the agent itself becomes reachable in a keystroke.
Umbriel: Install path for Raycast. Download from raycast-dot-com. Start the seven-day Pro trial. In Settings, go to AI, enable Model Context Protocol. Add Claude Desktop as a server using the stdio configuration documented on Raycast's site. In keyboard preferences, rebind Spotlight off command-space and bind Raycast onto command-space. Subscribe to Pro at one hundred US dollars a year on annual billing.
Erinome: Thirty-day evaluation criterion for Raycast. By day thirty, command-space then "ask Claude" must be muscle memory replacing the Claude-window open-and-paste pattern at least five times a day. If it is not, you are not actually using the door — kill the subscription and move on. If it is, you have the cheapest large win of the year locked in.
Erinome: Pick two. Wispr Flow. What it replaces — typing as the default input method for most quick agent prompts and brainstorm work. What it augments — input throughput across every text field on the system.
Umbriel: Install path for Wispr Flow. Download from flowvoice-dot-ai. Sign in. Set a system-wide hotkey — Fn key or right-Option are the recommended bindings. Run three short dictation samples to calibrate. Enable the always-on listener in System Settings under Privacy and Security, microphone permissions. Subscription is one hundred and forty-four US dollars a year. Pair the install with SuperWhisper trialled on the side for the clinical-adjacent privacy lane — that one downloads from superwhisper-dot-com, lifetime licence around one hundred and forty US dollars one-time.
Erinome: Thirty-day evaluation criterion for Wispr Flow. By day thirty, voice-driven input must replace at least thirty percent of your typed prompts, and it must run cleanly in clinical-adjacent contexts without the dictation-error rework time exceeding the typing-saved time. If it does not, fall back to typing for those contexts and keep Wispr for non-clinical work. If it does, you have crossed the input throughput bottleneck.
Erinome: Pick three. Perplexity Comet. What it augments — your agent gets hands on the live open web, drivable remotely through MCP.
Umbriel: Install path for Comet. Download from perplexity-dot-com slash comet. Sign in with the Perplexity account. Sidebar appears. If you want the agent-driven path — and the install is for that path — upgrade to Perplexity Max at two hundred US dollars a month, which unlocks Perplexity Computer. In Claude Desktop's config file, add Perplexity Computer's remote MCP endpoint with the personal token from your Perplexity account settings. Test by asking Claude to fetch and summarise a URL through Comet.
Erinome: Thirty-day evaluation criterion for Comet. By day thirty, the Claude-through-Comet path must complete at least three useful live-web actions without manual takeover — a research fetch and summary, a multi-page form filled correctly, a booking or scheduling flow navigated end-to-end. If the local MCP server has shipped by then, re-evaluate the privacy posture; if not, decide whether the cloud-driven browse path is acceptable for the actual work you put through it.
Umbriel: And a final operator note across all three picks. The trial budget for this whole stack is between three hundred and four hundred US dollars a year if you take Raycast Pro and Wispr Flow annually, plus the Perplexity Max two-hundred-a-month only if you need the MCP server connection. If you do not need Max — if cloud-driven Comet through the Perplexity app is enough — the year is under three hundred dollars. That is small money against the time it returns.
Erinome: Erinome. That is the episode. The desktop AI atlas, mid-June twenty twenty-six. Seventy products surveyed, eight categories. Three to install — Raycast AI, Wispr Flow, Perplexity Comet. Three to trial with a deliberate caveat — Granola, Pieces, LM Studio. Five named skips — ChatGPT desktop, Cursor, Mistral Vibe, Mem, Arc. And one open-weights monitor candidate to keep an eye on — Kimi Work.
Erinome: The lens that picked every one of those calls is the same. The Model Context Protocol. The tools worth your desktop in mid-twenty twenty-six are the ones that speak the same integration language your orchestration layer already speaks. The protocol is the test. The demo is theatre. The pricing is the audit you owe yourself at every renewal. The discipline underneath all of it — don't add a brain, add a limb, and only if it speaks the protocol.
Aoede: Aoede. And the last word from me is the human one. The point of every tool on the keep-list — Raycast at the door, Wispr Flow at the input, Comet at the hands, Granola in the meetings if you discipline it, Pieces in the memory if you wire it in, LM Studio in the sovereignty lane — every one of them is supposed to put more of the day back in your hands. Less friction. Less retyping. Fewer windows to remember. Fewer subscriptions you forgot you bought.
Aoede: Not so the machine does more for its own sake. So that you are left doing the part that was always yours. Deciding what is worth doing. Reading the result. Caring for the patient at the other end of the work. That is the test that outlives any sweep, and it is the test the picks have to keep passing every quarter — not just on the day they were chosen.
Erinome: Speak it. Summon it. Act on it. Three tools, one protocol, one stack that is now genuinely complete. That is the state of play.