Sadaltager: Sadaltager here — anchoring State of Play episode thirty, on Saturday the twenty-third of May, twenty twenty-six. We're back from a six-day stretch — seventeenth through today — and the inbox tells a coherent story this week. Two threads pull through it: one about voices, and one about bridges. Jacob asked me two things directly. First — is Vox Mimica a good solution for voice cloning? Second — if a local model on his MacBook gets stuck, what does it look like for that model to call out to Claude, and could I outline the work process? Those two asks anchor the episode. Around them we've got the Claude Code productivity wave that landed this week, a thickening local-first agent stack from Nous Research, four open-source clinical scribes that all dropped within forty-eight hours of each other, an ultrasound training cluster that's been sitting in starred mail since the seventeenth, and the creative-tooling layer that keeps pushing on Blender, Penpot, Luma and the new Google Stitch. Length scales with substance, per our v2 playbook — this one runs about forty-five minutes. Spawned Vault projects for both Ada-asks at the close. Five voices in cast — Aoede on builds, Iapetus on push-back, Leda on ethics and the wrap, Enceladus on industry context. Brand voice Alnilam at the back end. Let's get into it.
Aoede: This is Aoede — and I want to start where Jacob actually started, which is the voice-cloning ask. Vox Mimica, the link he forwarded, is positioned as a Dungeons and Dragons voice-transformation tool — change your voice to a goblin or a wizard or a paladin in real time during a tabletop session. That's the framing on the landing page. But the underlying tech is real-time low-latency voice transformation, which is the same primitive Jacob actually wants for two clinical and family use cases. The first is patient education videos in Pitjantjatjara, Yankunytjatjara and Adnyamathanha — where you genuinely cannot record a clinician in language because the clinicians don't speak the language, and you can't always get an elder into a studio. The second is the personal one — Jacob has voice samples from his late father and would like a respectful, family-only memorial use. Those are very different applications from real-time D&D voice swap, and the tool's fit varies hugely between them. So let's not answer the question "is this good" — let's answer "good for what."
Iapetus: Iapetus — I'll push back here before we go further. Vox Mimica being framed for D&D is not a small detail. Tools built for entertainment and tools built for clinical or memorial use sit on radically different consent and provenance foundations. A D&D voice swapper does not have to prove the source recording was consented for synthesis. It does not have to log who synthesised what and when. It does not have to refuse impersonation requests targeting specific real people. Clinical patient-education use, by contrast, requires informed consent from any voice donor, a clear scope of intended use, and — if we're talking about Aboriginal language content — engagement with the relevant community governance bodies before any recording is made. The memorial use case is even more sensitive: synthesising a deceased relative's voice is technically possible with a few minutes of audio, but the bereavement-counselling literature is split on whether it helps or hinders grief, and Jacob would want to think carefully before going there at all, let alone choosing a vendor pitched for fantasy gameplay.
Enceladus: Enceladus speaking — industry-context turn. The voice-cloning market in May twenty twenty-six divides cleanly into four tiers. Tier one is the consumer-grade real-time toolkit — Vox Mimica, Voicemod, Voice.AI — built for streamers and gamers, low latency, low provenance guarantees. Tier two is the creator-grade toolkit — ElevenLabs, Resemble.AI, PlayHT — which has provenance contracts, voice-clone marketplaces with consent attestation, and a much higher floor for clinical or commercial use. Tier three is open-source — F5-TTS, XTTS-v2, OpenVoice-V2 — which gives you full local control and no telemetry but requires you to run inference yourself and accept that the safety surface is whatever you build around it. Tier four is the cloud-foundation offerings — Google Gemini's prebuilt voice library, which is what we use for State of Play itself, plus xAI's TTS-1 and OpenAI's voice models — where you don't clone, you select from a curated catalogue and you trade individuality for governance. Vox Mimica is tier one. For clinical use, the answer is almost certainly tier two or three, not tier one.
Aoede: Aoede again — concrete implementation. For the Aboriginal-language patient-education use case, the path I'd actually recommend is a two-stage workflow. Stage one: engage the community language-authority — Iwiri for Anangu Pitjantjatjara Yankunytjatjara, the Adnyamathanha Traditional Lands Association for Adnyamathanha — before any voice recording happens, and make sure the project sits inside an existing language-revitalisation framework, not next to it. Stage two: record consented voice donors locally, then use F5-TTS open-source on Jacob's M4 to generate the synthesised content. F5-TTS keeps the voice model local, never leaves the machine, and means the community retains full sovereignty over the voice asset. That's a tier-three solution for a CARE-aligned context. For the memorial use case, my advice is different — don't pick a vendor yet. Sit with the bereavement-counsellor literature for a fortnight. The technology is ready; the question is whether the use is. We'll spawn a Vault Project — Voice-Cloning-Assessment — that captures all of this, the tier comparison, the consent framework, the implementation steps, and the open questions for both use cases.
Leda: Leda here, briefly, on the Indigenous data sovereignty thread before we move on. Any voice asset recorded from a Pitjantjatjara, Yankunytjatjara or Adnyamathanha speaker is, under the CARE principles for Indigenous data governance, collective community property — not the property of the individual donor and certainly not the property of the recording project. The fact that F5-TTS runs locally on Jacob's M4 is necessary but not sufficient: local inference still requires that the source voice asset be stored under community governance, that any derivative content be reviewed by the community before distribution, and that the community has a documented right to recall the asset and any derivatives at any time. The Vault Project will name this explicitly. We do not produce Aboriginal-language patient education on Jacob's say-so; we produce it inside a community-governed pipeline where Jacob is one collaborator among several.
Sadaltager: Sadaltager — and that pivots us neatly into the second Ada-ask, which is the bridge. Jacob forwarded an article on the seventeenth — title was "My local LLM can call Claude when it's stuck, and it changed everything about my local-first setup" — and asked me to outline a work process for it. The premise is that you run a small local model — say Llama three point three seventy-billion, or Qwen three thirty-two-billion, or DeepSeek-R-one-Distill — on your own machine for ninety per cent of the work, and when it hits a wall, it calls out to a frontier model — Claude Sonnet, or GPT-five, or Gemini three Pro — to get unstuck on the hard ten per cent. The economics are obvious. The local model handles the bulk of tokens for free; the frontier model handles only the genuinely hard turns and you pay only for those. The architecture is interesting. Let's unpack it.
Aoede: Aoede — the bridge architecture, concretely. You have three components. Component one — the local model server. Ollama on Jacob's M4, running whatever model has the right capability-to-VRAM ratio for the task at hand. Component two — the bridge orchestrator. A small piece of code that sits in front of the local model, watches each turn, and decides whether the local model's response is good enough or whether the question needs to escalate. Decision heuristics include — the local model said "I'm not sure," the local model produced output that doesn't validate against expected schema, the local model took more than N seconds to converge, the task has a marker in its prompt that flags it as known-hard. Component three — the frontier-model client. Anthropic Messages API, OpenAI Responses API, Google Gemini generateContent — whichever you've chosen, with appropriate retry and rate limiting. The orchestrator decides; the client executes.
Iapetus: Iapetus — push-back on the framing. There's a thing the article doesn't say cleanly. The bridge is only worth building if your local model is actually most of the work. If your tasks are all so hard that the bridge escalates ninety per cent of the time, you've added latency and complexity for no economic win. The bridge buys you something when there's a genuine bimodal distribution — most queries are easy, a tail are hard. Document drafting, structured-data extraction, code completion in a familiar codebase, summarisation of short inputs — these are the easy tail and a local model handles them. Multi-step reasoning, novel codebase exploration, legal-text interpretation, anything requiring tool use beyond what your local model has been trained for — these belong to the frontier. The bridge is a routing problem, and routing is only valuable if the destinations are differently priced or differently capable. Make sure your problem has that shape before you build.
Aoede: Aoede — fair. Implementation plan, then, assuming the shape fits. Step one — install Ollama and pull a single thirty-two-billion-parameter model. Don't try four models on day one. Pick Qwen three thirty-two-billion or Llama three point three seventy-billion, run it, get comfortable. Step two — write a thin Python wrapper that takes a prompt, sends it to Ollama, parses the response, and emits a "confidence indicator" — could be a self-rated number from the local model, could be schema validation, could be a rule-based heuristic. Step three — wire that into Claude Code or directly into the Anthropic SDK so that low-confidence outputs trigger an escalation. Step four — log every escalation with the inputs, the local-model output, the frontier-model output, and the eventual user verdict. Step five, after two weeks of logs, look at the data and tune. The escalation rate should land somewhere between five and twenty per cent for the architecture to make sense.
Enceladus: Enceladus — industry-frame on this. The local-frontier bridge is not a fringe idea any more. Cursor, Cline, Aider — all the major coding-agent tools have either shipped or announced some form of model routing. Continue.dev was the first to do it cleanly in their open-source plugin. The pattern this article surfaces — your local model knows when it's stuck and calls out — is the next refinement. Anthropic published a piece on intelligent routing a fortnight ago. OpenAI's Responses API explicitly supports cascading with their cheaper models. Google's managed-agents-with-Gemini announcement this week — which we'll talk about shortly — is a different cut at the same problem. The bridge orchestrator is becoming a standard architectural primitive, not a hobbyist novelty. Worth building once, properly. We'll spawn a Vault Project — LLM-Bridge-Orchestrator — with the deep-dive, the architecture diagram, the API references, and a thirty-sixty-ninety plan.
Sadaltager: Sadaltager — and that pivots us into the Claude Code surface, because if Jacob's local-frontier bridge is going to call out to Claude, it's worth knowing what's landed in Claude Code in the past week. The inbox sweep has six items: a piece on Claude Code plus Codex together; one on "the one setting" that makes Claude Code far more useful; a list of the three best Claude Code plugins; a build-mobile-apps-with-Claude-Code tutorial; an announcement that Claude can now build financial models and close month-end; and a CodexBar update on cost rendering. Let's start with the productivity surface and work outward.
Aoede: Aoede — the "one setting" piece refers to enabling the plan-mode default in Claude Code's config. When you turn on plan-mode-by-default, Claude reads the codebase, drafts a plan, and waits for your sign-off before changing anything. That sounds slow until you've watched Claude Code rewrite the wrong file at speed three times in one afternoon. The plugins piece highlights three — the Anthropic-published claude-code-guide for Claude Code's own help, a memory-management plugin that maintains a CLAUDE.md across sessions, and a SoX-testing audit plugin for SOX-compliance flows. We don't need SOX, but the memory-management plugin is directly applicable: it would let Jacob maintain working memory across Cowork sessions the way the productivity plugin already does. The Claude-plus-Codex piece argues the two are complementary because Codex is better at fast scaffolding and Claude is better at sustained reasoning, and that running both on the same project gives you the best of each. I'm sceptical of the workflow overhead, but I take the underlying point.
Iapetus: Iapetus — push-back, gently. The Claude-plus-Codex piece is a classic case of "this thing works for the author and the author wrote a piece." Two coding agents on the same codebase doubles the surface area for one to overwrite the other's work, doubles the surface area for diff confusion, and doubles the cognitive load of remembering which one you asked to do which thing. For Jacob, who is a clinician moonlighting as an engineer, the simpler architecture is one agent, used well. The "one setting" plan-mode default is the higher-leverage change. The plugins are the higher-leverage change. The financial-modelling capability is irrelevant to clinical work. CodexBar nicer-cost-rendering is a CLI quality-of-life update, not a workflow shift.
Leda: Leda — and on the financial-modelling announcement, briefly. It's interesting that Claude has crossed the threshold where Anthropic can market it as a month-end-close tool. That's a different audience and a different risk profile. The implication for clinical work is that the underlying capability — multi-step structured-data reasoning over long contexts — has matured enough that we should expect medical-record-summarisation and discharge-summary-drafting use cases to land soon, if they haven't already through SafeSpace or the equivalent. The Royal Australian College of General Practitioners published a position statement on AI scribing in March; the next twelve months are going to test it.
Sadaltager: Sadaltager — which is the perfect bridge into the clinical-AI cluster, because four open-source clinical scribes dropped into the inbox within forty-eight hours of each other on the nineteenth. Phlox, Open Scribe, Open Health, and StenoAI. All four are GitHub-hosted, all four are MIT or Apache-licensed, all four target the same job — turn a clinical-consultation audio recording into a structured note. We need to look at them.
Enceladus: Enceladus — industry frame first. Open-source clinical scribes are a response to a market gap. The commercial offerings — Heidi Health out of Sydney, Lyrebird Health out of Melbourne, Cogniora, Cerner Sema4 — all charge per clinician per month, usually fifty to one-fifty Australian dollars, and store the audio and the structured output in their cloud. Open-source clinical scribes promise the same workflow with no per-seat fee and no cloud egress. The trade-off, as ever, is that you maintain the stack, you provide the GPU, and the compliance posture is whatever you build. Phlox is the most mature of the four — it's been on GitHub for nine months and the May release notes show a stable release cadence. Open Scribe is the newest and the most opinionated. Open Health is the broadest — it tries to be a full clinical-AI platform, not just a scribe. StenoAI is the most minimal — it's effectively a Whisper-plus-Llama wrapper with a clean web UI.
Aoede: Aoede — concrete differentiation. Phlox runs Whisper-Large-V-three for ASR, then routes the transcript to a configurable LLM — Ollama-hosted by default, or Claude or GPT by API key — for note structuring. Templates are markdown-driven. It writes to Obsidian-compatible markdown files. It's the closest of the four to Jacob's existing vault workflow. Open Scribe is similar but bundles a hospital-templated note format — SOAP, ISBAR, discharge — out of the box, which is useful but means more code to bend if your template doesn't match. Open Health bundles patient-portal functionality alongside the scribe, which is more than Jacob needs and increases the maintenance surface. StenoAI is the lightest weight — twenty minutes to deploy, ten thousand lines of code in total — and the easiest to audit, which matters for a clinical-governance posture.
Iapetus: Iapetus — clinical-governance push-back, because this matters. None of the four are TGA-approved as a medical device. None of them carry the SBOM — software bill of materials — that a clinical-governance review would expect. None of them publish a clinical-safety case in the form the National Safety and Quality Health Service Standards expect. That doesn't mean they're unsafe; it means using them in a public-hospital context would require Jacob to author the safety case himself and walk it through the Yorke and Northern Local Health Network clinical-governance committee. Which Jacob can do — that's literally his Clinical Lead, Rural Sepsis CARE work — but it's not a weekend project. The right initial deployment for any of these is private-clinic or research-corpus, not the public ED.
Aoede: Aoede — agreed, and that's exactly the implementation plan. Step one — pick Phlox, install on a development MacBook, point it at Ollama with Llama three point three seventy-billion. Step two — feed it ten de-identified mock consultations, score the structured output against the gold-standard SOAP note Jacob would have written manually. Step three — write up the comparison, the safety considerations, and the residual gaps in a clinical-governance brief that could be reviewed by the YNLHN governance committee if and when Jacob wanted to expand it. Step four — share the brief with one rural GP colleague and one clinical-governance officer for sanity check. Don't deploy on patients in any setting in the next twelve weeks. Treat this as a research-grade evaluation of the scribe layer, not a workflow change.
Leda: Leda — and on de-identification for the mock-consultation corpus, the lightest path is to use synthetic consultations that don't represent any real patient. Generate them. Don't use real recordings, even consented ones, in an evaluation context where the scribe might error or where the corpus might end up reviewed by a third party. The cleanest research-grade evaluation uses synthetic input because it sidesteps the consent question entirely. Jacob already has the LLM stack to generate plausible consultations across the rural-ED case mix; the evaluation corpus is a half-day's work.
Sadaltager: Sadaltager — pivoting to the ultrasound cluster. Five items in the sweep, all on the seventeenth — Zedu, Clarius HD3, the Bowra Emergency Ultrasound Made Easy third edition, the AIU emergency-ultrasound courses, and the SLICE algorithm paper from PubMed via the EMUG forum. The pattern is unmistakable — Jacob's revisiting his point-of-care ultrasound stack, probably ahead of the ACRRM advanced-skill module timing. Worth saying what's actually new in the cluster.
Enceladus: Enceladus — Clarius is the newsworthy one. The HD-three handheld released a hardware refresh in April twenty twenty-six, the new model is smaller, lighter, and the on-device AI is now bundling first-pass measurement annotations — bladder volume, gestational-age, ejection-fraction by Simpson's. That's a meaningful change because it shifts the cognitive load. The novice operator still has to acquire the right view, but the measurement burden drops. Clinically, that lifts the floor without raising the ceiling. The Bowra book third edition is a different sort of update — it's the curriculum reference for the ACEM Emergency Ultrasound Diploma and the ACRRM POCUS course, and the third edition adds dedicated chapters on lung ultrasound, focused echo in shock, and a substantially-rewritten resus-room workflow chapter that I'd want Jacob to read in full. The AIU courses are the Sydney-based emergency-ultrasound short-course provider — eFAST, AAA screen, focused echo, lung, FELS — and they're worth flagging because they run a regional South Australia stream that's substantially cheaper than the eastern-states equivalents.
Aoede: Aoede — and the SLICE algorithm is the most interesting research item. SLICE stands for Sonographic Lung Index Classification by Echogenicity — it's a structured grading scheme published in the EMUG protocols collection in April twenty twenty-six, designed to standardise lung-ultrasound reporting in undifferentiated dyspnoea. The motivation is that lung ultrasound is hugely operator-dependent, and a structured grading scheme — like the BLUE protocol, but updated — improves reproducibility. For a rural ED where the second sonographer for cross-check might be a Royal Flying Doctor Service consultant on the phone, structured reporting is a force multiplier. The protocol is freely accessible through the EMUG GitHub. Jacob could trial it during the next POCUS shift.
Iapetus: Iapetus — quick caveat. SLICE is a proposal, not a validated standard. There's a single-centre prospective cohort behind it, n equals one-twenty, and the inter-rater reliability data is preliminary. Worth piloting; not worth defaulting to in a busy resus room. The Bowra third edition is the safer reference for now. And on Clarius HD-three on-device measurements — the manufacturer-claimed accuracy figures should be cross-checked against the published validation studies before they're trusted in a clinical-decision-relevant context. The bladder-volume measurement is fine. The Simpson's ejection-fraction estimate, less so — single-centre work suggests it drifts at the extremes of left-ventricular size.
Sadaltager: Sadaltager — pivoting to the creative-tooling layer, because we promised it. The week's items: Wan two point seven for video, Avatar V custom motion, HeyGen documents-to-video, Seedance two, and the Google Stitch design tool. Plus the open-source Figma alternative — that's Penpot — and the Blender physics add-on and the Blender five point two cloth-solver Ghost-in-the-Shell recreation. Underneath all of these is Luma's "creative agents that make you prolific" launch on the twenty-second. The creative-tooling layer is consolidating around agent-driven workflows.
Aoede: Aoede — the consolidation pattern is interesting. Twelve months ago, creative-tooling AI was a constellation of single-purpose generators — one for images, one for video, one for layout, one for music. The pattern in May twenty twenty-six is creative-agent orchestrators that hold a brief in mind, plan, generate, iterate, and ship. Luma's positioning explicitly — "agents that make you prolific" — is that they hold the project brief and you supervise. Google Stitch is the same shape — you describe a website, it composes a multi-page design, you iterate with comments. Wan two point seven and Seedance two are the new video generators that landed alongside, all promising next-gen quality. Avatar V custom motion ships a workflow for talking-head video without filming. HeyGen's documents-to-video tutorial shows the same thing in a different wrapper.
Iapetus: Iapetus — and the sceptic in me notes that the consolidation of creative agents is also the consolidation of creative dependencies. If Luma's agent goes down on a Friday afternoon and your client deck is due Monday, the workflow that made you prolific made you fragile. The same applies to Google Stitch — Google has a track record of sunsetting design tools, see Tilt Brush, see Blocks, see the original Material Design web app. Tool selection in the creative-agent layer should weight long-term hostability heavily. Penpot — the open-source Figma alternative — and Blender — long-running, foundation-governed, fully local — are the durable picks. The Luma and Stitch agents are the productivity picks. Mix the two layers; don't depend solely on either.
Enceladus: Enceladus — short industry note on the open-source side. Blender five point two shipped the new cloth solver in late April, which is what the Ghost-in-the-Shell recreation showcases. The new solver is two orders of magnitude faster than the old one on multi-mesh interactions, which means real-time cloth in animatics is now feasible on consumer hardware. The Blender Studio is supplementing this with a foundation-funded asset library — for Jacob's medical-illustration use, this opens up the workflow where a clinical scene can be blocked out in Blender with realistic clothing simulation, then rendered through the Eevee Next engine, then post-processed through whatever AI image-edit tool is in vogue. Not for daily use; useful when a publication needs a custom medical illustration that none of the existing libraries cover.
Aoede: Aoede — and SANA-WM, while we're on research-grade tools, is worth one note. NVIDIA's SANA-WM is a two-point-six-billion-parameter open-source world model that generates minute-scale seven-hundred-twenty-pee video on a single GPU. The relevance for Jacob is two-fold. First, world models are the substrate that's going to enable medical simulation training that's actually responsive, not pre-canned. Second, it's a single-GPU open model — the M4 won't run it, but a desktop with a single consumer RTX five-thousand series card will. For the SISU charity's medical-education work, that's an interesting twelve-to-twenty-four-month horizon, not a now thing.
Sadaltager: Sadaltager — let's close out the lighter clusters and then go to synergy. Three items I want to flag quickly. First, the Whyalla steel and lead piece — the ABC reporting on regional South Australian heavy industry facing "trial by fire" — speaks directly to the Port Pirie context. The piece is worth reading not because it has clinical implications today, but because the regional-resilience narrative shapes what funding Yorke and Northern Local Health Network can apply for in twenty twenty-seven. Second, the SA Child Protection and Family Support Awards nominations — these closed on the twenty-second but the awards run annually; if Jacob's working on rural-sepsis-CARE adjacencies that touch family support, nominations for twenty twenty-seven open next March. Worth a calendar reminder. Third — the Obsidian-as-Notion-replacement plugin piece. The plugin in question is Bases, which ships native database views inside Obsidian. Jacob's vault is already structured for it. Half an hour to enable, possibly substantial reduction in the cognitive overhead of finding Project files.
Aoede: Aoede — synergy time. The two anchors of the episode — voice cloning and the LLM bridge — interlock. Both are about hybrid architectures: keep some capability local, escalate or specialise the rest. Both want a small piece of orchestration code in the middle. Both pay off when there's a bimodal workload — most calls easy, some hard, the bridge worth building because the routing's worth the latency. And both have a community-governance dimension that the hobbyist framing in the source articles doesn't fully surface — for voice cloning it's CARE-aligned community sovereignty over voice assets; for the LLM bridge it's data egress from local to frontier provider on the hard turns, which means anything routed to Claude or GPT or Gemini has crossed an organisational boundary and entered a different governance regime. The orchestrator is the place to enforce both. Whatever code you write, log every escalation, redact identifying detail at the boundary, and make sure the audit trail tells the truth.
Iapetus: Iapetus — and the deeper synergy. If you've built a local-frontier bridge for code and reasoning, you already have most of the infrastructure for a clinical-AI bridge. The Phlox-on-Ollama setup is the same shape — local capture, local first-pass, frontier escalation when the local model isn't confident. The Vox Mimica question — what tier of voice tooling is right for clinical use — has the same shape too: a local F5-TTS first-pass, a frontier tier-two service for specific high-stakes outputs where higher quality matters, and a strict audit of which calls crossed the local-frontier boundary. The orchestrator becomes the central piece of clinical-AI infrastructure on Jacob's M4, not just the coding-assistant infrastructure. Build it once, properly, and it earns its keep across three workflows: coding, clinical scribing, and voice synthesis.
Leda: Leda — closing on the ethics and the wrap. Two spawned Vault Projects from this episode — Voice-Cloning-Assessment and LLM-Bridge-Orchestrator, both with the for-review-true flag set so Jacob knows they exist for his sign-off, not as Ada-blessed decisions. The Voice-Cloning project carries the CARE-principles framing as a first-class concern, not an afterthought. The Bridge-Orchestrator carries the data-egress and audit-trail framing as the same. The Phlox evaluation sits in the Vault as an open-ended brief — not a project yet, because it doesn't cross the threshold of greater than two hours of Jacob's time committed; we'll graduate it when Jacob signals interest. The ultrasound cluster lives as study notes, not a project. The creative-tooling cluster lives as a watchlist, not a project. Everything that crossed the project threshold is in the Vault by the time this episode hits the feed. Everything else is in the show notes for next week's sweep to pick up if it persists.
Sadaltager: Sadaltager — final word. Episode thirty in the books. Six days of sweep, two anchored asks, four clinical scribes evaluated at a brief level, one ultrasound study cluster surveyed, one creative-tooling layer mapped, three smaller threads flagged for follow-up. Two Vault Projects spawned. The pattern this week is "hybrid architectures earn their keep" — across voice synthesis, across coding, across clinical scribing, across creative work. Jacob will see this go live by mid-afternoon Adelaide time. Next episode lands when the inbox justifies it — probably the twenty-ninth or thirtieth of May based on the current cadence. Thanks for being with us. Alnilam takes us out.
Alnilam: Thanks for listening to State of Play. Until next week.