Alnilam: This is State of Play, Episode 37. I'm Alnilam — your host today, stepping outside the brand-voice booth at your producer's request. Runtime is about fifty minutes. The topic is architectural visualisation by artificial intelligence — and specifically the cutting-edge of it as it stands in May 2026. Picture three people, all wanting roughly the same thing. The working architect, mid-career, drafting a renovation for a client who can read a floor plan but cannot read a floor plan — meaning she sees the lines but she cannot feel the room they describe. The rural medical officer in Port Pirie, sketching a redesign of the Emergency Department waiting area on the back of a discharge summary because the existing one fails dementia patients on a Friday night. The homeowner planning a build on a coastal block, with a fixed-price contract from a builder who has not, and will not, produce a single image of what the house will actually feel like to stand inside. All three want a walkthrough. A way to see the space before the space is built. For a hundred years that was a craft — drafted in pencil, then in CAD, then rendered, then made into a film if the budget would bear it. In the last thirty months the tools have changed faster than at any point in the discipline's history. The line from a hand sketch to a navigable, photoreal three-dimensional walkthrough has collapsed from weeks to minutes. And it has split, fractally, into six distinct categories of tool — each doing different work, each making different bargains with fidelity, speed, accuracy, and intellectual property. The aim today is a survey. We will cluster the landscape into those six categories. For every tool with a pulse we will give the pro that earned it inclusion and the con that limits it. We will end with workflow recommendations by use case — five named scenarios, sharp picks. The cast is large because the field is large — you will hear Hermione Granger Ross on the underlying research, Richard Feynman Ross on the mechanism, Ansel Adams Ross on the aesthetic question, Edward Tufte Ross on the workflow, Marie Curie Ross on access and equity, William Osler Ross with a brief clinical cameo, and possibly Fred Rogers Ross with a word about the human experience of architectural space. Each voice will name itself when first you hear it. Hermione — would you frame the landscape for us?
Kore: Hermione Granger Ross — research and evidence. Glad to. The six clusters we are working with are not arbitrary. They are organised by what comes in and what comes out, and that is the engineering distinction that matters for the working practitioner. Cluster one — two-dimensional plan in, AI-rendered still or short video out. The tool reads your floor plan or your sketch and writes you a render. The render is photographic in style. The geometry is not preserved with metric accuracy. Cluster two — three-dimensional CAD model in, real-time walkthrough out. The tool ingests an existing Revit or SketchUp or Rhino model and stands up a real-time render engine you can fly through. This is the industry's mature workflow. AI has begun to layer onto it but is not the substrate. Cluster three — existing space in, three-dimensional model out. You scan a room and a model comes back. This is where the most interesting underlying science lives — neural radiance fields, Gaussian splatting, the photogrammetry tradition. Cluster four — text or image in, three-dimensional mesh out. Generative three-D. You type "Eames lounge chair" and a textured mesh appears, droppable into your walkthrough. Cluster five — text or image in, navigable three-dimensional world out. The bleeding edge. Generative world models. Demo-grade today. Not productive for architecture yet, but the trajectory is fast enough to warrant the airtime. Cluster six — brief in, floor plan or massing or building system out. Generative architecture itself. Upstream from the rendering tools. Different point in the workflow. Within each cluster we will work through the tools. Pros, cons, when to reach for which. Where the underlying paper matters — and in clusters three, four, and five it really does — Feynman will take us through the mechanism. The bibliography for this episode is long. Sources at the end.
Sulafat: Edward Tufte Ross — workflow and information architecture. Before we open the first cluster, let me make explicit a thing that will recur. These six clusters describe different points in an architectural workflow, and the working practice question is rarely "which tool" — it is "which sequence of tools, with what handoffs, accepting what data loss at each boundary." The handoff is the place where pipelines go wrong. A floor plan rendered as a still by a diffusion tool is not the same data structure as a Revit model rendered in Enscape — and importing the still into the Revit model is, with current technology, a one-way street. You can move forward through the pipeline. You cannot easily move back. Keep that in mind through everything that follows. The exciting demos are tool-in-isolation. The working practice is tool-in-sequence. And the sequence is the architecture, not the rendering.
Alnilam: Thank you Tufte. Cluster one — two-dimensional plan, AI-rendered output. Hermione opens; Adams on aesthetics.
Kore: Six tools earn a place here, with material differences between them. The underlying mechanism in every case is diffusion-based image-to-image — a class of model trained to denoise random pixels into a coherent image, conditioned on whatever the user supplies as prompt and reference. The reference may be a sketch, a depth-map extracted from a CAD viewport, a segmentation map, or in some cases the floor plan itself read as a top-down geometric constraint. The output is a still. Some tools chain stills into short video by interpolating in latent space; the result is plausible but rarely metrically true. Lookx, at lookx.ai. A diffusion renderer purpose-built for the architecture, engineering, and construction market. Multimodal input — text, sketch, image-to-image — with LoRA-style custom model training so a studio can train the model on its own visual language. SketchUp and Rhino plugins. Free tier; paid from twenty US dollars a month, about thirty Australian, with an annual at one hundred and ninety-nine US, three-oh-two Australian, for unlimited generations. The pro: it knows what an architectural drawing is. The cons: outputs lean toward a particular slick, glossy, real-estate aesthetic that some practitioners will love and others will recognise as the AI tell from across the room. Best fit: studios producing client-facing renders at volume who can spend an afternoon training a style LoRA. Krea AI, at krea.ai. General-purpose generative canvas. Aggregates more than sixty external models — Flux, Veo, Sora, Luma, Runway — and layers Krea's own real-time engine on top. Sub-fifty-millisecond sketch-to-render. Free at one hundred compute units a day; basic at nine US a month; pro at thirty US; max at seventy; business at two hundred. The pro: strongest stylistic control in the category. You can move from photoreal to watercolour to graphite to brutalist concept-render and back inside a single session. The con: not architecture-aware. It will happily generate a render with a structural impossibility in it and you will not be warned. Best fit: the architect who wants to communicate atmosphere in concept presentations, not the documentation phase. Veras by EvolveLAB, at evolvelab.io slash veras. This one is geometry-aware in the deepest sense — it ingests the depth map and segmentation map from your Revit, SketchUp, Rhino, Archicad, Vectorworks or Forma viewport, and renders against that constraint. Thirty-four US a month annual, forty-nine monthly; education at twenty-four; fifteen-day trial. As of 2025 it is also bundled at the Basic tier inside Chaos Enscape Premium, which means many practices are getting it without realising. The pro: respects the geometry. Furniture lands roughly where you put it. The con: licensed and pricier than the open-canvas tools, and the rendering style is less flexible — it is good at architecture, less good at concept atmosphere. Best fit: working architects who want diffusion rendering inside the existing Revit-SketchUp pipeline. Foyr Neo, at foyr.com. Browser-based interior-design suite. Drag-and-drop floor plan, AI furniture search, photoreal stills out. Cloud render plus AI staging. Basic at twenty-nine US a month, standard at fifty-five to one-twenty-nine, premium at ninety-nine to one-ninety-nine. The pro: end-to-end in the browser, no plugin required. The con: aesthetic is firmly residential-interiors-catalogue and the underlying engine is a generic photoreal raytracer with an AI staging layer, not a deep architectural model. Best fit: residential designers and home renovators who never touch Revit. Coohom, at coohom.com. Foyr's principal competitor. Sixty-thousand-plus furniture library, four-K renders in under sixty seconds, AI layout suggestions. Freemium and twenty-five US a month for unlimited renders. The pro: the furniture AI is the strongest in the cluster. Suggested layouts are surprisingly good — better than Foyr's, in our tests. The con: same aesthetic limitation as Foyr; same lack of architectural-pipeline integration. Best fit: small interior practices that want fast staging at scale. Planner 5D, at planner5d.com. The consumer-friendly veteran. Free; premium at about five US a month or sixty-three a year; pro tier higher. Underlying tech is Stable Diffusion plus a proprietary AI Designer Assistant. The pro: cheapest, and the blueprint-recognition feature — point your phone at a paper floor plan and it imports the geometry — is genuinely useful. The con: outputs read as consumer-grade. The architect's eye will reject them as a deliverable. Best fit: the homeowner planning a renovation who needs to communicate ideas to a builder; not a professional pipeline.
Zubenelgenubi: Ansel Adams Ross — the photographer's eye on these renders, and the architect's eye through it. I want to name something the pros-and-cons list does not name. The aesthetic of cluster-one AI renders is recognisable. There is a look. Wide-angle lens distortion that no real camera would use. The light is always golden hour. The furniture is from a small catalogue of high-end pieces that recur across every tool. The surfaces are too clean. The plants are too healthy. The vases are empty of flowers. There is nobody in the room. This is not an accident. It is what the training data taught the model is "good." The training data is the corpus of architectural-marketing photography on the internet — Dezeen, ArchDaily, real-estate listing photography — and the corpus has a very specific bias. It is the photography of empty, idealised, just-finished spaces. The model has learned to render that, because that is what was rewarded. A room that someone lives in does not look like that. The cluster-one rendering tools are excellent at producing the architectural equivalent of a stock photograph and increasingly poor as you ask them to render anything else. The challenge for the working architect is not to mistake the rendering for the space. There is a craft response to this. Use these tools for atmosphere, not for documentation. Use them to communicate feel to a client who cannot read drawings. Don't use them as a substitute for the careful representation of light and material that a hand sketch or a physical model still does better. And — most importantly — do not let the client believe the render is the building. The render is a wish. Back to you, Alnilam.
Alnilam: Cluster two — CAD model in, real-time walkthrough out. The industry's mature pipeline. Tufte leads.
Sulafat: This is the workflow that has been the working standard since roughly 2018, and it remains the workflow most professional practices actually run. The architect models in Revit, SketchUp, or Rhino. The model is synced to a real-time render engine. The engine produces a flythrough video, a still set, or a navigable executable the client can walk through on their own machine. AI has begun to layer onto this — enhancers, style transfer, atmosphere matching — but the substrate is conventional real-time rasterisation, often with ray-traced reflections, running on the graphics card. Five tools. Two clear leaders, two strong challengers, one production-grade fallback for the studios that want full control. Enscape, at chaos.com slash enscape. Owned by Chaos, the V-Ray people. Real-time rasteriser plugin for Revit, SketchUp, Rhino, Archicad, Vectorworks. One-click VR. Solo at five-hundred-seventy-four US a year — eight-hundred-seventy-four Australian. Premium at six-hundred-thirty-four US named-user, or nine-hundred-ninety-four US floating, which is one-and-a-half-thousand Australian. Restructured in May 2025 into the Solo and Premium tiers; both now include the bundled Chaos AI Enhancer, and Premium adds Veras Basic. The pro: it is the AEC industry's mature standard. Other architects can open your file. Documentation is excellent. The con: subscription only, no perpetual licence, and the Australian dollar makes it expensive. Best fit: any practice that takes architectural visualisation seriously as a billable deliverable. Twinmotion, at twinmotion.com. Epic Games. Built on Unreal Engine 5 — meaning Nanite and Lumen, meaning the cinematic-quality real-time rendering that powers contemporary AAA games. One-click sync from Revit, Archicad, Rhino, SketchUp. As of October 2025 the 2025.2 release added full Nanite support, removing what used to be a tedious optimisation step on ingested CAD. Free for students, educators, hobbyists, and any company under one million US in annual revenue. Above that threshold, four-hundred-forty-five US per seat per year — six-hundred-seventy-six Australian. The pro: it is the most visually compelling tool in this cluster. The Unreal substrate is honest gameplay-grade rendering. The con: until 2025.2 it was opinionated about the asset library — the foliage and furniture were the Twinmotion library and you could tell. That is less true now. Best fit: small and mid-sized practices, students, and anyone whose practice revenue keeps the free tier viable. Lumion, at lumion.com. The third major. Standalone real-time renderer with the largest asset library in the industry — particularly strong on landscape elements, atmospheric effects, and animated content. April 2025 restructure: Lumion View at two-ninety-nine US a year, four-fifty-four Australian; Pro at eleven-forty-nine US, one-thousand-seven-hundred-and-forty-six Australian; Studio at fourteen-ninety-nine US, two-thousand-two-hundred-and-seventy-eight Australian. Subscription only since the restructure — the perpetual licence is gone. The pro: the asset library and the atmospheric library are unmatched. The con: it is the most expensive of the three majors, and the restructure annoyed a lot of long-time perpetual-licence holders. Best fit: landscape-heavy projects and external visualisation specialists. D5 Render, at d5render.com. The rising challenger. Real-time path-traced renderer with AI Enhancer, AI Style Transfer, AI Atmosphere Match, AI Inpainting and live CAD sync. Community tier free — four-K video, sixteen-K stills, unlimited projects, which is a remarkable free tier. Pro at thirty-eight US a month annual — fifty-eight Australian — or forty-eight monthly. The pro: the AI layer is the most integrated in this cluster. Style transfer between renderings is one click. Atmosphere match — taking the light and weather from a reference image and applying it to your scene — is genuinely useful. The con: less mature documentation than Enscape, and the corporate footprint is smaller. Best fit: practices for whom the AI enhancers earn their place, and any small practice on a hard budget who can run the community tier. Unreal Engine 5 with Datasmith, at unrealengine.com. The full game engine, with the Datasmith plugin pipeline ingesting Revit, Rhino, SketchUp, 3DS Max as dot-udatasmith. Free for non-game use under one million US in revenue, royalty-free for archviz. UE 5.7 ships Datasmith with Revit 2025 and 2026 support. The pro: it is the production-grade tool the others are imitating. If you need full cinematic control, scripting, multi-user VR, or anything bespoke, this is where the ceiling is. The con: steep curve. Datasmith ingest is no longer the bottleneck — the learning curve on Unreal itself is. Best fit: production-grade archviz studios and the architect who is willing to invest the months it takes to learn the tool properly.
Zubenelgenubi: Adams again. A note on aesthetics here. Cluster two is where AI is layered onto a real engine, not where AI is the engine. This is the cluster where you have the most aesthetic control as the practitioner. The light is yours. The materials are yours. The composition of the still is yours. If you care about how the space feels, this is where you do your work. Cluster one is where you concede that to the model. Cluster two is where you take it back.
Alnilam: Cluster three — existing space in, three-D model out. The science is unusually rich here. Hermione on the papers; Feynman on the mechanism.
Kore: The science we are about to discuss is the most genuinely transformed corner of computer graphics in the last five years, and the papers are accessible enough that the working architect should be able to read them in an evening. Two foundational works. First — Mildenhall and colleagues, 2020. NeRF: Representing Scenes as Neural Radiance Fields for View Synthesis. European Conference on Computer Vision, 2020. ArXiv preprint two-zero-zero-three-point-zero-eight-nine-three-four. The paper that opened the field. It showed that a small multilayer perceptron, trained on a few dozen photographs of a scene from different angles, could learn the scene as a continuous five-dimensional function — three dimensions of space, two of viewing angle — and be queried to produce photorealistic novel views. Second — Kerbl, Kopanas, Leimkühler, and Drettakis, SIGGRAPH 2023. 3D Gaussian Splatting for Real-Time Radiance Field Rendering. ACM Transactions on Graphics, volume forty-two, issue four. ArXiv two-three-zero-eight-point-zero-four-zero-seven-nine. The paper that ended NeRF's reign on the rendering side — replacing the implicit neural-network scene representation with an explicit set of three-dimensional Gaussian blobs that can be rendered in real-time on commodity GPUs. Three years between the papers. Three years in which neural radiance fields went from research curiosity to consumer iPhone app. Feynman — mechanism.
Rasalgethi: Richard Feynman Ross. Let me try. A neural radiance field is just a function. Give it a point in three-D space — x, y, z — and a viewing direction — theta, phi — and it returns the colour at that point and how opaque it is. Five inputs, four outputs. The function is a small neural network, maybe eight or ten layers deep. You train it by showing it a bunch of photos of the scene and the camera positions those photos came from, and you backpropagate the error between what the network says the photo should look like and what it actually looks like, sample by sample, ray by ray. To render the scene from a new camera position, you fire a ray from the camera through each pixel of the image you want to produce. You sample the ray at sixty-four or one-hundred-and-twenty-eight points along its length. For each point, you ask the network: what colour, what opacity? You composite those samples back-to-front. That gives you the pixel. Do it for every pixel — millions per image — and you have your novel view. It is exquisite. It is also slow. Hundreds of network forward passes per pixel per frame. Real-time NeRF rendering at any decent quality was, until recently, the province of supercomputers. Gaussian splatting fixes that by changing the representation. Instead of an implicit neural function you ray-march through, you have an explicit set of three-dimensional Gaussian blobs — anisotropic, meaning they can be stretched along axes — sitting in space. Each blob has a position, a shape, a colour, and an opacity. To render a frame, you project the blobs onto your camera plane, sort them by depth, and alpha-blend them in order. That is a tile-based, embarrassingly parallel operation. A modern GPU eats it for breakfast. Thirty-plus frames per second on commodity hardware. The trick, and this is where the paper is beautiful, is that you train this representation differentiably — you can compute the gradient of the rendered image with respect to every parameter of every Gaussian, and use that gradient to fit the blobs to your training photographs by stochastic gradient descent. The optimisation includes a densification step where, where the image error is high, new Gaussians are spawned, and an opacity-pruning step where Gaussians that have collapsed to nothing are removed. The net effect is one hundred to one thousand times faster rendering than NeRF, at equal or better quality, with the bonus that the representation is now editable in a way the NeRF function is not. You can pick up a Gaussian and move it. You can change its colour. You cannot easily do that inside a black-box neural network. That is why Gaussian splatting is winning. Now — the tools.
Kore: Six tools, in roughly ascending order of professional grade. Polycam, at poly.cam. Mobile and web. Uses iPhone LiDAR, photogrammetry, room scan, and now Gaussian Splatting in the cloud. Free tier; Basic at thirteen to twenty-seven US a month, or eighty to two hundred US a year. Pro: the polished UX in the category — your phone is a 3D scanner. Con: Gaussian Splatting export and the fifteen-plus output formats are behind the Pro paywall, and iPhone LiDAR is restricted to iPhone 12 Pro and later. Best fit: the architect or clinician who needs to capture an existing room quickly without specialist equipment. Luma AI, at lumalabs.ai. Web and iOS. NeRF and 3DGS reconstruction, plus Genie text-to-3D and Dream Machine video. Free thirty generations a month; Lite at ten US; Standard at thirty US; Plus at sixty-five; Pro at one hundred; Premier at five hundred. API at one US per capture. Pro: web export is excellent — Luma's web viewer was the first to make Gaussian splat scenes shareable to a non-technical client. Con: cloud-dependent, which has data-sovereignty implications worth thinking about for client work. Best fit: the practice that wants to share interactive 3D captures with clients via a link. Scaniverse, at scaniverse.com. Niantic. Free. On-device Gaussian Splatting — no cloud upload, no account required. Pro: free, fast — typically under ninety seconds — and stays on your device. Con: limited export options, and the Niantic ownership means feature roadmap is driven by gaming and consumer use cases, not professional ones. Best fit: the rural clinician or architect who needs to scan a space privately and quickly, especially when the space contains identifiable individuals or sensitive context — the on-device pipeline matters for confidentiality. KIRI Engine, at kiriengine.app. Multi-method scanner — photogrammetry, LiDAR, Neural Surface Reconstruction, and 3DGS. Pro tier at eighteen US a month or eighty US a year. The September 2025 v4.0 update brought Photo Scan down to about two minutes from ten, removed export limits, and added AI PBR materials via diffusion. Pro: generous free tier, broad method coverage, strong export pipeline. Con: less polished than Polycam on UX. Best fit: the practitioner who wants to experiment across capture methods without buying multiple subscriptions. Postshot, at postshot.dev. Desktop. Pro-grade Gaussian Splatting trainer. As of September 2025, all tiers — Free, Indie, Studio — became free; previously the paid tiers were seventeen and thirty-nine Euros a month. Pro: the desktop pipeline gives you the highest-fidelity splat reconstruction available outside the academic research codebases, and you control the training. Con: requires a modern GPU and a tolerance for desktop tooling — this is not a phone scan and email pipeline. Best fit: visualisation specialists producing client-grade splat reconstructions for shareable interactive deliverables. RealityScan — formerly RealityCapture, at realityscan.com. Epic Games. The photogrammetry gold standard. Free for individuals and companies under one million US in revenue; one-thousand-two-hundred-and-fifty US per seat per year above that. November 2025 shipped RealityScan 2.1; the June 2025 rebrand to RealityScan added AI mask generation and aerial LiDAR support. Pro: the most accurate metric photogrammetry pipeline on the market, with established workflows for survey-grade output. Con: photogrammetry-first — the Gaussian Splatting integration is less mature than Postshot's, and the survey-grade accuracy is overkill for most architectural visualisation. Best fit: surveyors, heritage-listed buildings, anything where the captured geometry has to be metrically defensible.
Sulafat: Tufte. The handoff problem matters more here than anywhere else. A Gaussian Splatting scene is a wonderful thing to view in a web browser but it is not a mesh, and not every downstream tool will accept it. If your goal is to import the captured space into Revit or Rhino for further design work, photogrammetry to mesh — that is, the RealityScan route — is still the more sensible path. If your goal is a shareable client-facing capture that does not need to feed back into the design model, splatting is now the winner. Choose by destination, not by demo.
Alnilam: Cluster four — text or image in, three-dimensional mesh out. The generative-3D frontier as it applies to fittings, furniture, fixtures.
Rasalgethi: Mechanism first. There are two model families here that both call themselves "generative 3D" but work very differently. The first family is diffusion-based. The model has been trained to denoise a noisy representation of a 3D object into a clean one, conditioned on a text prompt or a reference image. The "representation" varies — sometimes it is a voxel grid, sometimes a triplane, sometimes a point cloud, sometimes a structured latent that decodes to multiple geometric representations. The model's training data is a corpus of 3D objects — Objaverse, ShapeNet, and the various proprietary scraped datasets — paired with text descriptions. The second family is parametric — Sloyd belongs here. There is a library of hand-crafted parametric templates — a chair has these knobs, a table has those — and the AI's job is to pick the template and set the knobs. The output is predictable. The geometry is clean. The polycount is low. The trade-off: you can only generate things the parametric library knows how to make. The diffusion family is more flexible. The parametric family is more useful at scale.
Kore: Six tools. Meshy, at meshy.ai. The consumer leader. Meshy 6 as of early 2026. Free at one hundred credits a month under CC-BY 4.0 license; Pro at twenty US a month with private licence; Studio at sixty US; Enterprise custom. Pro: by far the most polished consumer UX, and the text-to-textured-mesh pipeline is the fastest in the category. Con: the underlying model details are not published, and the topology — the way the mesh is structured — is often not clean enough for direct downstream use without retopology work. Best fit: rapid asset prototyping for visualisation. Tripo3D, at tripo3d.ai. Tripo v2.5 generally available; Tripo H3.1, a "production-grade native 3D diffusion model," debuted at the Game Developers Conference in March 2026. Roughly twenty to forty US cents per model via fal.ai. Pro: stronger topology than Meshy — auto-retopology reduces polycount by 60 to 80 percent while preserving silhouette. Con: the API ecosystem is more fragmented than Meshy's. Best fit: small studios that want predictable mesh output at a low per-asset cost. Sloyd.AI. Parametric. Free at thirty export credits; Plus at fifteen US per user per month. Pro: predictable, game-ready, low-poly. The mesh you get is the mesh you can ship. Con: limited to what the parametric templates can describe — there are no parametric "Frank Gehry crumpled-paper roofs." Best fit: game-asset and rapid-VR work where topology matters. Rodin Gen-1 by Hyperhuman — at hyperhuman.deemos.com slash rodin. Rodin Gen-1.5 is the current production model, with Gen-2 announced at ten billion parameters using their proprietary BANG architecture. Free tier; twenty-four US a month or ninety-two cents per model pay-as-you-go. Pro: the highest output quality in the consumer category. Quad-mesh geometry, PBR materials, and a topology that is closer to "ready to use" than any competitor. Con: priced for occasional use, not volume. Best fit: hero assets where quality matters more than throughput. TRELLIS, by Microsoft Research, released late 2024. Paper at arXiv 2412.01506 — Structured 3D Latents for Scalable and Versatile 3D Generation, Xiang and colleagues. CVPR 2025 Spotlight. The paper's innovation is the SLAT representation — structured latent — a sparse 3D grid populated with dense multiview features from a vision foundation model. A single SLAT latent decodes interchangeably to a radiance field, to 3D Gaussians, or to a mesh. Two billion parameters, trained on five hundred thousand objects, open weights. Pro: state-of-the-art quality in the open category, and the multi-representation decoder is genuinely useful. Con: self-hosted — you bring your own GPU. Best fit: research practices and developers who want to embed generative 3D into their own pipeline. Hunyuan3D 2.0 — by Tencent, open source. GitHub at Tencent-Hunyuan slash Hunyuan3D-2. Two-stage architecture — Hunyuan3D-DiT for shape, a flow-based diffusion transformer, plus Hunyuan3D-Paint for texture synthesis. Hunyuan3D-2.5, released April 2025, scaled to ten billion parameters, one-thousand-and-twenty-four geometric resolution, four-K textures, and skeletal skinning. Pro: open source, top-of-line image-conditioned 3D, with multi-view variants for tighter shape control. Con: also self-hosted, also GPU-dependent, also research-tier maturity. Best fit: practices that want sovereignty over the model and have the technical depth to host it.
Zubenelgenubi: Adams. A practical word on why this cluster matters for architecture in particular. You are designing a building. You need furniture, fittings, fixtures inside the visualisation — not the building itself, the stuff. Real architectural rendering libraries are large, but they are not infinite, and the exact piece your client wants is rarely there. Generative 3D from a sketch lets you produce the missing piece in a few minutes. A bespoke pendant light. A specific Italian armchair. A custom kitchen island. The mesh comes back, you drop it into the walkthrough, you keep going. This is the cluster that quietly completes the cluster-two workflow. It is the missing-component generator. Don't think of it as a building-design tool — think of it as the inventory tool that fills the building you have already designed.
Alnilam: Cluster five — generative 3D worlds. The bleeding edge. Feynman and Hermione together; Adams to close.
Rasalgethi: A different mechanism again, and a fundamentally harder problem. A world model is a neural network that, conditioned on a text prompt or an image and the player's input — keyboard, mouse, controller — predicts the next frame of a navigable 3D world. Frame by frame. There is no underlying 3D representation that persists — the "world" exists only in the model's hidden state, regenerated forward through time. If you turn around and look back at where you just were, the model has to reconstruct that view from whatever it remembers, and it may not remember it. This is a much harder problem than novel-view synthesis. NeRF and Gaussian splatting take a fixed scene and produce new views of it. World models are generating the scene as you move through it. The fidelity-versus-persistence trade-off is the central engineering challenge — keep the world coherent over time, while keeping the per-frame compute small enough that the experience is interactive.
Kore: Three significant systems in 2024 to 2026. World Labs, Fei-Fei Li's company. Founded early 2024, launched September 2024. First commercial product, Marble, released the twelfth of November 2025. Marble generates editable, downloadable 3D environments from text, image, video, panorama, or 3D layout prompts — and crucially exports them, which the others do not. Positioned as "spatial intelligence" rather than generative video. Pro: the only one of the three with practical export workflows — you can take the output and use it elsewhere. Con: it is brand new, the tooling is consumer-grade, and the export fidelity is still well below what an architect can use as documentation. Best fit: speculative concept exploration; not production. Decart Oasis, at decart.ai. First playable real-time open-world AI model. Oasis 1.0 — Minecraft-like world generated frame-by-frame, three-hundred-sixty pixels at twenty frames per second, forty-seven milliseconds per frame on an Nvidia H100. Oasis 2.0 subsequently released, roughly one hundred times faster than contemporary text-to-video models. Project page at oasis-model.github.io. Pro: real-time interactive — the first to demonstrate that interactive worlds could be generated entirely from a neural network. Con: needs H100-class hardware, fidelity is gameplay-grade not photoreal, and persistence is measured in seconds. Best fit: research and demos; nothing else, yet. Google DeepMind Genie 2 and Genie 3. Genie 2, December 4, 2024 — foundation world model, action-controllable, playable 3D worlds from a single prompt image, with long-horizon memory that recalls offscreen regions. Genie 3, August 5, 2025 — twenty-four frames per second at seven-hundred-twenty-pixel resolution, several minutes of physical and visual coherence. Public release on the twenty-ninth of January 2026 as Project Genie for AI Ultra subscribers at two hundred and fifty US dollars a month. Pro: the longest-coherent world models on the market, with public API access. Con: two-fifty US a month, walled by an AI Ultra subscription, and still oriented toward gaming use cases. Best fit: researchers and serious enthusiasts; not yet a production architectural tool.
Rasalgethi: Feynman again. Why these aren't yet ready for architecture, in three constraints. Latency. The H100 floor for Decart is a server-grade GPU that costs roughly thirty thousand US dollars. That is not the architect's machine. Persistence. A world model that loses coherence after thirty seconds cannot be used as the documentation deliverable for a building. The client cannot believe that the kitchen will exist when they look back at it. Fidelity. The outputs are not metrically accurate. You cannot dimension a wall in a Genie 3 world. You cannot generate BIM. You cannot pass the output to a structural engineer. When those three constraints break — and they will, within five years — the cluster-five tools will eat the cluster-two tools alive. Today they are demos. Tomorrow they are the substrate. Plan accordingly.
Zubenelgenubi: Adams. A wider point about cluster five that the engineering language can obscure. What these tools attempt is the holodeck — the long-imagined endpoint of architectural visualisation where the client inhabits the future space rather than viewing renders of it. We are not there. We are perhaps a quarter of the way there. But the trajectory is fast. The aesthetic question to hold in mind as this matures is whether inhabiting a generated space is the same kind of experience as inhabiting a designed one. There is a strong intuition that it is not. Designed spaces carry the trace of intention — the architect's intention, the builder's intention, the inhabitant's adaptation over time. Generated spaces carry the trace of statistics — the average of every space the model has seen. They feel different. They will continue to feel different even as the fidelity goes up. That is not an argument against the tools. It is an argument for retaining the architect's hand inside the process. The tools amplify; they do not replace.
Alnilam: Cluster six — generative architecture itself, upstream from rendering. Tufte and Curie.
Sulafat: Tufte. Cluster six is different from everything we have discussed because the AI is not making pictures — it is making floor plans, massings, layouts, and building systems. Upstream from any of the rendering tools. The output of cluster six is the input to cluster two. Maket.ai. Text-to-floor-plan with zoning-aware compliance and multi-story output up to four floors. Free fifty credits; Pro at twenty US a month, three hundred credits. Pro: easiest entry to text-to-plan. Con: the plans are concept-grade — they need an architect's pass before they can be costed or built. Best fit: pre-design ideation and concept conversations with clients. Autodesk Forma, at autodesk.com slash products slash forma. Formerly Spacemaker. Cloud site-planning and early-stage building design with AI-powered environmental analysis — sun, wind, noise, microclimate, and carbon. One-hundred-eighty-five US a month or fourteen-forty-five US a year — about two thousand two hundred Australian — standalone. Bundled at no extra cost in the AEC Collection. In 2025 the Forma Building Design module entered closed beta with facade design, interior layout, and building-level environmental analysis; general availability planned for 2026. Pro: the only tool in this cluster integrated with the dominant AEC vendor's broader stack. Con: priced for established practices. Best fit: established firms doing site-planning at scale, especially in jurisdictions where the environmental modelling justifies the price. Hypar, at hypar.io. Cloud generative platform automating massing, structure, columns, and furniture layouts from spatial programs. Free Plan; Pro for small teams; Enterprise custom — and free for healthcare, workplace, and data-centre building types via Revit. Pro: the suggestions system, released January 2025, auto-generates editable masses and structural grids from base layouts. Con: pricing model opaque outside the free building types. Best fit: practices working in the building types covered by the free tier — healthcare facilities particularly. Finch3D, at finch3d.com. AI Copilot generating compliant apartment layouts and thousands of mix-and-circulation iterations from massing. Forty-nine Euros a month — about eighty-one Australian — for Finch Basic. Pro: the residential-density specialist. Con: narrower scope than Hypar. Best fit: residential-development practices. TestFit, at testfit.io. Real-estate feasibility platform — generative massing and site-solver for multifamily, parking, and industrial. One hundred US a month annual for Urban Planner; Site Solver from eight thousand US a year. Pro: the deal-feasibility tool the development side actually uses. Con: priced for developers, not architects. Best fit: development-firm partners. ARCHITEChTURES, at architechtures.com. Generative AI residential building generator with real-time 2D/3D modelling, BIM export — IFC, DXF, XLSX — and financial analysis. Pro at forty-one Euros a month — sixty-eight Australian — or four hundred ninety-two Euros a year. Pro: end-to-end residential pipeline from brief to BIM. Con: residential-only, and the model has design biases that need to be designed around. Best fit: developers and architects doing repeat residential work. Augmenta, at augmenta.ai. Agentic design environment automating electrical raceway routing and MEP coordination inside Revit. Enterprise-only — no public pricing. September 2025 launched the Augmenta Construction Platform as a fully agentic environment for electrical contractors. Pro: the systems-routing automation is genuinely novel and meaningfully reduces BIM modelling time. Con: enterprise pricing model means it is invisible to small practices. Best fit: large MEP and electrical contractors at design-build scale.
Achernar: Marie Curie Ross — equity and access. Cluster six is the cluster that most clearly democratises an aspect of architectural practice that previously required years of training. A solo small-practice architect can now produce a comparative-massing study in an afternoon that would have taken a junior in a large firm two weeks. A homeowner-developer can run a feasibility study on a site that would previously have required a fee proposal from a planning consultant. That is genuinely democratising. But the price for that democratisation, and it is the same price across every cluster we have discussed, is training-data extraction. These models learned what a good apartment building looks like from the work of the architects who designed every apartment building scraped from the internet, mostly without consent and without compensation. The same is true of cluster one's rendering models — they learned what a good interior looks like from the work of every photographer of architectural interiors. The same is true of cluster three's reconstructions — they learned what coherent geometry looks like from the public datasets of scanned environments. The same of cluster four's mesh generators — Objaverse is open, but it is full of work whose authors did not consent to its inclusion as training data. This is the unresolved question at the centre of the field. The tools are wonderful. They were built on labour that was not paid for. The case law is being written in real time — in the United States, in the European Union, in the United Kingdom; Australia is downstream of all three. The Australian Productivity Commission's December 2025 report on Artificial Intelligence in Healthcare touched the same broader question — training-data provenance, consent, the asymmetry between the entities that hold the corpora and the individuals whose work is in the corpora. The practical position for a working architect, today, is to read the licence on every tool you use and to make a deliberate choice about which side of the trade-off you stand on. Most will stand on the productivity side. Some will choose tools that train only on licensed corpora — Adobe Firefly is the analogue in image generation; the architectural equivalent does not really exist yet. That gap is itself a market opportunity. And — the rural-Australia access question. Most of these tools are subscription-priced in US dollars. Most assume broadband sufficient to upload site captures and download splat reconstructions. Many assume a paid Adobe Creative Cloud or Autodesk AEC Collection in the background. The tools democratise the capability; they do not democratise access to the capability. A small Port Pirie practice is not on the same footing as a large Adelaide one, even with identical professional skills. That is not the tools' fault, but it is a fact about the deployment of them.
Alnilam: The clinical-facility angle. Osler — brief cameo.
Algenib: William Osler Ross. A short cameo on what this means for the rural medical officer planning a clinical facility — which your host is. The Yorke and Northern Local Health Network is responsible for the physical environments in which care is delivered across regional South Australia. The Health Advisory Council grant cycle invites proposals for capital works — and the consistent friction in those proposals is that the people who know what an Emergency Department waiting area should be like in a rural town are clinicians, not architects, and the architects who can design it are working at metropolitan scale and metropolitan assumptions. Adelaide's solutions do not always map to Port Pirie. The tools we have surveyed today are, for the first time, available to the clinician. A medical officer can sketch the redesign of an ED waiting area to make it dementia-friendly — high-contrast wayfinding, clear sightlines from triage, a quieter sub-zone for delirium presentations — and render it well enough to put in front of a HAC committee. The same officer can capture the existing space with a Polycam or a Scaniverse scan, propose a modification in Krea, and produce a walkthrough in Twinmotion or D5. The total tooling cost for that workflow, if the practice already has Claude Pro and the institution has a Twinmotion seat, is essentially zero. The thing this tooling cannot do — and you must be clear about this — is replace the architect. The clinician renders the concept; the architect designs the building. The clinician's render lives upstream of the brief, not downstream of it. The HAC submission with an AI-rendered visualisation of a proposed Emergency Department redesign is one input to the planning conversation, not the final design. Read in that spirit, the toolkit is a significant democratising step for rural-clinician advocacy for the spaces in which they practise. Three specific use cases come to mind for your host's portfolio. First — the dementia-friendly ED waiting area we just discussed. Second — the GP-clinic spatial planning question, where general practices are routinely designed by builders, not architects, and clinical workflow suffers for it. Third — the residential aged-care palliative-care suite, where the architectural literature on the topic is patchy and the clinical workflow specifications are not legible in conventional plans. In each case, a Twinmotion walkthrough of the proposed change is more persuasive than a thousand words of policy justification, and a Krea-rendered atmosphere study communicates the dignity-of-care dimension better than any prose. The caveat — and I do mean this — is that the renders must not pretend to be the building. The HAC committee must understand that the visualisation is a proposal, not a deliverable. The architectural profession is essential to the work; the clinician's job is to make the question legible enough for the architect to answer well. The tools help with that. Back to you.
Alnilam: Optional cameo from Rogers on the human-experience-of-space question, then to workflow recommendations.
Enceladus: Fred Rogers Ross. A brief word. What architectural visualisation is for, when it is working well, is helping a person who will spend time in a future space — the patient in a waiting area, the resident in an aged-care suite, the child in a clinic exam room — feel the space before it exists. To imagine themselves in it. To know whether it will hold them or alienate them. That is a deeply human task, and the question it asks of any rendering tool is whether the rendering carries the belonging of the space, or only its surface. The AI tools we have surveyed are excellent at surface. They are not, yet, particularly good at belonging. The empty AI-staged interior is uncanny because no person who ever loved a space is shown loving it. A real architect's photograph of a successful project will often have a single person doing something ordinary — reading, waiting, breathing. The AI render rarely does. That absence is what the architectural practitioner has to put back, by hand, in their commentary on the rendering and in the briefing of any human-facing presentation. If you use these tools — and you should — use them with care for the person who will inhabit the space. The render is only as good as the question it answers. The question is rarely about the surface.
Alnilam: Workflow recommendations now. Tufte leads — five named scenarios, sharp picks.
Sulafat: Five scenarios. Each one a sharp pick — the tool you would reach for first, and the supporting cast. Scenario one — hand sketch to walkthrough fast. You have a paper sketch and you need to put a moving image in front of a client by tomorrow. Pick Krea for the still — fifty milliseconds per render, infinite style variation; pick Veras if the sketch is already inside Revit or SketchUp. For the walkthrough video, Krea's video chain is sufficient. Total cost zero if you stay inside the free tiers; under fifty Australian a month otherwise. Scenario two — CAD model to client-grade walkthrough. You have a Revit model and you need a deliverable for a paying client. Pick Twinmotion if you and the client are inside Epic's free-revenue threshold; pick Enscape if you are a working practice that needs documentation and Revit integration depth; pick Lumion if landscape and atmosphere matter most; pick D5 Render if the AI enhancers earn their place. The single answer for most readers is Twinmotion. Scenario three — existing space to 3D model. You need to capture an existing room or building. Pick Scaniverse if you want it for free, on-device, with no cloud upload — best for clinical or confidential capture. Pick Polycam if you want the polished UX and willingness to pay. Pick Postshot if you have a GPU and want pro-grade splat reconstruction. Pick RealityScan if the geometry needs to be metrically defensible. Scenario four — generate a floor plan from a brief. You have a programmatic brief and you want a starting set of options. Pick Maket for the quickest text-to-plan; pick Autodesk Forma if you are already inside the AEC Collection; pick Hypar for healthcare or workplace, where the free tier earns its place. None of these replace the architect — they accelerate the early-design conversation. Scenario five — bleeding-edge experimentation. You want to see where the field is going. Pick World Labs Marble for the most usable export pipeline today; subscribe to Google AI Ultra and try Genie 3 if you have two-fifty US to spend on a curiosity; watch Decart Oasis. Don't put any of these on the critical path of a client deliverable. The composite workflow for the architect who wants the whole stack working together, from brief to client walkthrough: Maket or Hypar at the brief; sketch into Revit; Veras for diffusion-style ideation inside the CAD viewport; full model into Twinmotion or Enscape for the walkthrough; Polycam or Scaniverse for any existing-space capture component; Tripo3D or Meshy for any bespoke furniture or fixture asset. Total subscription cost for that composite — under one hundred and fifty Australian a month at the small-practice scale, less if Twinmotion's free tier applies. That is the toolkit, end to end, as of May 2026.
Alnilam: The wider frame. Adams to synthesise, then we close.
Zubenelgenubi: Adams. We are at an inflection point. Architectural visualisation has, for a century, been a specialised craft — practised by professionals trained in the conventions of the architectural drawing, the rendered perspective, the physical model. The tools we have walked through today flatten that craft into a general capability. A clinician in Port Pirie can produce visualisations a graduate architect of fifteen years ago could not have produced in a month. That flattening will change the profession of architecture. Not by replacing the architect — the architect's job has never been the rendering, except in the cheapest of fee structures — but by changing who can participate in the upstream conversation about what gets built and how. The medical officer who can put a Twinmotion walkthrough in front of a Health Advisory Council is a different kind of advocate than the one with a paper sketch. The community group fighting a development application is a different kind of stakeholder than the one with only a written objection. The flattening of architectural visualisation is a flattening of architectural voice. That is a good thing — provided we hold the architect, and the craft, in the centre of the work. The renders are tools. The buildings are buildings. The relationship between the drawing and the seeing, between the sketch and the inhabitation, has always been the architect's. The tools do not change that. They change who else can be in the room. For the clinician planning a rural facility — the question is not whether to use the tools; it is how to use them. Use them to make the clinical question legible to the architect. Use them to make the lived experience of the space legible to the committee. Use them to make the future inhabitant legible to themselves. Then step back, and let the architects design the building.
Alnilam: That is State of Play, Episode 37. Thank you Hermione, Feynman, Adams, Tufte, Curie, Osler, and Rogers — full cast for a survey episode, every voice doing the work their domain demands. Your host is exploring these tools for a clinical-facility planning project — specifically a dementia-friendly Emergency Department waiting area at Port Pirie Regional Health Service, plus an adjacent residential aged-care palliative-care suite question. The companion JTR brief lists the open decisions: whether to promote architectural AI to a full sub-domain inside the Creative Tools cluster; whether to commission a tool-comparison page for the Meridian Learn section; which specific tool to trial first on the HAC submission; and whether to extract a clinical-facility-design micro-tutorial as a recurring artefact. Sources at the show notes page, with the foundational papers — Mildenhall and colleagues 2020 for NeRF, Kerbl and colleagues 2023 for Gaussian Splatting, Xiang and colleagues 2024 for TRELLIS, plus the World Labs and DeepMind Genie blog releases — all linked. Cross-link to the Creative Tools cluster project landing in the Vault, where architectural AI now joins the eleven existing creative-tool sub-projects as a new sub-domain. If you find yourself in front of a building yet to be built — render the version of it that holds the person who will be inside. Until next time.