Charon: This is State of Play. I'm Charon. And this is the first proper weekly Augmentation Roundup — seven days, not the month-long sweep we opened the series with. Here's the striking thing about this particular week. The most useful augmentation that shipped wasn't a model, and it wasn't a server. It was a single new place in the session lifecycle to hang a hook. On the eighth of June, Claude Code shipped a post-session lifecycle hook — code that runs after a session ends and before the workspace is torn down.
Charon: That sounds like plumbing. It is plumbing. But sit with what it solves for a stack like ours. Every session this assistant runs is supposed to end with a written handover — a note from now-me to future-me, so the next session on the next machine wakes up knowing what happened. And the single most common way that discipline fails is the obvious one: the session ends before the note gets written. The post-session hook closes exactly that gap. It is the place where a handover can write itself, on the way out the door, whether or not anyone remembered to ask.
Charon: So that's the shape of the week. A model that quietly moved the top of the tier — and a four-line hook that fixes the most human failure mode we have. Around those two sit a fast-mode price cut, a clean-room debugging switch, a sovereign local voice engine, and one genuinely lovely creative tool that's already on the desk. Six picks, rated hard against rails that are — deliberately — already very good. Over to the frame.
Erinome: I'm Erinome, the standing anchor. One paragraph of frame, because the frame is what makes this series different from the dozen "what's new in AI" feeds that already exist. We don't list what shipped. We rate it — against the actual stack we run. A fleet of specialised sub-agents that fan out across the work. A personal tracker site with a clinical-simulation build inside it. A gateway that federates the machines over a private network. This show's own audio runner, the thing rendering this very episode. A vault that works as a second brain. And a resuscitation-training project with a three-dimensional capture pipeline behind it. A tool that dazzles in the abstract can still be useless to that. The fit is the test, not the demo.
Erinome: Four ratings, same as always. Strong-yes: install it this week. Try-it: worth one evaluation session, plausible but unproven for us. Monitor: interesting, not yet. And skip — always with a reason, because skip without a reason is just taste pretending to be judgment. And one rule sits in front of all four: name the gap before you name the tool. If it doesn't fill a hole we actually have, it doesn't matter how clever it is.
Erinome: The running order. Kore takes the survey — every candidate, grouped, functional descriptions only. Then the ratings, traded between Charon and Sulafat, with mechanism beats from Rasalgethi where the how matters. Then Charon's install shortlist — what to actually do this week, sequenced. Then Achernar on what to ignore and what to guard against. Then Sulafat on how the new pieces compose with the rails. And our featured install of the week gets its own segment, because it's the one that's already earning its keep. Over to the survey.
Kore: Kore here. Six candidates this week, in three groups — the platform layer that Anthropic shipped directly, the one community server worth your attention, and the featured creative tool. Functional descriptions only; the scoring comes after.
Kore: Group one, the platform. Four things landed in seven days. First, the post-session lifecycle hook in Claude Code, version two-point-one-point-one-six-nine, on the eighth of June — a hook that fires after a session ends and before the workspace is deleted, so you can snapshot uncommitted work or export logs before they evaporate. Second, on the same release, a safe-mode flag — start the tool with every customisation switched off: instructions file, plugins, skills, hooks, servers, custom commands, the lot — while login and model choice still work. A clean room, on demand. Third, a small cost lever: fast mode now runs on the upgraded flagship at a lower price, the flagship became the default on the paid tiers, and the rate limits roughly doubled. And fourth, the new top of the range — a Mythos-class model made safe for general release on the ninth of June, described as more capable than anything previously put out generally.
Kore: Group two, the community server. There's a small, sovereign text-to-speech server doing the rounds — a local, on-device voice engine that runs natively on Apple silicon and exposes itself as a Claude server. It speaks text without a single byte leaving the machine. Hold that one; it lands squarely on two of our projects. Group three is the featured install, and I'll leave that for its own segment. Rasalgethi — before the ratings, set the lifecycle-hook mechanism cleanly, because the whole top pick turns on it.
Rasalgethi: Rasalgethi. Happy to. Think of a session as having a life — it's born, it does work, it dies. For a long time you could attach behaviour to the middle of that life: before a tool runs, after a tool runs, when the model wants to stop. Hooks. Little tripwires. But the end of the session — the moment after the last word and before the room is swept and the lights go off — had no tripwire. Nothing ran there. So anything you wanted to happen "as the session closes" had to be remembered and done by hand, which means it mostly didn't happen.
Rasalgethi: The post-session hook is just a tripwire on that last moment. The deal is precise and that precision is the point: it fires after the work is done — so it can see everything that happened — and before the workspace is deleted — so the files are all still there to read. That's the one window where you can look back over the whole session and write down what it was. It's the natural home for a handover. Not a clever home. The correct one. That's the mechanism. Back to the ratings.
Charon: Charon. I'll take the first three. Post-session lifecycle hook — strong-yes, and it's the strongest yes of the week. The gap is real and chronic: handovers are supposed to be written at the end of every session, and the failure mode is always that the session ends first. This is a config-level change — a script in a hook directory — that cannot break the running work, because by definition it fires after the work is finished. We point it at a small "write the handover" routine that reads the session and drops a file into the handovers folder with the right naming. Lowest risk, highest discipline payoff. Install it.
Sulafat: Sulafat — and I want to underline why that one rates so high from a systems angle, because it's not about the feature. We already decided, weeks ago, that handovers are the connective tissue between sessions and between machines. We wrote the convention down — folder, filename, local time, em dash before the slug. The hook doesn't add a capability. It enforces a decision we already made at the exact moment we keep failing to honour it. That's the most valuable kind of augmentation there is: not new power, but a guarantee that an existing rule actually fires. Strong-yes, no reservation.
Charon: Safe mode — strong-yes, with a narrower use. The gap: when something in a heavily customised setup misbehaves, you cannot tell whether it's the base tool or one of the forty things bolted onto it. Our stack is exactly that — a federation gateway, a fleet of sub-agents, a vault full of standing rules, a pile of skills and hooks. Safe mode boots all of it off in one flag, so you can ask the clean question: is this the platform, or is it us? It's a diagnostic, not a daily driver. You don't work in safe mode; you bisect in it. Strong-yes as the debugging tool we've been missing.
Sulafat: Sulafat. The model tier — Charon, I'll take this one. Fast mode on the upgraded flagship at a lower price, the flagship now default, limits doubled. Rate it strong-yes, but the discipline from last week still governs it: the question is never "use the best model," it's "which class of call can drop a tier without the listener, the reader, or the patient noticing?" Last week we put the cheap small model under the mechanical fan-out. This week's lever is the other end — the heavy thinking is now cheaper in fast mode, so the orchestration tier got cheaper without getting worse. Config, no new trust boundary. Take it.
Charon: The new top-of-range model — monitor, edging to strong-yes for one seat only. It's the most capable thing generally available, and this assistant's own orchestration is the one job where the ceiling actually matters. But "most capable" is not a gap on its own, and most of our calls don't need it. So: route the orchestration seat to it, leave everything else where the cost-routing policy already puts it, and re-check next week. It's a tier ceiling moving up, not a hole being filled.
Sulafat: The sovereign local voice server — try-it, leaning strong-yes, and Rasalgethi should say why the locality is the whole story.
Rasalgethi: Rasalgethi. Our podcast voices today are synthesised in the cloud. The text of every episode — including the clinical ones — goes up to a service to be spoken, and comes back as audio. For a hobby feed that's fine. For a stack that wants to speak patient-adjacent material, and for a training project whose entire premise is sovereign, local, on-device — the cloud round-trip is the thing you're trying to design out. A voice engine that runs natively on the machine and never sends the text anywhere closes that loop. Same job, no round-trip. That's not a luxury for us; it's the architecture we already said we wanted.
Sulafat: Which is exactly why it's try-it and not strong-yes yet — the gap is real and the direction is right, but it has to clear the quality bar this show holds, and it has to prove it on real episode text, not a demo line. One evaluation session against a known script, compared head-to-head with the current voices. If it holds up, it graduates. The featured install is next, and it gets its own segment.
Sulafat: Sulafat. The featured install is called HyperFrames — open-sourced by the team behind a well-known avatar-video product, released under a permissive licence in April, and now wrapped as an installable plugin. It is the one on this list that's already on the desk; it went onto the workstation on the ninth of June, and the first test render of an intro for this very show is sitting in the show's intros folder right now.
Sulafat: Here's what it is, and it's beautifully simple once you see it. You write a web page — markup, styling, a little animation, media. HyperFrames drives a headless browser to render that page frame by frame, hands the frames to the standard video encoder, and out comes a deterministic video file. Frame-accurate. Reproducible. The same input gives you the same output every time. It treats video as code — which means an agent that's already fluent in web pages is, suddenly, fluent in video.
Charon: Charon. And that's the part that matters for us, because we don't have a motion-graphics person — we have an agent that writes web pages all day. So everywhere we currently need a short, designed, repeatable video, this turns it into a templating job. Start with the obvious one: an automatically generated intro for each episode of this show, keyed off the title in the production manifest. The runner already knows the episode number, the title, the date. Feed those into a HyperFrames template and every episode gets a clean, consistent, on-brand title card rendered from the manifest, with no hand-editing.
Charon: And it doesn't stop at the podcast. The sepsis poster work, the resuscitation-trainer overlays, the explainer videos for the tracker site, patient-education clips, grant-communication pieces — every one of those is "designed, short, needs to be reproducible and on-brand," which is precisely the shape HyperFrames fits. One tool, rendered the same way from web technologies we already write.
Sulafat: The concrete next use is the one already half-built: wire a HyperFrames template into the audio runner so that producing an episode also produces its intro, generated from the manifest title rather than rendered by hand. Build the template once; every future episode inherits it.
Sulafat: Caveats, because the featured slot still gets the honest accounting. The licence is permissive and the tool is free — there's no per-render fee. But it isn't free of cost: every render spins up a headless browser and pushes frames through the encoder, and that's real processor and memory time on whichever machine runs it. For a fifteen-second title card that's nothing. For long or high-resolution pieces it's a genuine workload you schedule, not a thing you fire off carelessly. Plan the renders; don't let them pile up on a machine that's doing other work.
Achernar: Achernar. The week's quieter, so the anti-patterns are sharper — three things to not do, each with a reason.
Achernar: First, the enterprise healthcare gateways. There's a whole category of impressive product this week — managed platforms offering governed access to three hundred-plus healthcare integrations, electronic record systems, billing, scheduling, the works, all behind one compliant gateway. It is genuinely good engineering. It is also built for a hospital IT department with a procurement budget and a compliance team, not for a single clinician with a vault and a federation of personal machines. The gap it fills is an institution's gap, not ours. Skip — with respect, and with the reason named: right tool, wrong scale.
Achernar: Second, the unifying middleware — the "one control plane to manage all your servers through a graphical console" tools. Same shape of error as the multi-harness conductors we skipped at the kickoff. They solve the problem of a team running dozens of connections across many people. We are one operator. Adding a management layer to be managed is negative work. Monitor at most; skip in practice.
Achernar: Third, and this is the values point, because the week handed us a perfect example. A new most-capable model arrived, and the temptation it manufactures every single time is to reach for the ceiling by reflex. The discipline cuts the other way. The newest, largest model is not an upgrade you apply; it's a tier you route to deliberately, for the one or two jobs that actually need it. Reaching for maximum capability on every call is how you burn budget and trust nothing to the cheaper tiers that were doing the job perfectly well. Capability is not the same as fit. And on the sovereign-voice candidate specifically — the one bar that doesn't move: anything that touches clinical or community material is held to local-only by default. A cloud voice for a music-bed tagline is fine. A cloud round-trip for patient-adjacent text is not, however convenient. That's a constraint, not a preference.
Sulafat: Sulafat. Three compositions, because the picks are worth more together than apart.
Sulafat: One — the post-session hook and the handover convention. We already wrote down where handovers live and how they're named, and the cross-device rule that the next machine reads the last few on waking. The hook is the actuator for that rule. Wire them together and the connective tissue between sessions stops depending on anyone remembering to lay it down — the note writes itself on the way out, in the right folder, with the right name, and the next session on the next machine simply finds it. The decision and the enforcement finally meet.
Sulafat: Two — HyperFrames and the runner. The runner already holds the structured truth of every episode: number, title, date, cast. HyperFrames turns structured truth into a rendered title card. Connect them and the show gains a visual identity as a byproduct of publishing, not a separate chore. And the same template family then serves the poster work, the trainer overlays, the site explainers — one rendering rail, many surfaces, all fed from data we already keep.
Sulafat: Three — the local voice engine and the trainer. The resuscitation-training project's whole thesis is sovereign, on-device, local-edge. A voice that synthesises without leaving the machine isn't just a cost win for the podcast; it's a component the trainer was always going to need — spoken prompts, scenario narration, feedback — generated locally, on the same principle the project is built on. Prove it on episode audio first, where the stakes are low, and you've de-risked a part you'll want in the clinical build later. That's the pattern worth keeping: let the low-stakes surface road-test the component the high-stakes surface depends on.
Erinome: Erinome, to close. Three things to carry into next Saturday. Watch the lifecycle surface — once a session can run code at its end, the obvious next question is what else belongs there besides handovers, and the answer for us is probably "a clean checkpoint of anything uncommitted." Watch the local-model and local-voice story keep maturing, because every piece of it that moves on-device is a piece the sovereign projects no longer have to apologise for. And keep the one discipline that makes this series worth the time: survey wide, rate ruthlessly, install narrow, and name the gap before the tool — even, especially, on the week a shiny new ceiling arrives. The hook that writes this episode's own handover goes in first. That's the week.