Alnilam: This is State of Play, Episode 36 — about forty-five minutes today on something that almost every doctor over fifty in regional Australia has thought about at three in the morning and never quite acted on. The fitness program. Not the version that gets prescribed in glossy magazines for someone who's already in shape. The version that has to work for a fifty-four-year-old, hundred-kilogram, busy rural medical officer with two dodgy knees and a clinical roster that doesn't care about your training plan. I'm Alnilam, anchoring tonight. The Ross family is across the desk. We've got William Osler Ross on the clinical reasoning, Hermione Granger Ross on the evidence base — and there is a lot of it, much of which has shifted in the last eighteen months — Richard Feynman Ross on the mechanism, Edward Tufte Ross on what to measure and what to ignore, Fred Rogers Ross on sustainability and the conversation that matters most, and brief cameos from Marie Curie Ross on the equity dimension and Epictetus Ross on what the Stoics have to say about a twelve-week arc. We are going to walk you through a real, evidence-led, knee-safe, age-appropriate, busy-clinician-compatible fitness program. Not as a prescription — this is not medical advice. As a worked example. Stay with us.
Alnilam: Picture the patient. He is fifty-four years old. He is a hundred kilograms at one hundred and eighty-eight centimetres, which puts him at a body mass index of around twenty-eight — overweight in the technical sense, not yet obese, carrying about twenty kilos he didn't carry at thirty. He is a medical officer at a regional hospital. He runs an outpatient clinic three days a week, covers the inpatient ward, does an after-hours roster, and one Sunday a month he runs an emergency shift that finishes at eleven at night. He has bilateral chondromalacia patellae — patellofemoral pain syndrome, PFPS — diagnosed informally five years ago, formally never. His knees ache when he stands up after sitting through a long meeting. He cannot run anymore. He used to run. He has not been to a gym in three years. His blood pressure is 138 over 86. His cholesterol panel is slightly off in the way that everyone's is at this age. His resting heart rate is in the low seventies. He drinks four or five standard drinks on a Friday night, sometimes six. He sleeps poorly when on-call. His wife is supportive. He wants to do something about it but every program he has read about online assumes he can run, has two hours a day, and is twenty-five. This is a real archetype. It is, by some distance, the most common adult patient any regional medical officer in Australia treats — and it is also the regional medical officer himself, more often than not. Tonight we walk through the program built for him.
Alnilam: And before we dive into the evidence, one more piece of framing. Osler, why does mainstream fitness writing fail this archetype so badly?
Orus: William Osler Ross here. The reason is straightforward. Mainstream fitness writing is a market, and the market has its eye on the wrong customer. The two big segments that the wellness industry caters to are the under-thirty-five male who wants to look better in a singlet, and the under-fifty woman who wants to feel better about herself. Both are legitimate. Neither describes the fifty-something clinician who has a sore knee and a Mediterranean midsection and a forty-five-hour clinical week. The fifty-four-year-old rural doctor is poorly served by the running-and-CrossFit canon because the canon assumes structural integrity that he doesn't have. He is poorly served by the high-intensity interval training literature because at his age and BMI the joint cost outweighs the cardiovascular gain. He is poorly served by the bodybuilding-derived strength programs because they centre around movements — back squat, deadlift, barbell bench — that load the patellofemoral joint or the lumbar spine in ways his anatomy can no longer absorb without complaint. And he is poorly served by the "just walk thirty minutes a day" health-promotion line because walking, while it's better than nothing, does not produce the body-composition change or the metabolic shift he is asking for in any reasonable timeframe. The result is that the most common adult clinical archetype in Australia has almost no published fitness writing aimed at him specifically. The program we're walking through tonight is one attempt to fix that.
Alnilam: And that is the spine of this episode. There is a draft fitness program. The program is published as a Vault document linked in the show notes. Tonight we explain the literature behind every choice in it. So that a thoughtful listener — clinician, registrar, anyone in a similar constraint set — could understand the why and build their own version.
Alnilam: Let's start where the program starts. The patellofemoral pain. Hermione, walk us through the evidence base on PFPS rehab — because it shapes everything downstream.
Erinome: Hermione Granger Ross, evidence base. Patellofemoral pain syndrome is the formal name for the condition often diagnosed informally as chondromalacia patellae — pain behind or around the kneecap, worsened by stair-descent, by prolonged sitting, by squatting, by running. It is the single most common knee complaint in adults under fifty in primary care. The evidence base for treatment is large and the headline finding has been stable for a decade. Exercise therapy is the first-line intervention. The highest-quality summary remains the Cochrane review by van der Heijden and colleagues, published in two thousand and fifteen — thirty-one trials, sixteen hundred and ninety participants — concluding that exercise reduces pain and improves function compared with no treatment, and that combined hip-and-knee exercise is better than knee exercise alone. The Cochrane verdict on quality was "very low" — meaning the underlying trials are mostly small and methodologically modest — but the consistency of direction across trials is strong.
Erinome: The crucial 2015 paper, the one that shifted clinical practice, is Lack and colleagues in the British Journal of Sports Medicine — a systematic review and meta-analysis showing that adding proximal hip strengthening to a knee-focused rehabilitation program produces clinically meaningful additional pain reduction. The standardised mean difference for pain was substantial. That paper, combined with Christopher Powers' body of work — particularly his 2010 JOSPT review on the influence of hip mechanics on knee injury — moved the field from "the problem is at the kneecap" to "the problem is at the hip." Weak hip abductors and external rotators allow the femur to internally rotate under load; when the femur rotates inward the patellar groove rotates with it, and the patella effectively tracks laterally relative to the groove. That lateral maltracking is what generates the pain. So strengthening the hip glutes — gluteus medius, gluteus maximus, the external rotators — keeps the femur in better alignment, which keeps the patella in better alignment, which reduces pain. That is the modern PFPS frame.
Erinome: And there is a 2026 update worth flagging — Hart and colleagues published in February of this year in the Journal of Orthopaedic and Sports Physical Therapy an evidence-and-gap map covering three hundred and seven randomised trials in patellofemoral pain. The take-home is sobering. Two-thirds of the trials are at high risk of bias. Only fifteen per cent used a proper diagnostic checklist. Pain and function are the dominant outcomes; sleep and psychological outcomes are measured in fewer than ten per cent. So a decade after van der Heijden's Cochrane verdict — "exercise works, but the evidence quality is low" — that verdict still stands. We have more trials, not better ones. The 2025 Halabi meta-analysis confirms once again that hip-plus-knee outperforms knee-only, with a standardised mean difference for pain of around minus one-point-three — a large effect. So the direction of the evidence is settled even though the quality of the evidence is not.
Orus: Osler. And the clinical implication for the program is this. The fifty-four-year-old chondromalacic doctor should not be doing back squats and leg extensions and calling that knee rehab. He should be doing closed-chain quadriceps work in the shallow range — mini-squats, leg press limited in range, wall sits — paired with hip strengthening — clamshells, side-lying leg raises, cable hip abduction, glute bridges, hip thrusts, Romanian deadlifts. That combination is what the evidence supports. The program's strength session reflects this exactly. No deep squats. No open-chain knee extension in the painful arc. Heavy emphasis on glute and posterior-chain work. Terminal knee extension — the band-resisted last thirty degrees — included specifically for what people used to call VMO bias.
Erinome: And while we're there — a brief note on VMO bias. The vastus medialis obliquus, the medial portion of the quadriceps, has been a clinical target for forty years because anatomical theory says it pulls the patella medially against the lateralising pull of the larger vastus lateralis. The trouble is the evidence for selective VMO activation is poor. A 2020 study by Harput and colleagues in Human Movement Science showed that even with abdominal-drawing-in manoeuvres, VMO activation increased by only two-and-a-half to five per cent over the vastus lateralis baseline. A 2025 meta-analysis of neuromuscular electrical stimulation in PFPS — adding NMES to exercise — showed no significant change in the VMO-to-VL ratio despite functional improvement. So the honest position in 2026 is that VMO bias is a useful pedagogical fiction. The active ingredient is loading the quadriceps as a unit and the hip as the proximal stabiliser. Terminal knee extension still has a place in the program, but for general quad-strength and end-range loading reasons, not because we are selectively activating the VMO.
Orus: And the corollary — closed-chain versus open-chain knee work. Steinkamp and colleagues in 1993 in the American Journal of Sports Medicine did the foundational biomechanical comparison. Leg press, which is closed-chain, imposes lower patellofemoral joint reaction force than leg extension, which is open-chain, in the range from zero to about forty-five degrees of flexion. Above fifty degrees the relationship inverts — open-chain leg extension at depth puts less load through the patellofemoral joint than closed-chain squat at depth. The clinical translation is: closed-chain work below ninety degrees, never below parallel; if you must do open-chain work, do it in the deep-flexion arc only. That paper is over thirty years old and modern modelling has refined the magnitudes but not overturned the qualitative pattern. The program's gym session reflects this exactly — box squats to a high box, goblet squats with depth limited, no leg extension in the painful early range.
Alnilam: The aerobic prescription. Three things in the program — swim, cycle, walk. No running. Zone 2 dominant. Hermione, walk us through the endurance training distribution literature, then Feynman on the mechanism.
Erinome: Hermione. The endurance training distribution literature has been dominated for two decades by Stephen Seiler's work. The canonical paper — Seiler and Kjerland in the Scandinavian Journal of Medicine and Science in Sports in 2006 — analysed training distribution in elite endurance athletes and found a consistent pattern. Roughly seventy-five to eighty per cent of total training volume is performed at low intensity. Roughly fifteen to twenty per cent is at high intensity. Threshold work — the middle zone — gets about five per cent. This is the so-called polarised distribution. Subsequent work — Tønnessen and colleagues in 2014 looking at gold-medal endurance athletes in the year of their gold medal; Guellich, Seiler and Emrich looking at junior world-class rowers — confirmed the pattern. About ninety per cent low-intensity training in the very best.
Erinome: And then the big update. Rosenblat and colleagues, with Seiler as senior author, published in Sports Medicine in March 2025 a network meta-analysis of individual participant data — thirteen studies, three hundred and forty-eight athletes — comparing polarised against pyramidal training distributions. Pyramidal is more low-intensity work and more threshold work, less true high-intensity work. The headline is that across the whole cohort there was no statistically significant difference between polarised and pyramidal for VO2 max gains or time-trial performance. The subgroup nuance — and this is the bit that matters for the fifty-four-year-old doctor — was that recreational athletes may actually respond better to pyramidal distributions, while elite competitive athletes may respond better to polarised. Which is a meaningful softening of the 2010s "polarised is best for everyone" orthodoxy. For the recreational athlete returning to fitness in middle age, the practical implication is that you do not need to obsess about hitting the high-intensity zones. The bulk of the value is in the low-intensity foundation.
Fenrir: Richard Feynman Ross. And here's the mechanism — why low-intensity, Zone 2 training does what it does. The cellular target of endurance training is the mitochondrion. When you do an hour of conversational-pace cycling at a heart rate that lets you talk in full sentences, you are oxidising fat in skeletal muscle at the maximum sustainable rate. The signalling pathway that gets activated by this — PGC-1-alpha is the master regulator — drives mitochondrial biogenesis. You make more mitochondria, larger mitochondria, better-organised mitochondrial networks. The capillary density in your trained muscle increases. The enzymatic machinery for fat oxidation — beta-oxidation enzymes, carnitine transferases — upregulates. The functional result is that your muscle can burn more fat per minute at a given heart rate. Which means that at fifty per cent of your maximum heart rate you go further, faster, with less reliance on carbohydrate. Iñigo San Millán, the cycling physiologist who has done the most to popularise the term Zone 2, puts it like this — Zone 2 is the metabolic-machinery building zone. It is not where you compete. It is where you build the engine that lets you compete.
Fenrir: And there's a corollary that matters for the fifty-four-year-old. Mitochondrial density declines with age. Sarcopenia — the age-related loss of muscle mass — is paralleled by mitochondrial dysfunction. The fifty-year-old has, on average, fewer mitochondria per gram of muscle than the thirty-year-old. Zone 2 training is one of the most potent interventions known to bend that curve. So the aerobic prescription in the program — swim Tuesday, cycle Saturday, walk Wednesday and Friday — is not just about burning calories. It is about rebuilding mitochondrial capacity. And the cardiovascular adaptations follow — lower resting heart rate, lower blood pressure, better stroke volume — but the metabolic adaptation, the fat-burning engine, is the headline.
Alnilam: Why no running, Feynman. And why high-cadence cycling instead.
Fenrir: The peak knee load numbers tell the story. The systematic review and meta-analysis in the British Journal of Sports Medicine in 2022 — sometimes called the "May the force be with you" paper — pooled the patellofemoral joint reaction force across activities. Walking comes in at roughly one-and-a-half times bodyweight. Cycling at an appropriate cadence comes in below one times bodyweight. Running comes in at a weighted mean of five-point-two times bodyweight, plus or minus one-point-two — so the upper end is over six times bodyweight per step. For a hundred-kilogram person that's six hundred kilograms of force across the kneecap every footstrike, twice per second, for the entire run. There is no chondral surface, healthy or chondromalacic, that absorbs that without paying a price.
Fenrir: And the per-bout dose matters. A thirty-minute run is something like five thousand to seven thousand footstrikes. Five thousand impacts each at five-and-a-bit times bodyweight is a cumulative load you cannot replicate in any other modality. So when the question is "can I do the running I used to do" — the answer for the fifty-four-year-old chondromalacic doctor is "no, and even if you could, the upside is small." Because — and this is the bit that surprises people — you can deliver every aerobic adaptation that running would give you, without the joint cost, by swimming and cycling. The cellular signalling for mitochondrial biogenesis doesn't care which modality drove the cardiovascular load. The capillary density adaptations are modality-agnostic above the activation threshold. VO2 max gains transfer reasonably well between running and cycling. The fat-oxidation engine builds either way. So the lost-running grief is real but the actual physiological loss is small.
Fenrir: And on cycling cadence specifically. Bini and Hume in 2013 published a study in Sports Biomechanics comparing peak patellofemoral compressive force at different cadences in cyclists at the same workload. At ninety revolutions per minute, peak knee force was twenty-nine per cent lower than at seventy revolutions per minute. Twenty-nine per cent. For someone with chondromalacia, that is the difference between a sustainable cycling habit and a knee flare-up. The reason is mechanical — at higher cadence each pedal stroke moves a lighter load over a shorter arc, so the peak force per stroke is lower. The corollary is that the worst thing you can do on a bike with a sore knee is grind. Out-of-saddle climbing, low cadence in a heavy gear, mashing the pedals — that's the cycling equivalent of running for your knees. The program is explicit on this — eighty-five to ninety-five revolutions per minute, low resistance, sit and spin. If you have to grind to get up a hill, drop the gear or get off and walk the bike.
Fenrir: One more thing on bike setup. Bini and colleagues also showed in a 2010 paper in the Journal of Sport Rehabilitation that saddle height affects knee work contribution. Too low a saddle increases peak knee flexion, which increases patellofemoral load. The rule of thumb in the program — heel on the pedal at the bottom of the stroke, leg straight; when pedalling normally, slight bend at full extension — gets the saddle height in the right ballpark. Wrong saddle height is the most common cycling-related knee injury cause, full stop. A bike fit is a two-hundred-dollar investment that prevents a thousand-dollar physio bill.
Alnilam: The strength session. Osler and Feynman, walk us through it exercise by exercise.
Orus: Osler. The program's strength template is eight movements, organised in supersets, finishing in sixty minutes. We've already covered why no back squat — patellofemoral load and lumbar load at the same time. The Romanian deadlift is the spinal-loading movement of choice instead. Why? Three reasons. First, it loads the posterior chain — hamstrings, glutes, erector spinae — without compressing the patellofemoral joint, because the knee stays nearly straight throughout the movement. Second, the eccentric loading of the hamstrings at near-full hip flexion is one of the best-evidenced ways to reduce hamstring injury risk and improve glute activation. Third, the spinal load at the bottom of the RDL is substantial but it is sustained briefly and the trunk angle is controllable. The technique points — neutral spine, soft knee bend, hinge at the hip, bar travels close to the body, weight in the heels — make it knee-friendly even at moderate load.
Orus: The hip thrust. The hip thrust is the gluteal-activation movement of choice for the same reason the RDL is the spinal-loading movement of choice — it produces maximal gluteus maximus activation across a controlled range of motion with no patellofemoral compression. Bret Contreras's body of work on this is the foundation; the EMG studies are unequivocal that the hip thrust produces higher peak glute activation than the squat or deadlift. For someone whose PFPS rehab depends on hip strengthening — which is everyone with PFPS — the hip thrust is structurally the right tool.
Orus: The pull-up over the lat pulldown. Both develop the latissimus and the upper back. The pull-up has two advantages — first, it loads the whole kinetic chain, requiring core stability and scapular control that the seated machine doesn't ask for; second, it grades naturally with bodyweight, so as you lose body mass the relative load drops and your reps increase, which is a built-in motivator. For someone who can't yet do a strict pull-up, the band-assisted progression — or a seated cable row as a substitute — works fine. The point is the upper-back work has to happen for postural reasons; the kneeless clinician slumped over the inpatient ward notes is anatomically primed for thoracic kyphosis and rounded shoulders, and the gym session is the counterweight.
Orus: The Pallof press for anti-rotation core, instead of crunches. Crunches load the lumbar spine in flexion under repeated compression — exactly the loading pattern that drives disc degeneration in middle-aged adults. The Pallof press is a cable anti-rotation movement — you hold a cable handle against your chest with the cable pulling sideways, and you resist the rotation. It trains the core for what the core actually does — stabilise against rotational forces, transmit load between the upper and lower body. Stuart McGill's body of work on lumbar mechanics underwrites this — McGill has been the loudest voice in spinal biomechanics for thirty years arguing that anti-rotation and anti-extension are the functionally important core capacities, and that repeated trunk flexion under load is harmful for most adults.
Fenrir: Feynman, on the terminal knee extension. The band-resisted terminal knee extension — the last thirty degrees of knee extension against a band — is in the program for a specific reason that's worth unpacking at the mechanism level. The patellofemoral joint reaction force is highest in the deep-flexion range and lowest in the near-extension range. So loading the quadriceps in the last thirty degrees gives you quadriceps work at the safest point in the range, with the lowest peak compressive force across the patellofemoral surfaces. It's a small movement. The bands provide light resistance. It is not the highest-intensity exercise in the session. But it serves a specific role — quadriceps loading in the safe range, daily reinforcement of end-range knee extension, low cumulative joint cost. For someone with chondromalacia, the daily small dose of safe-range quad work is more valuable than the occasional heavy dose of dangerous-range quad work.
Orus: And the progression rule. The program specifies two-and-a-half kilograms added to the RDL and the hip thrust every two weeks if the last set finished at rate of perceived exertion seven or below. No more than monthly progression on the squat or the bench press. The knee-specific work — terminal knee extension — is held at the same load, because it is about quality and recruitment, not about adding weight. That progression pattern is conservative by twenty-five-year-old standards and exactly right for a fifty-four-year-old. The literature on master's athletes is consistent that recovery between resistance sessions takes longer at fifty than at thirty, and that progressive overload at the same percentage rate produces more injury and less adaptation than slower progression. Forty-eight hours minimum between any two leg-loading sessions, and often seventy-two. The program respects this with one gym day per week.
Alnilam: Protein at fifty-four. Phillips's case. Hermione and Feynman.
Erinome: Hermione. The recommended dietary allowance for protein in adults is set at zero-point-eight grams per kilogram of bodyweight per day. That number was derived from nitrogen-balance studies and is intended to be the minimum required to prevent deficiency in healthy adults. It is the floor, not the ceiling. The sports-nutrition and geriatric-nutrition literature has been arguing for two decades that the optimal intake is substantially higher than the RDA — that the RDA prevents deficiency but does not optimise function. The PROT-AGE consensus statement, published by Bauer and colleagues in 2013 in the Journal of the American Medical Directors Association, recommends one to one-point-two grams per kilogram per day for healthy older adults, and one-point-two to one-point-five grams per kilogram per day for older adults with acute or chronic illness, and at least one-point-two grams per kilogram for older adults who are exercising regularly. The newer sports-medicine consensus puts the optimal intake for active adults at one-point-six to two-point-two grams per kilogram per day. Two grams per kilogram, which is what the program specifies, is a reasonable middle ground.
Fenrir: Feynman. The mechanism is what's called anabolic resistance. The cellular signalling that drives muscle protein synthesis in response to a meal of protein is mediated through the mTOR pathway, and the dose-response relationship for that pathway is age-dependent. A twenty-five-year-old gets near-maximal muscle protein synthesis from twenty grams of high-quality protein in a meal. A sixty-year-old gets a flatter response — they need a larger per-meal dose to get the same anabolic signal. That phenomenon is called anabolic resistance and it appears progressively from about age forty onwards. The mechanistic explanation is multifactorial — reduced insulin sensitivity at the muscle, reduced amino-acid transporter density, altered translation initiation factor expression — but the practical implication is simple. The fifty-four-year-old needs more protein per meal, and more total protein per day, than the twenty-five-year-old, to achieve the same muscle protein synthesis response.
Erinome: And the per-meal threshold is leucine-driven. Witard and colleagues in the American Journal of Clinical Nutrition in 2014 demonstrated that twenty grams of high-quality whey protein produces near-maximal muscle protein synthesis in young men. Above twenty grams, the additional protein gets oxidised or converted to urea, not built into muscle. That paper is sometimes cited as evidence that twenty grams is enough. The follow-up — Macnaughton, with Witard as senior author, in Physiological Reports in 2016 — showed that after a whole-body resistance workout, forty grams of whey produces greater muscle protein synthesis than twenty grams. So the dose-response curve shifts up with whole-body exercise. The crucial 2023 update — Larsen and colleagues in the Journal of Nutrition — looked at older overweight women in an eight-hundred-calorie energy deficit and found that thirty-five grams of whey was needed to saturate muscle protein synthesis. Fifteen grams was insufficient. The implication for the fifty-four-year-old in an energy deficit aiming to preserve lean mass — the per-meal protein dose needs to be in the thirty-five to forty gram range. Twenty grams may be enough in a young, well-fed person; it is not enough in an older person in a deficit.
Erinome: And the distribution matters as much as the total. Mamerow and colleagues in the Journal of Nutrition in 2014 compared two diets, both providing the same total daily protein — about ninety grams. One distributed it evenly across three meals — thirty grams per meal. The other distributed it the way most Western adults eat — small breakfast, modest lunch, large dinner. The even-distribution group had twenty-five per cent higher twenty-four-hour muscle protein synthesis. Twenty-five per cent for free, just by spreading the same total across three meals instead of skewing it to dinner. The implication for the fifty-four-year-old — breakfast cannot be one slice of toast. Lunch cannot be a coffee and a banana. Each main meal needs roughly thirty-five to forty grams of protein.
Fenrir: And the practical translation. Forty grams of protein is one of: a hundred and eighty grams of grilled chicken; two hundred grams of salmon; six eggs; two large tins of tuna; two hundred grams of Greek yoghurt plus a scoop of whey; two hundred grams of cottage cheese. The program's sample day hits two hundred grams of protein across five eating occasions, all from real food. No supplement protein necessary — though a whey protein scoop after the gym session is the one supplement with strong evidence at these stats.
Alnilam: The deficit. Five hundred calories below maintenance, not a thousand. Hermione and Rogers.
Erinome: Hermione. The rationale is metabolic adaptation. Rosenbaum and Leibel, the Columbia obesity researchers, have spent thirty years documenting what happens to energy expenditure when humans lose weight. The findings are now well-established. At ten per cent weight loss, both resting and non-resting energy expenditure fall below what their prediction equations would suggest. At twenty per cent weight loss, resting energy expenditure plateaus — a threshold effect — but non-resting energy expenditure continues to fall. The body becomes more energy-efficient. The same activity now burns fewer calories. The mechanism involves increased skeletal muscle work efficiency, increased SERCA-2 expression that reduces wasted calcium-cycling heat, and reduced thyroid and sympathetic nervous system tone. It is the body's evolutionary defence against starvation. It is also why most people regain the weight they lose.
Erinome: The practical implication is that the deeper the deficit, the more aggressive the metabolic adaptation. A five-hundred-calorie deficit produces roughly half a kilogram of weight loss per week with relatively modest metabolic adaptation. A thousand-calorie deficit produces faster initial loss but accelerated adaptation — and importantly, accelerated loss of lean mass alongside fat mass. The sports-nutrition rule of thumb — half to one per cent of bodyweight per week — translates for a hundred-kilogram person to half a kilogram per week. That is the sustainable rate. The program's prescription of two thousand two hundred calories against a maintenance of around two thousand six hundred and seventy puts the patient in a four hundred and seventy calorie deficit. Right in the sweet spot.
Callirrhoe: Fred Rogers Ross. And the most important number here is not the kilocalorie number. It is the months number. The diet that works is the one you can hold for twelve months. The diet that produces nine kilograms of loss in twelve weeks and that is then abandoned because it is too hard is worse than no diet at all, because it teaches the body to be more efficient and it teaches the patient that diets do not work. The case for a moderate deficit is not just metabolic, it is psychological. Five hundred calories below maintenance is sustainable. A thousand is not, for most people, for most of a year. So the program's deficit is set at the rate that the average doctor can hold while still going to dinner at the in-laws' once a month and not feeling like he is on a diet. That is the right design.
Erinome: And on why not the trendy diets. Keto first. Keto — very low carbohydrate, moderate protein, high fat — produces fast initial weight loss because the muscle and liver glycogen stores deplete and each gram of glycogen drags about three grams of water with it. The first three or four kilos of keto weight loss are largely water. The metabolic shift to ketosis takes two to three weeks and is poorly tolerated by many people during the adaptation phase. For someone training in Zone 2 and lifting weights, the glycogen depletion is a performance liability. Carbohydrate is the substrate for moderate-to-high intensity exercise; without it, training quality drops, and training quality is most of what drives the metabolic adaptation in the first place. So for the active fifty-four-year-old, low carb works against the program's other goals.
Erinome: Intermittent fasting. The sixteen-eight or the five-two patterns. The evidence is that intermittent fasting produces weight loss equivalent to continuous energy restriction at the same total calorie deficit. It is not metabolically magical. For a doctor whose schedule requires a pre-work breakfast at six in the morning before a long clinical day, the eight-hour eating window starting at noon and ending at eight is incompatible with how the program's gym session is structured. The pre-workout snack literature is clear — training fasted is fine for low-intensity Zone 2 work but produces lower-quality strength sessions. So intermittent fasting and the gym day don't combine well for this archetype.
Erinome: Paleo. Excludes legumes, dairy, and grains. There is no convincing evolutionary biology for the exclusion of legumes — they have been part of the human diet for at least eight thousand years. The exclusion of dairy in particular costs the patient one of the most concentrated protein sources available; for someone targeting two grams of protein per kilogram per day in an energy deficit, removing dairy makes the protein target harder to hit. Plant-based. The cardiovascular outcomes evidence for a predominantly plant-based dietary pattern is strong, but a pure plant-based diet makes the protein-per-meal target substantially harder to hit because plant proteins tend to be lower in leucine. For a sustainable approach in a busy clinician's life, the Mediterranean pattern — predominantly plant but with fish, eggs, dairy, and occasional meat — captures most of the cardiovascular benefit while preserving protein density.
Alnilam: The Mediterranean lean. Hermione.
Erinome: Hermione. The Mediterranean dietary pattern is the single most evidence-supported dietary pattern for cardiovascular disease prevention. The seminal trials are the Lyon Heart Study — de Lorgeril and colleagues, originally published in The Lancet in 1994 and updated through the 1990s and 2000s — which showed a roughly fifty to seventy per cent reduction in cardiac event recurrence over four years in patients post-myocardial-infarction assigned to a Mediterranean diet. And PREDIMED — the Prevención con Dieta Mediterránea trial, originally published in the New England Journal in 2013, retracted in 2018 because of randomisation irregularities affecting about six per cent of participants, then republished within months with conclusions essentially unchanged. The reanalysed PREDIMED data — same New England Journal in 2018 — showed roughly a thirty per cent relative risk reduction in major cardiovascular events for the Mediterranean-diet-plus-extra-virgin-olive-oil arm and for the Mediterranean-diet-plus-nuts arm, compared to a low-fat control.
Erinome: The Mediterranean pattern is not a prescription. It is a description. High intake of vegetables, fruits, legumes, whole grains, nuts, fish, and extra-virgin olive oil. Moderate intake of dairy and poultry. Low intake of red and processed meat. Moderate red wine with meals if you drink — that is the original Mediterranean caveat, although the 2020s alcohol-cancer evidence has weakened the case for the wine component, which we'll come back to. The umbrella reviews of 2024 and 2025 — eighteen meta-analyses pooling two hundred and thirty-eight randomised trials in one synthesis — consolidate the cardiovascular benefit and add the all-cause mortality benefit. For the fifty-four-year-old with a borderline lipid profile and a creeping blood pressure, the Mediterranean pattern is the highest-value dietary architecture available. The program's sample day — grilled chicken salads with olives and feta and olive oil, baked salmon with roasted vegetables, Greek yoghurt and berries and almonds — is Mediterranean-flexible by construction.
Erinome: And the practical implementation — Mediterranean is a pattern, not a prescription. It does not require a fortnight in Crete. It works in regional South Australia, in a busy clinician's kitchen, with what's on the shelves at the Port Pirie Foodland. The single most important purchasing change is the cooking oil — replace seed oils and butter with extra-virgin olive oil as the default cooking medium. The second most important is the protein source mix — fish twice a week, legumes regularly, nuts as snacks, and reducing red and processed meat to perhaps once or twice a week. The third is the vegetable volume — half the plate, every meal. That is the pattern. It is not exotic. It is not expensive. It does not require giving anything up — except the highly processed convenience foods that aren't really food.
Alnilam: The alcohol conversation. The hardest segment to write well. Delivered kindly. Fred Rogers.
Callirrhoe: Fred Rogers Ross. The alcohol conversation is the conversation that most clinicians have with their patients and never have with themselves. It is also the conversation that most fitness writing gets wrong — either by ignoring it entirely or by moralising about it. I want to do neither. I want to lay out what the literature shows, what realistic looks like, and let the listener decide for themselves.
Callirrhoe: Here is what the literature shows. The NHMRC, the National Health and Medical Research Council, updated the Australian guidelines on alcohol in 2020. The current recommendation, still in force in 2026, is no more than ten standard drinks per week, and no more than four on any single day, with less always being better than more. The previous guideline allowed fourteen per week. The change reflected the evidence base on alcohol and cancer, on cardiovascular outcomes, and on what's called the J-curve — the historical idea that moderate drinking was actually protective for cardiovascular disease. That J-curve has largely collapsed under more recent analyses. The 2023 Lancet Public Health position from the World Health Organization, led by Anderson and colleagues, states explicitly that there is no safe level of alcohol consumption for cancer risk. Alcohol is a Group One carcinogen for breast, colorectal, oesophageal, oral, pharyngeal, and hepatic cancers. The earlier idea that one or two drinks a day was actually good for your heart has been substantially revised.
Callirrhoe: For someone in a fitness program, three specific effects matter beyond the long-term cancer and cardiovascular risk. The first is calorie density. Alcohol provides seven calories per gram. Two standard drinks contain roughly two hundred and eighty kilocalories — more than the program's evening snack. Drinking four to six standards on a Friday night is six hundred to nine hundred kilocalories on top of food. Over a week, that is more than enough to neutralise a five-hundred-calorie daily deficit. The second is sleep architecture. Pietilä and colleagues in a 2018 study of over four thousand Finnish workers wearing heart-rate-variability monitors found that even one or two drinks before bed reduced overnight heart-rate-variability-derived recovery by ten per cent. Moderate intake reduced it by twenty-four per cent. High intake by nearly forty per cent. And — this is the important bit — the effect was the same in physically active subjects as in sedentary subjects. Exercise does not protect against alcohol's recovery cost. The third effect is on muscle protein synthesis. Parr and colleagues in PLoS One in 2014 showed that ingesting one-and-a-half grams of alcohol per kilogram of bodyweight — roughly twelve standard drinks for an eighty-kilogram person, so a heavier Friday than the program assumes — after exercise reduced post-exercise muscle protein synthesis by twenty-four per cent even when co-ingested with protein, and by thirty-seven per cent with carbohydrate alone.
Callirrhoe: So here is the kindly version. The patient does not need to give up alcohol. The patient probably will not give up alcohol; very few middle-aged Australian doctors do. But the patient who drinks four to six standards every Friday and a couple of glasses of wine with dinner most nights is, on the metrics that matter for this program, eating into the deficit, eating into the sleep recovery, and eating into the muscle-protein-synthesis response to the gym session. The realistic recommendation in the program — alcohol-free Monday to Friday, a maximum of four standards on Saturday night or split across Saturday and Sunday, no drinking the night before a training session — is below the NHMRC ten-per-week ceiling, preserves social drinking, and dramatically reduces the metabolic and recovery cost. It is not perfect. It is realistic. And the honest part — if the patient is currently drinking substantially more than this, the single highest-leverage change they can make for the program's outcomes is to cut alcohol back. Not running. Not protein supplements. Not extra gym sessions. Cutting alcohol. The losses scale faster on the alcohol axis than on any other axis available.
Callirrhoe: And one more thing. There is a version of this conversation that is moralising — that says the patient should not drink, that drinking is a moral failure, that the only acceptable answer is abstinence. I am not saying that. There is also a version of this conversation that minimises the cost — that says a drink or two never hurt anybody, that the evidence is contested, that you only live once. I am not saying that either. The middle position — drinking has costs, the costs are dose-related, you can choose how much you want to spend — is the position the evidence supports and the position that treats the patient as an adult capable of weighing trade-offs. If the patient decides the social value of a Friday night with friends is worth the metabolic cost, that is a defensible choice. The job of the program is to make sure the patient is making the trade-off knowingly, not accidentally.
Alnilam: What to measure. What to ignore. Tufte.
Autonoe: Edward Tufte Ross. The data architecture of a fitness program is more important than most patients realise. The wrong metrics will discourage progress that is real, and they will encourage decisions that are wrong. Here is what to measure, and what to ignore, in order of importance.
Autonoe: First — waist circumference. Measured at the level of the umbilicus, post-exhale, with a soft tape, monthly. Waist circumference is a substantially better marker of cardiometabolic risk than body mass index. The European Society for Clinical Investigation's 2025 consensus statement, with Després as senior author — the same Després who has spent forty years arguing this point — explicitly calls out BMI as inadequate as a sole diagnostic measure and calls for waist circumference as the supplement. The reason is that BMI cannot distinguish a hundred kilograms of muscle from a hundred kilograms of visceral fat. Waist circumference is a proxy for visceral adipose tissue, which is what drives the cardiovascular risk. A patient who loses three centimetres off the waist over twelve weeks while the scale moves only two kilograms has lost much more fat than the scale suggests. The waist measurement is the dominant outcome.
Autonoe: Second — weight, but only as a trend. Weighed on the same day each week, in the morning, post-bathroom, pre-food, pre-coffee. The daily weight oscillates by one to two kilograms purely from hydration, sodium intake, glycogen storage, and gut transit. A single day's weight is noise. A four-week rolling average is signal. The mistake patients make is weighing themselves every morning and reading the daily fluctuation as feedback about yesterday's behaviour. That is signal extraction from noise. It is psychologically destructive and it is statistically wrong. The right framing is — what is the trend across four weeks, and is the slope what we expect.
Autonoe: Third — resting heart rate. Measured first thing in the morning, lying in bed, before the alarm gets you out. Over twelve weeks of consistent Zone 2 training, the resting heart rate should drop by four to eight beats per minute. That drop is one of the cleanest markers of mitochondrial and cardiovascular adaptation available. A modern smartwatch will track this automatically and the four-week rolling average is the thing to look at. A sudden increase of ten or more beats per minute over baseline for several days is the overreaching signal — the body asking for a rest week.
Autonoe: Fourth — Zone 2 pace at a given heart rate. The functional fitness metric. If at week one the patient could hold one hundred and forty beats per minute at twenty kilometres per hour on the bike, and at week twelve they hold one hundred and forty beats per minute at twenty-five kilometres per hour, that is a measurable adaptation. Same effort, more output. That is what the training is building.
Autonoe: Fifth — gym lift progression. The working sets in the strength session should add weight or reps over twelve weeks. The Romanian deadlift starting at fifty kilograms for eight reps should be at sixty for eight by week twelve. That is sarcopenia going the other way.
Autonoe: And the things to ignore. Daily weight oscillation. Body fat percentage from consumer bioimpedance smart scales — the day-to-day variance is dominated by hydration status and the absolute accuracy is plus or minus three to five per cent versus DXA. So while the trend over months may be informative, any single reading is noise. Calorie burn estimates from wrist-worn fitness trackers — these are systematically inaccurate, often by twenty to forty per cent. Sleep stage breakdowns from consumer wearables — modestly informative about total sleep duration but unreliable for the REM-versus-deep breakdown that the marketing wants you to act on. Social media transformation photos — they are taken under different lighting, different angles, different posing, different abdominal tension. Comparison is the thief of progress when the basis of comparison is theatre.
Autonoe: The data architecture in summary — one monthly waist measurement, one weekly weight, one daily resting heart rate, one weekly Zone 2 pace check, every gym session logged. Five numbers. A simple spreadsheet or a single paper log. Resist the temptation to instrument further. Most progress is invisible at the day-to-day level and obvious at the month-to-month level. Build the apparatus that tells you about the month.
Alnilam: The twelve-week arc. What to expect. Feynman, Hermione, Rogers.
Fenrir: Feynman. The twelve-week arc has a fairly predictable shape, and explaining it in advance saves the patient a lot of self-doubt at the wrong moments. Weeks one and two are the central-nervous-system and form-acquisition phase. You are not getting fitter in the metabolic sense yet — the cellular adaptations need three to four weeks. But your nervous system is learning the movements. Your form on the Romanian deadlift is improving. The swim feels less awkward. The bike feels more natural. Sleep may be slightly disturbed because the body is recalibrating. Don't expect weight loss in weeks one and two — fluid shifts and glycogen loading often make the scale wobble. The right expectation is "I am learning to do this." Not "I am transforming."
Fenrir: Weeks three to six are the early metabolic shift. The mitochondrial adaptations have kicked in. The body is starting to oxidise fat at higher rates at given heart rates. Sleep often improves. Resting heart rate begins to fall. The scale will typically move three to four kilograms down. The first real moment of "this is working" is usually in week four or week five. The protein and the lifting are starting to add lean tissue while fat is coming off. The mirror lies but the waist tape tells the truth — three to four centimetres down is realistic.
Fenrir: Weeks seven to ten — the first plateau. This is the moment when patients abandon programs. The rapid weight loss of weeks three to six slows. The scale may park for a week or two. The reason is metabolic — the body has adapted to the deficit. Resting energy expenditure has fallen. The same training is producing less calorie burn because the patient is now ten or twelve kilograms lighter and movement costs are lower. This is normal. This is not failure. The right response is patience, not panic.
Erinome: Hermione. And the literature on this — the plateau at this stage is one of the most consistent findings in the obesity-management trials. It is a feature, not a bug. The patient who pushes through the plateau by cutting calories further or adding training volume typically experiences accelerated lean-mass loss, worsened sleep, increased hunger, and program abandonment within two weeks. The patient who holds the program steady through the plateau typically resumes loss at a slower rate in week ten or eleven. So the correct intervention at the plateau is — wait. Hold the prescription. Check waist circumference, not weight. Check the trend over four weeks, not the daily oscillation.
Fenrir: Weeks eleven and twelve are the reset decision. By this point the patient has lost five to eight kilograms, dropped four to six centimetres off the waist, lost four to six beats per minute off the resting heart rate, and added five to ten per cent on the working strength lifts. The body composition has shifted meaningfully. The maintenance calorie target needs recalculating — at lower bodyweight, maintenance calories are lower. The deficit needs to be repegged. The patient might also choose to take a deload week — fifty per cent volume, fifty per cent intensity, same diet, to let the cumulative training fatigue dissipate before the next twelve-week block.
Callirrhoe: Rogers. And the psychological arc that runs alongside the metabolic arc — patients often experience a confidence dip in week two when nothing has changed yet, a confidence spike in week five when the first real results appear, a confidence dip in week eight at the plateau, and a confidence stabilisation in week eleven as the long-term identity shift takes hold. Knowing this curve in advance lets the patient ride it. The patient who is told "you will probably want to quit in week two and again in week eight, and both moments will pass" is much more likely to make it to week twelve than the patient who is told "this will be steady linear progress." Linear progress is a myth. The real shape is a stutter, a climb, a plateau, a smaller climb, a reset. Tell the patient the truth about the shape and you bank the adherence.
Alnilam: When this fails. What to do. Osler and Rogers.
Orus: Osler. Three failure modes are common. Each has a protocol.
Orus: First — the knee flare. The patient has a flare-up of patellofemoral pain twenty-four to forty-eight hours after a training session. The pain is worse than baseline, persistent, sometimes accompanied by mild effusion. The protocol is to drop the offending modality for one week. Substitute pool walking or aqua-jogging, which load the muscles aerobically without joint compression. Ice fifteen minutes post-session for the flare week. Resume the original modality at fifty per cent volume the following week and build back to baseline over a fortnight. If the flare recurs on resumption, that is a physiotherapy referral, not a push-through. The single most common reason for recurrent knee flare in this program is one of two things — saddle height too low on the bike, or squat depth going below ninety degrees in the gym. Both fix easily once identified. The reason the program specifies a single physiotherapy session in week one or two is that an early appointment catches these technique faults before they generate weeks of cumulative tissue irritation.
Orus: Second — the "I've stopped losing weight" plateau. We've already covered the seven-to-ten week plateau as a normal phenomenon. The patient who has plateaued for four weeks at the same weight, despite adherence to the program, has likely either drifted upward on calorie intake — the most common cause, almost always unconscious — or has adapted metabolically to the deficit. The protocol is to retighten the food log for two weeks, weigh and measure everything, and check whether the calorie target is actually being hit. Eighty per cent of plateaus resolve on tightening the food log. For the other twenty per cent — the genuinely adapted patient — the move is a diet break. Two weeks at maintenance calories. Same training, same protein. The metabolic rate recovers somewhat. Then resume the deficit at the same level, with the deficit now being relative to a slightly higher maintenance.
Orus: Third — the "I'm too tired" pattern. The patient feels exhausted, training quality drops, sleep gets worse, motivation flattens. This is either overreaching from too much training, or life-loading from outside the program. The honest assessment matters here. If the resting heart rate has gone up ten beats over baseline for several days, it is overreaching — cut training volume to fifty per cent for a week. If the resting heart rate is normal but the patient is up against an on-call run, a research deadline, a family stressor, it is life-loading — drop to two maintenance sessions per week for the duration, do not try to maintain progression, and resume the full program when the external load lifts. The mistake patients make is trying to keep the program intact through life storms. The program is designed to be downsizable to two sessions per week without losing adaptations. Use that flex.
Callirrhoe: Rogers. And the compassionate-honest framing for all three failure modes — failure is data, not verdict. The knee flare is data about technique or load. The plateau is data about metabolic adaptation or calorie drift. The exhaustion is data about training load or life load. None of them is a judgement on the patient's character or motivation. The program is designed to absorb these signals and adjust, not to ignore them. The patient who hides a knee flare from himself for three weeks because admitting it feels like failure has caused a six-week setback that did not need to happen. The patient who admits the flare in week one, drops the modality, and substitutes pool work for a week, loses nothing. The infrastructure that makes failure-recovery work is honest tracking and willingness to adjust. The patient who can say "this week did not go well, here is what I am going to do differently next week" is the patient who makes it to week twelve.
Alnilam: Marie Curie, a brief cameo on the equity dimension before we close.
Vindemiatrix: Marie Curie Ross. The fitness program we have walked through tonight assumes a pool, a bike, a gym, a clinician with discretionary income and time, and a regional Australian supermarket that stocks fresh fish and salad greens year-round. Most of those assumptions hold in Port Pirie. Many do not hold in much smaller regional towns, and they hold much less in remote Aboriginal communities. The Wandearah Aquatic Centre is a thirty-minute drive from the centre of Port Pirie; the Alice Springs equivalent for an Aboriginal patient in Yuendumu does not exist. The Mediterranean diet's emphasis on extra-virgin olive oil and fresh fish twice a week is a North Adelaide supermarket assumption — it works less well at the Coober Pedy IGA where one Atlantic salmon fillet costs forty-five dollars and the freezer aisle is what's open. The bike-fit advice presupposes a bike shop that does fits, which is a metropolitan-and-large-regional resource.
Vindemiatrix: The point of saying this is not that the program fails the regional Australian context — it works for the regional medical officer it was designed for. The point is that the program is a worked example of one constraint set, and the equity question is what happens when the constraint set is harder. The patient with patellofemoral pain in a remote Aboriginal community has the same anatomy as the patient in Port Pirie. The evidence base on PFPS rehab does not change with geography. But the ability to act on the evidence is shaped substantially by what is available within driving distance. A pool. A gym. A bike. A supermarket with salad greens. The fitness writing that fails the fifty-four-year-old regional doctor — that we opened with — fails the patient in the remote community more profoundly. The honest extension of the program is to ask, for any patient — what is the constraint set, and what is the highest-leverage version of these principles that fits inside it. For the patient who has no pool — walking and bodyweight work and a creek for swimming once a week is a version. For the patient who cannot afford fresh fish twice a week — tinned mackerel is forty cents a serve and has the same omega-three profile. The principles scale across constraints; the prescription does not. That is the equity lesson worth carrying out of this episode.
Alnilam: Epictetus, your cameo. Discipline as sustainability.
Sadachbia: Epictetus Ross. I am cast tonight because there is a Stoic frame on the twelve-week arc that earns its place in the program. The frame is this. Epictetus, the slave-philosopher of Hierapolis, in the Discourses — book three, chapter fifteen — writes: "In every affair, consider what precedes and what follows, and then undertake it. Otherwise you will begin with spirit indeed, careless of the consequences, and when these are developed, you will shamefully desist." That is the line that has more to say to the fifty-four-year-old starting a twelve-week fitness program than any modern motivational poster.
Sadachbia: The Stoic point is not that you should be disciplined for its own sake. The Stoic point is that you should consider, before you begin, what the program will cost you across its full arc — the early-morning starts, the Friday-night-out trade-offs, the slow plateau weeks when nothing visible is happening, the recalibration in week twelve. Then, having considered, you commit, and you remove the question of "should I do this today" from your daily decision space. The decision was made at the beginning. The execution is what's left. That is what Stoic discipline actually is — not grim self-flagellation, not the unsustainable burst of January resolve, but the patient continuation of a thing you decided in advance was worth doing. The twelve-week arc only works if the decision to do it was made before the program started, not renewed daily. So if you are weighing whether to start the program described tonight, consider both its beginning and its consequences. Then commit. Then stop deciding.
Alnilam: The wider frame. How a clinician's own fitness reshapes the consult-room conversation. Rogers and the close.
Callirrhoe: Rogers. The under-discussed payoff of the fifty-four-year-old doctor doing the twelve-week program is not in the doctor's body. It is in the doctor's clinic. When you have actually done patellofemoral rehab — felt the difference between the painful arc and the safe arc, felt the cumulative quad work over six weeks, felt the difference high-cadence cycling makes versus grinding — you advise it differently. The recommendation becomes specific instead of generic. The encouragement is credible instead of theoretical. When you have actually held a twelve-week deficit, ridden the plateau, felt the metabolic adaptation, you understand patient inertia differently. The patient who has lost five kilograms and stalled at week eight is not weak-willed; they are at the most universal sticking point in the metabolic literature. When you have actually had the alcohol conversation with yourself — and made the adjustment, or not — you have the conversation with patients with less judgement and more practical advice. The doctor who eats five servings of vegetables a day, who cycles three times a week, who does the resistance work, who has cut back on alcohol because he has felt the recovery cost — that doctor is a different consult-room presence. Not because he is better. Because he knows the path from the inside.
Callirrhoe: And the wider frame is — fitness is not vanity for a fifty-something clinician. It is professional competence. The clinical skills that matter most in a generalist regional practice are pattern recognition, stamina, judgement under sleep deprivation, and the ability to be present with a patient in distress. All four are affected by the physical and metabolic state of the clinician. The doctor who is doing the work on himself is investing in his clinical capacity in a way that the doctor who is not doing the work cannot match. The ten years of clinical practice he has left at fifty-four — five years past the typical Australian rural-doctor retirement age, fifteen years before the typical age of significant cognitive decline — those ten years are an asset whose maintenance starts in the gym. The program is not about the body. It is about the practice.
Alnilam: And the closing acknowledgement, briefly. The composite case we have walked through tonight — the fifty-four-year-old, hundred-kilogram, busy regional medical officer with bilateral chondromalacia patellae — is, as the more attentive listener may have already worked out, also the person hosting this podcast. The program in the show notes is the program your host is starting tomorrow. The twelve-week arc you have heard described is the twelve-week arc your host has signed up for. Not because this is a personal podcast — it isn't, and the framing tonight has deliberately been on the archetype rather than the individual. But because the experience of building this program for himself was the prompt to build it for the listener too. The literature is the literature. The constraint set is shared. The program works for one fifty-four-year-old regional doctor and it works, with adjustment for individual circumstance, for many.
Alnilam: Tonight we have covered the patellofemoral pain rehab evidence base — van der Heijden's 2015 Cochrane, Lack and Powers on hip strengthening, the 2026 Hart evidence-gap map. The aerobic prescription — Seiler's polarised-versus-pyramidal training distributions, the 2025 Rosenblat update, the Zone 2 framing from San Millán and Brooks. The patellofemoral biomechanics — Steinkamp's closed-versus-open-chain, the modern peak-force literature. The cycling cadence work — Bini and Hume on the twenty-nine per cent peak-force reduction at ninety revolutions per minute. The protein literature — Phillips's body of work, Bauer's PROT-AGE consensus, Witard on the leucine threshold, Mamerow on per-meal distribution, Larsen's 2023 update on the higher per-meal dose required in energy deficit. The Rosenbaum and Leibel metabolic adaptation work. The PREDIMED retraction-and-republication. The 2018 Pietilä study on alcohol and overnight heart-rate variability. The NHMRC 2020 alcohol guidelines and the 2023 Lancet Public Health position. The EWGSOP2 sarcopenia consensus. The 2025 European obesity-research consensus on waist circumference over BMI. The Stoic frame on commitment. The equity frame on what scales and what does not. And the closing observation that fitness for the busy clinician is, in the end, professional competence — that the program is not about the body. It is about the practice.
Alnilam: Thanks to the Ross family — Osler, Hermione, Feynman, Tufte, Rogers, Marie Curie, and Epictetus. The fitness program file is linked in the show notes. The companion JTR brief is linked in the show notes. Music as ever — intro is Comparsa by Kevin MacLeod from Incompetech, outro is Awaiting Return, both Creative Commons Attribution four-point-zero.