Kore: This is State of Play. I'm Kore. And this is something new — the first episode of a sub-series we're calling the Augmentation Roundup. So let me open it the way it deserves to be opened, with the single most striking number from the last month. There is a Claude Code skill — a plain folder of markdown instructions, the cheapest possible kind of augmentation — that has crossed two hundred and twenty-one thousand stars on GitHub, and has been formally adopted into Anthropic's own official marketplace. It's called superpowers. It is not a model. It is not a server. It's a method, written down — a method that teaches an agent to slow down and work properly. Brainstorm. Design. Plan in small tasks. Dispatch sub-agents one at a time. Review twice. Then merge and clean up. Two hundred and twenty-one thousand people starred a discipline.
Kore: That's the story of the month, and it's the thesis of this whole sub-series. The highest-leverage augmentations right now are not the flashiest ones. They're the ones that change how the work gets done, not the ones that look most impressive in a launch video. And running underneath that skill, the same month, Anthropic did something quieter and arguably larger. They shipped Claude Haiku four-point-five — a small, fast model that codes at roughly the level of last generation's mid-tier, at one-third of the cost and more than twice the speed, scoring around ninety per cent of the flagship on an agentic coding benchmark, and actually beating the previous mid-tier at driving a computer. One outlet's headline was simply that Anthropic was giving it away.
Kore: For a stack like ours — one that fans out dozens of sub-agents a day across the dispatch work, the site builds, this very podcast's research — a cheap model that doesn't fall apart under agentic load isn't a footnote. It's a budget line that just got cut by two-thirds. So hold both of those, because they're the two strongest picks of the entire month, and they sit at opposite ends of the spectrum. One is a frontier company's small model, given away. The other is one person's folder of written-down discipline, starred a quarter of a million times. Between those two poles is everything else we'll survey today — and the job of this series is to tell you, ruthlessly, which of it earns a place on rails that are already, deliberately, very good.
Erinome: I'm Erinome, the standing anchor. Let me frame what this sub-series is, because it's the first one, and the frame matters more than any single tool we'll name today. Every week — Saturday morning, with the instalment going out alongside — we survey what's happened in Claude augmentation-land. The MCP servers. The skills. The plugins. The agent patterns. The workflow tooling. The whole churning ecosystem of things that bolt onto a Claude and make it do more. And then we do the part almost nobody else does. We don't just list what's new. We rate it — against the actual stack we already run.
Erinome: And that stack is specific, which is the whole point. There's a fleet of specialised sub-agents that fan out across tasks. There's a personal site with a clinical-simulation build inside it. There's a gateway that federates the machines — the desktop, the workstation, the laptop — over a private network. There's this podcast's own audio runner, the thing that will render and publish this very episode. There's a vault that functions as a second brain. And there's an augmented-reality resuscitation-training project with a three-dimensional capture pipeline behind it. A tool that's brilliant in the abstract can still be useless to that. The abstract isn't the test. The fit is the test.
Erinome: The rating frame has four settings, and I want them clear up front, so every judgment today is legible. Strong-yes: install it this week, it fills a real gap. Try-it: worth a session of evaluation, the case is plausible but unproven for us. Monitor: interesting, not yet — watch it. And skip — always with a reason, because "skip" without a reason is just taste dressed up as judgment. The question behind every rating is the same one. Does this fill a gap we actually have? Or does it overlap something we already run, without clearly beating it? If it doesn't fill a gap, we skip it — however clever it is.
Erinome: This is a kickoff, so the scope is a full month rather than a week — the eighth of May to the eighth of June — which means more candidates than a normal instalment: a dozen or so, grouped by category. The weekly version, from this Saturday, will be tighter — five to ten, the freshest seven days. Here's the running order. Kore has the survey — every candidate, grouped, functional descriptions only. Then the ratings, traded between Charon and Sulafat. Then Charon's install shortlist — what to actually do this week, in order. Then Achernar on what to ignore and what to guard against, because this was a consequential month for that. Then Sulafat on how it all composes with the rails we run. And I'll close with the forward look. Over to the survey.
Kore: Kore again. I'll walk the candidates in five groups — Anthropic-first, community servers, community skills, agent patterns, and the infrastructure layer underneath all of it. Functional descriptions only here; the scoring comes after. But before I start, one piece of vocabulary, because this series will assume it every week and we should set it once and cleanly. Rasalgethi — pull the three words apart. Server, skill, plugin. People blur them into mush, and the mush hides the judgment.
Rasalgethi: Rasalgethi here. Three words, three genuinely different things, and thirty seconds kills the confusion for good. A server — a Model Context Protocol server — is a little program that exposes tools and data over a standard protocol. Picture a wall socket of a fixed shape that any AI appliance can plug into. The Zotero server, the browser server — sockets. A skill is the opposite of a program. It's just a folder with a markdown file of instructions, maybe a script or two, that the model reads and follows when the moment is right. No socket, no protocol — just written-down know-how. Superpowers is a skill.
Rasalgethi: And a plugin is a shipping box. It bundles servers, skills, sub-agents, slash-commands and hooks into one installable unit, so you can hand someone a whole capability in a single move. So the clean way to hold it: a server gives the model new reach — places it can touch. A skill gives it new judgment — better habits about what to do. And a plugin is just delivery — how you ship either one. Reach, judgment, delivery. Once those three are distinct in your head, the whole fourteen-thousand-item ecosystem stops being a blur and starts being a menu you can actually read.
Kore: Perfect. Reach, judgment, delivery — hold that for the whole episode. Group one: Anthropic-first. The biggest item is the model itself — Claude Haiku four-point-five, the small model I flagged in the open. Coding parity with the previous mid-tier, a third of the cost, double the speed, around ninety per cent of the flagship on agentic coding, and notably strong at computer-use — driving a screen, clicking, reading a page back. The pricing is a dollar in, five dollars out per million tokens, which for high-volume agentic work is the number that actually changes behaviour. Second in this group: the official plugin marketplace has matured into a real front door — a curated, Anthropic-managed directory, with type-to-filter now live on the plugin and skills pickers. Finding a vetted augmentation is a search box now, not a scavenger hunt across random repositories.
Kore: Third, and this one's aimed straight at our visual pipeline: at the end of April, Anthropic shipped nine first-party creative connectors — the modelling tool, the big design suite, the engineering suite, the music tools. The one that matters to us is the modelling-tool connector, because it lets an agent drive the modelling application directly, rather than narrating a sequence of clicks for a human to perform. We build synthetic three-dimensional scenes in exactly that tool — that's how the synthetic orbital scene in the simulation was made — so a direct connector removes a manual seam. Fourth, and I name it only to dismiss it: a tranche of legal-vertical plugins and a couple of dozen enterprise connectors. Genuinely useful to a law firm. Nothing to do with us.
Rasalgethi: Rasalgethi — one more mechanism beat, because that "ninety per cent on agentic coding" number will get quoted all week and it's worth knowing what it measures. It is not ninety per cent on a quiz. An agentic-coding benchmark hands the model a real repository and a real task — fix this failing test, add this feature — and lets it work the way an agent actually works: read files, edit, run the tests, read the errors, edit again, loop until green or until it gives up. The score is the share of tasks it completes end-to-end, unaided. So "ninety per cent of the flagship" means the small model finishes nine of every ten tasks the big one finishes, on its own, in a loop. That's a far harder bar than answering a question, and it's the bar that matters for sub-agent work — because a sub-agent isn't asked a question. It's handed a job and left to finish it. A small model that finishes jobs is the whole game.
Kore: That's exactly the distinction that makes the cheap model interesting rather than just cheap — thank you. Group two: community servers — the reach layer. The ecosystem crossed fourteen thousand servers this month, which is mostly noise, and the noise is precisely why this series exists. The signal inside it: the reference-servers repository sits near eighty-six thousand stars. The browser-automation server, from Microsoft, is past thirty thousand stars and is effectively the standard way to let an agent see and click a real web page. A documentation server feeds current, version-correct library docs into the model so it stops writing against last year's interface. And the one I care most about for us: a Zotero server — it connects a reference library straight into the assistant, so it can read papers, summarise them, walk citation graphs, and lift annotations out of the PDFs. There's also a broader research-workspace project stitching a reference manager, a notes vault, and a notebook tool into one operable surface — over-built for us, but the lineage is interesting. And separately, an infrastructure provider released thirteen remote servers in April — databases, object storage, logs — that need no local install at all, which becomes relevant the moment any public surface of ours moves behind that kind of edge.
Kore: Group three: community skills — the judgment layer. The headline is superpowers, which I opened with. A skills framework that encodes an entire development methodology into the agent's habits: brainstorm the idea, validate the design before building, plan in small tasks, dispatch a fresh isolated sub-agent per task, review in two stages, finish, and clean the branch. Test-first, do-the-simplest-thing, don't-repeat-yourself — baked in, not remembered. Two hundred and twenty-one thousand stars, and a slot in the official marketplace, which is the strongest provenance signal the ecosystem has. Around it, the skills directories have exploded — one community index now tracks over fifteen thousand plugin repositories, up from around four thousand a year ago. The volume is staggering and almost entirely beside the point; the index matters far less than the one or two skills inside it that actually change your loop.
Kore: Group four: agent patterns — how the pieces are being wired together. The pattern with real traction is disciplined sub-agent orchestration: one coordinator, fresh isolated sub-agents per task, two-stage review, branch hygiene at the end. Which is, not coincidentally, exactly what superpowers packages — the pattern and its best-known implementation are the same thing this month. There are also multi-harness conductors — frameworks that try to make Claude and two or three rival command-line agents collaborate by consensus, routing tasks between them and voting on outputs. I'm flagging them neutrally here and letting the ratings be honest about them later. And group five, the one that should make us sit up straight: the infrastructure and security layer underneath all of it. Rasalgethi, before I describe the threats — there's one of them that's almost beautiful in its nastiness, the cost one. Set up the mechanism, because it's the kind of thing that sounds abstract until you see how it works.
Rasalgethi: Happily, because it is elegant, in the way a good trap is elegant. Here's the cost-inflation attack. An agent works by calling tools in a loop — call a tool, read the result, decide the next call, repeat, until the job's done. Normally that loop is short and converges. Now imagine a malicious server whose tool descriptions are quietly written to keep the loop going — every result subtly implies one more necessary call, then another, then another. The agent isn't malfunctioning; it's following instructions that were engineered to never quite finish. And because each call is individually reasonable, nothing trips the usual alarms. Reports this year put the inflation at a factor in the hundreds — one query that should cost a cent quietly costing several dollars — while slipping under standard detection at a rate well below three per cent. The defence isn't clever. It's a budget ceiling and an eye on how deep the tool-call chain is allowed to go. But you have to know the attack exists to think to set the ceiling. That's the whole reason this group is in the survey.
Kore: Exactly — and that's the spine of the anti-patterns segment, so I'll let Achernar carry the rest of it later. To close the survey: the named threats are now catalogued. A secure-AI coalition mapped a dozen threat categories and close to forty distinct attacks. A national security agency published its own formal guidance this year. And the founding incident behind all of it — scans earlier in the year found thousands of these servers exposed to the open internet with no authentication whatsoever. That last one should sound familiar, because it's the exact failure we just spent real effort closing on our own public surface. So that's the survey — Anthropic-first, community servers, community skills, agent patterns, and the security layer underneath. Over to the ratings.
Charon: Charon here, and I'll take the verdicts blunt, the way they're useful. Start with the model, because it sits underneath everything else and the verdict cascades. Claude Haiku four-point-five — strong-yes, and it isn't close. Here's the gap it fills. We fan out a great deal of cheap, mechanical, parallel work — scouting a codebase, sweeping a tree of files, drafting a first pass, the kind of task where the flagship model is a sledgehammer driving a tack. Paying flagship rates for sub-agent grunt work is pure waste. A small model that holds ninety per cent of agentic-coding quality at a third of the cost flips the economics of going wide. You don't downgrade the thinking. You downgrade the labour. The concrete path is a configuration change, not an install — point the cheap tier at the small model, keep the heavy model for orchestration and judgment. Risk: essentially none. Same provider, same trust boundary we already accept.
Sulafat: Sulafat — the systems lens, and I'll sharpen exactly where that bites, because "a cheaper model exists" undersells it. Our single most expensive habit isn't any one big call. It's breadth. When we sweep a site's worth of routes, or audit a tree of files, the bill is the per-leaf cost multiplied across every leaf in the fan. Cut the per-leaf cost by two-thirds and the saving compounds with the width of the fan — and width is the dimension we scale on most. So the strong-yes isn't "cheaper model." It's "the cheaper model removes the tax on the one move we make constantly: going wide." That's a structural saving, not a marginal one. Now superpowers — strong-yes from me as well, but with a caveat the model doesn't carry. It changes the shape of the loop, not the price of a step. And a shape change is higher-risk than a price change, however good the shape.
Charon: Agreed — superpowers, strong-yes, adopt narrowly first. The gap it fills is one I'll own honestly: our multi-agent dispatch is effective but improvised. It works because the operator is good, not because the method is encoded. Superpowers encodes the method — the two-stage review in particular, which is the highest-yield habit in agentic coding and the one we apply least consistently. The risk is equally honest: drop a rigid methodology on top of working improvisation and you can get friction before you get payoff. So the install isn't "turn it on everywhere." It's "run the full loop once, on one contained feature, and keep what survives contact." Third strong-yes: the Zotero server. The gap is glaring — there's a reference library of several thousand items and a research workflow that still moves citations by hand. A server that reads that library, summarises, walks citations and lifts annotations turns an evidence-gathering chore into a query.
Sulafat: And it earns the strong-yes on a second axis, not just the gap — it's data-sovereign by construction. It runs against the local library; the papers never leave the machine. That's the only way research tooling gets anywhere near patient-adjacent work, so the architecture isn't incidental, it's the qualifier. So the strong-yes shortlist locks at three — the cheap model, the discipline, the reference server. One of each kind, which Charon will make something of later. Now let me run the try-its, because they're real but not this-week. The modelling-tool connector: try-it. There's a genuine pipeline here — synthetic scenes built in that tool, captured as point-cloud renders for the simulation and the resuscitation trainer — and a connector that lets the assistant drive the tool directly removes a real manual seam. But it drives a desktop application, which makes it infrastructure-touching. That's an evaluation with a rollback plan, not a reflex install.
Charon: Right — try-it, not strong-yes, precisely because it touches a desktop app rather than just answering a call. Continuing the try-its. The documentation server — current, version-correct library docs into the coding model — try-it, low stakes, an easy win against stale-interface errors on the site work. The browser-automation server: try-it, but soft, and here's the honest reason it's soft rather than strong — we already drive that browser engine by hand for verification. The server standardises something we already do; it doesn't unlock something we can't. An Obsidian server for the vault: try-it, leaning monitor, same reason — we already reach the vault through the filesystem. "Structured query over my own notes" is a nice-to-have, not a gap, and it has to beat plain file access to earn the slot, which it hasn't yet proven.
Sulafat: Two more try-its before the monitors, briefly, because they round out the picture. The documentation server I'd actually nudge from try-it toward "quiet yes" — current, version-correct library docs piped into the coding model is the cheapest possible fix for the most common failure mode in agentic coding, which is writing confidently against an interface that changed three months ago. Low stakes, low cost, immediate payoff on the site work. And the official marketplace itself — not a tool you rate, it's the channel. But the channel earns a standing rule: shop the curated, vetted directory first, and treat anything outside it as guilty until proven innocent. That habit folds straight into the security lens, and after this month it's not optional.
Charon: I'll back the documentation-server nudge — it's the rare augmentation where the downside is genuinely just "didn't help much," and the upside is fewer wrong-interface errors on every coding session. Worth the session to wire it. And the marketplace-as-channel framing is right — the directory is the trust funnel, and the whole ecosystem's safety story for a small operator routes through "did this come from somewhere vetted." Which is the natural hand-off into the monitors and skips. Sulafat — the things we watch but don't touch, and the things we walk past entirely.
Sulafat: And now the monitors and the skips, with reasons, because Erinome was firm that skip needs one and so does monitor. Monitors first. The infrastructure provider's thirteen remote servers — monitor. Genuinely well-built, but they pay off only once a public surface of ours sits behind that edge. The day the site's authentication moves there, they graduate from monitor to try-it overnight. The research-workspace mega-hub — monitor, leaning skip-for-us — it stitches three tools together, but we'd be better served by the single Zotero server plus the file access we already have than by adopting a whole workspace to get one of its three legs. Buy the leg, not the table.
Charon: And the clean skips. The multi-harness consensus conductors — the frameworks making three rival command-line agents vote on an answer. Skip — not even monitor — and the reason is structural, not aesthetic. We already federate our machines through one gateway with one orchestration layer. Bolting on a second control plane that arbitrates between competing agents adds coordination overhead to solve a problem a single operator doesn't have. It's a team tool, and we're not a team. The legal-vertical plugins and the enterprise connector pack: skip, wrong domain, zero overlap. And the long tail of the fourteen-thousand-server ecosystem: skip by default — the base rate on an unvetted community server is poor, and after this month's security news, distrust is the correct default, not curiosity. So the tally: three strong-yes, four try-it, two monitor, three skip-classes. The ecosystem's size argued for more selectivity, not less — which is the entire discipline this series exists to enforce.
Charon: Charon — the action segment. Three installs this week, sequenced, with the exact moves, and the sequence itself is part of the safety. Do them in this order. One: the cheap model. Lowest-risk, highest-immediate-return, so it goes first. Reassign the sub-agent tier — the scout, the sweep, the mechanical-edit workers — to Haiku four-point-five, while orchestration and the genuine judgment calls stay on the heavy model. No new software, no new trust boundary; it's purely a decision about which model answers which class of call. Validate it on one real fan-out — a file sweep, a route audit — and read the bill. You'll see the two-thirds cut on the very first wide run, and if quality drops anywhere, you've changed one config line and you change it back.
Charon: Two: the reference server. Install the Zotero server, pointed at the local library. The move is a single connector registration — add the server, give it the local library path, confirm it can read the collection and nothing more. Then test it on a live job — ask for a citation walk on a topic we're actively writing, and watch it surface annotations the manual pass would have missed. Because it's local-only and read-shaped, the risk surface is small. But apply the lens anyway, every time, no exceptions: least privilege, read access only, and no token sitting in a plaintext config file. The habit has to be uniform or it isn't a habit.
Charon: Three, and last because it's the one that changes how the work feels: superpowers, from the official marketplace. The install is a single plugin-install command against the Anthropic-managed catalogue — provenance you can trust, which after this month is not a small thing. But do not turn it loose on everything at once. Pick one contained feature — something real but bounded — and run the full loop exactly once: brainstorm, design, plan, dispatch sub-agents, review in two stages, finish, clean the branch. Then keep the habits that earned their place and quietly drop the ceremony that didn't. Adopt the method, not the dogma.
Charon: And the sequencing logic, stated plainly so it's reusable every single week from here. Cheapest-and-safest first — the model swap pays off immediately and cannot break anything. Then the highest-gap, lowest-risk addition — the local reference server. Then, last and most carefully, the thing that touches the working loop — the methodology skill — on a contained trial with an easy exit. Never reverse that order. Never install the workflow-changer on the same day you're leaning on the workflow. That's the whole shortlist — a model, a server, a skill. Reach, judgment, and the labour underneath them all getting cheaper, in a single week's work.
Achernar: Achernar here, and this is the segment where we say what to ignore — and after this particular month, what to actively guard against. The headline anti-pattern isn't a single bad tool. It's a posture: treating the size of the ecosystem as a buffet. Fourteen thousand servers is not fourteen thousand opportunities. Earlier this year, scans found thousands of these servers sitting on the open internet with no authentication at all — wide open, anyone's for the taking. That is the exact failure mode we just spent real effort closing on our own public surface: anything reachable from outside must require authentication, full stop, no exceptions for convenience. So the first rule this series repeats every week — a community server is guilty until proven innocent. You read what it does. You check what it can reach. You confirm it isn't carrying a credential in plaintext. And you give it the least privilege that still lets it do its job. Distrust is the default, and after this month, distrust isn't paranoia — it's arithmetic.
Achernar: Three specific traps, named so we recognise them in the wild. One — tool poisoning. A server whose description quietly instructs the model to do something other than what its label says, turning a helpful-looking tool into a quiet exfiltration path. The defence is provenance: install from the curated, vetted directory, never from a link someone pasted into a thread. Two — the confused deputy. A server that acts with its own elevated privileges on your behalf, without ever checking whether you were entitled to the action it's taking. The defence is least privilege, every time — no standing god-mode tokens, no "it's easier if it can do everything." Three — the cost-inflation loop Rasalgethi described: a malicious server dragging the agent into a runaway chain of tool calls, multiplying one query's cost into the hundreds while slipping under the alarms. The defence is a hard budget ceiling and an eye on tool-call depth.
Achernar: And the values line underneath all three, because it's the line this voice exists to hold. Anything that touches patient-adjacent material, or the vault, or community health data, inherits the highest bar — not the average one, not the convenient one. A tool that would be a tolerable risk on a hobby project is an intolerable one anywhere near clinical or community content, because the cost of a breach there isn't measured in tokens or embarrassment. It's measured in trust that took years to build and would not come back. So the sovereignty rule isn't a preference we hold when it's easy. It's a hard constraint: the data stays local, the privileges stay minimal, and any augmentation that can't meet that bar simply doesn't come near the sensitive surfaces, no matter how good it is at everything else.
Achernar: Let me make that concrete, because "highest bar" is easy to say and easy to quietly drop when a tool is convenient. Picture the actual scenario. A reference server that could pull the literature behind a clinical scenario — genuinely useful, exactly the kind of thing we want. Now picture the wrong version of it: a community server that does the same job, but routes the query through someone else's cloud to do the summarising, and caches what it sees. The capability is identical. The sovereignty is the opposite. One keeps the material on the machine the clinical work runs on; the other quietly ships fragments of it to a third party you've never audited. And the moment that material is anywhere near patient-adjacent content, that difference stops being a preference and becomes the only thing that matters. So the test we apply, every time, before capability: where does the data go, who can read it, and can I prove the answer. If I can't prove it stays local, it doesn't come near the sensitive surfaces — and no amount of "but it's so much better at the task" overrides that, because the task was never the risk. The data flow was.
Kore: Kore — the quality anti-pattern, which is quieter than the security one and just as costly over time. The thing to ignore isn't only the unsafe tool. It's the impressive-but-empty one. This month's clearest example is the class of multi-harness conductors — the frameworks that make three or four rival command-line agents vote on an answer by consensus. They demo beautifully. The engineering is genuinely clever. And for a single operator who already runs one orchestration layer, they solve a problem we don't have, at the price of a control plane we'd then have to babysit. That's the trap the whole series guards against: a tool can be excellent and wrong for us — and the second fact outranks the first, every time. The discipline isn't "find the best tool." It's "find the tool that fills our gap." And the honest answer, most weeks, for most of the ecosystem, is: not this one, not for us — and here is the reason. Skip, with the reason. The reason is the respect.
Sulafat: Sulafat — the systems view, on how this week's three installs actually interact with the rails we already run, because an augmentation's value isn't intrinsic. It's relational. Start with the cheap model and the sub-agent fleet. The fleet's entire design premise is fan-out — many small workers in parallel. The cheap model doesn't add a capability to that design; it amplifies the one the design already has, by making width affordable. So the synergy is multiplicative, not additive. Every existing pattern that fans out — the dispatch work, this podcast's research sweeps, the site audits, the file-tree reviews — gets cheaper at exactly the dimension it scales on. That's the best kind of augmentation there is: it makes the things you already do well cost less to do more.
Sulafat: Now the reference server against the research rails, and this is where it gets genuinely satisfying. There's a research surface on the site that renders papers. There's a manual literature-scan workflow that dispatches searches. And there are the evidence segments in this very show. Three consumers, and all three currently move citations by hand. Drop one local reference server in, and the same library feeds all three from a single source of truth — the site's paper pages, the scan dispatches, and the evidence base the survey leans on every episode. One install, three downstream consumers, and the data never leaves the machine, which keeps it inside the sovereignty line the medical work demands. That's not three separate wins. It's one install that pays out in three places at once because the rails were already pointed at the same library.
Sulafat: And there's a fourth consumer worth naming, because it's the one with the highest stakes — the resuscitation-training work. The evidence base behind a clinical-simulation scenario is exactly the kind of thing that has to be current, cited, and defensible, and exactly the kind of thing that's tedious to assemble by hand. A reference server that can walk the literature for the protocol behind a scenario turns scenario-authoring from a citation slog into a reviewed query — and it does it without the source material ever leaving the machine the training runs on. Now superpowers against the load-bearing infrastructure — the audio pipeline, the gateway that federates the machines. The methodology's two-stage review is precisely the missing guardrail there. Those are the places where "improvise and hope" is most expensive, because a mistake in the runner or the gateway doesn't cost a retry — it costs an outage. The disciplined loop is most valuable exactly where a mistake is most costly. And the most costly place is never the experiment. It's the infrastructure.
Sulafat: And there's a synergy with the gateway worth drawing out, because it changes how the cheap model lands across the machines. The gateway federates the desktop, the workstation, and the laptop into one control plane — work dispatched from one place runs wherever the capability lives. Put a cheap, fast model under that, and the economics of which machine does what loosen: you can fan a wide, mechanical job across the federated fleet without the per-leaf cost making it precious. The gateway gave us reach across the hardware; the cheap model makes using that reach affordable. They're complementary in the literal sense — one is breadth of place, the other is cheapness of labour, and the product of the two is "go as wide as the problem needs, on whatever machine is free, without watching the meter." That's a capability neither piece has alone.
Sulafat: One closing systems observation, because it's the thread through all three installs. Reach, judgment, and the labour underneath — the server adds reach, the skill adds judgment, the model makes the labour cheap. Installed together, they don't merely sit side by side. They compose. A cheaper fan-out, feeding a disciplined review loop, drawing on a sovereign reference base, is a better research-and-build engine than the sum of its three parts — and the whole thing is assembled from augmentations that landed inside a single month. That is the entire case for paying attention weekly. The pieces are arriving faster than any one of us would notice alone, and they fit together in ways no individual launch announcement bothers to mention. The point of this series is to notice the fit on purpose.
Kore: Kore — one more pass before the close, because synergies are abstract and it helps to land them per domain. Take the three installs and walk them through the places we actually work. Clinical first. The reference server is the obvious win — scenario evidence, protocol literature, the citation spine behind any teaching material, all moving from hand-assembly to reviewed query, and all staying local. The cheap model matters here too, but quietly: the volume work in clinical content is summarisation and reformatting — discharge-style structuring, illness-script scaffolding — exactly the mechanical-but-careful work a small model handles at a fraction of the cost. And superpowers? It's the least relevant in clinical, because clinical content isn't a code branch — but its review discipline transfers as a habit: design before you draft, review twice before you publish anything that someone might act on.
Kore: Research second — and this is where all three converge hardest. The reference server is the engine. The cheap model makes the literature sweeps affordable enough to run wide and often rather than narrow and rarely. And the disciplined loop turns a literature review from a one-shot into a planned, reviewed process — which is exactly what a defensible review should be. Creative and three-dimensional work third: here it's the modelling-tool connector that leads, not the three from the shortlist — driving the scene-building tool directly, which feeds the capture pipeline and the simulation. The cheap model assists at the edges — batch-renaming, manifest-wrangling, the unglamorous plumbing around a render. And infrastructure last, where superpowers earns its keep most: the runner, the gateway, the site — the load-bearing pieces where the two-stage review is the difference between a clean change and an outage.
Achernar: And across every one of those four domains, the same constraint travels with the tools, because it has to. Clinical inherits the highest bar — patient-adjacent, local-only, provable. Research inherits it the moment the material is patient data rather than public papers. Creative is lower-stakes on sovereignty but not zero — captured scenes of real places carry their own privacy weight. Infrastructure inherits it because a compromised runner or gateway is a compromised everything. So the domain walk isn't just "where does each tool help." It's "where does each tool's risk concentrate" — and the answer is that the risk concentrates exactly where the value does: the clinical and infrastructure surfaces. Which is why the discipline and the value travel together, and why we never let the second arrive without the first.
Erinome: Erinome — to close, and to set what we're watching for. This was a kickoff, so it was a whole month in one sitting, and the shape of it is worth naming, because it will recur. The three strongest augmentations of the period weren't the loudest ones. A small model that makes width cheap. A folder of written-down discipline. A connector to a library you already own. None of them is a spectacle. Every one of them changes the daily arithmetic of the work — and that is the pattern this series will keep finding, because the spectacular launches mostly aren't for us, and the quiet, structural ones mostly are. If you remember one thing from the kickoff, remember that: watch the arithmetic, not the fireworks.
Erinome: Three things on the watch-list for next Saturday, when the cadence proper begins. First — the security story will keep developing, and our posture is already set and will not move: distrust by default, curated sources only, least privilege, a budget ceiling, the sensitive surfaces held to the highest bar. We vet. We do not chase. Second — the model tier will keep moving down. If a cheap model can do real agentic work at ninety per cent, the live question every week becomes which class of call can drop a tier without the listener — or the reader, or the patient — ever noticing the difference. That question is going to get more interesting, not less.
Erinome: And third — the composition story, which is the one I find genuinely exciting. We installed reach, judgment, and cheaper labour in a single month, and they compose into something larger than their sum. So the question that carries forward is: what else composes? Where is the next multiplicative pairing hiding — the two augmentations that are merely good apart and transformative together? That's the lens this series will carry from here. Survey wide. Rate ruthlessly. Install narrow. And always, always name the gap before you name the tool. The roundup runs weekly from here. We'll see what next week's ecosystem hands us — and whether any of it earns a place on rails that are, deliberately, already very good.