Erinome: This is State of Play. I am Erinome, the standing anchor, and tonight is about thirty-five minutes. The question I am bringing to the desk this evening is the question the project lead has been living with for weeks. How do you synchronise state, not just files, not just knowledge, but the running mind of an artificial intelligence assistant, across multiple instances of Claude Desktop running on multiple computers, when each machine sees a different conversation, holds a different memory, and has no first-party way to know what the others have learned in the last ten minutes. The project lead's setup is three machines. An M4 Mac mini at home. An M5 MacBook Air in the bag. An Alienware Dell R12 with a real graphics card and a hundred and twenty-eight gigabytes of memory in the home office. All three machines run Claude Desktop. All three run a federation tool called OpenClaw. All three sit on a private overlay network called Tailscale. The knowledge databases sync fine, because Obsidian Sync handles the vault. The problem is not the files. The problem is the mind. The instance on the M5 does not know what the instance on the M4 did ten minutes ago without a manual handover. And worse, a single instance keeps re-discovering things it has already been told. The M4 keeps forgetting OpenClaw is installed, even after it has been told three times. That is the paired problem we are going to pull apart tonight. State sync across instances on one side. Per-instance memory amnesia on the other. They look the same from a frustrated user's seat. They are not the same. They need different fixes. With me are four voices. One who builds and explains, one who pushes back hard on architecture choices, one who holds the privacy and equity questions, and one who has spent decades watching distributed systems break and is going to tell us where the foot-guns are. Sadaltager, the methods seat is yours. Open the architecture.
Sadaltager: Sadaltager here, in the methods seat. The right way to start is by being precise about what state actually means, because loose usage of the word defeats analysis. There are nine concrete categories. Conversation history, which is the turn-by-turn message log. Derived memory, which is the structured fact store that Claude builds about you over time. Model Context Protocol server configuration, which is the list of external tools each Claude instance has plugged in. Tool-permission grants, which are the explicit yes-and-no decisions a user makes about what tools the agent can call. Approval queue, which is the user-facing list of pending requests. Working files, which are the documents the agent has been editing during the session. Model preferences, which are the temperature and persona settings. Sub-agent state, which matters for anyone running Claude Code with delegated worker agents. And plugin and skill state, which is the inventory of installed extensions. Nine categories. Each has a different sync requirement, and lumping them together is the first mistake.
Sadaltager: Take conversation history first. It is high-frequency append-only data that tolerates eventual consistency. If the M5 sees the M4's morning conversation thirty seconds after the M4 finished it, no harm done. Compare that to tool-permission grants, which are security-critical. If the user grants computer-use permission on the M5, you do not necessarily want that grant replicated to the M4 ten seconds later, because the M4 is sitting on the hospital network and the trust posture is different. Same shape, different consistency requirement. The architecture has to honour the distinction.
Sadaltager: The cleanest insight, the one that organises the rest of the conversation, is that most of what we call Claude state is, mechanically, a filesystem. It is JavaScript Object Notation, Markdown, JSONL, SQLite. The hard parts are which filesystem, what merge semantics, and what is genuinely private to each machine and must not sync. Once you see that, the candidate solutions sort themselves into six categories. File-as-state, which means write the standing facts to Markdown files and let some external sync tool handle them. MCP-as-state, which means push the state into a Model Context Protocol server that all instances point at. Dedicated agent-memory services, like Letta or Mem0 or Supermemory, which model agent memory explicitly. Federated agent frameworks, like LangGraph with shared Postgres checkpointers, or OpenClaw with its gateway pattern. Anthropic-native primitives, which is the Memory Tool and CLAUDE.md and the Agent SDK session resume. And manual handover protocols, which is what most people including the project lead are actually doing today, whether they admit it or not.
Sadaltager: Each category has trade-offs. File-as-state is the cheapest. Set up a wake-up Markdown file in the vault, point CLAUDE.md at it on each machine, accept that Obsidian Sync handles the propagation, and you solve maybe seventy percent of the felt pain in half a day of work. The constraint is that high-churn files break under that approach. If three instances are writing to MEMORY.md every minute, you will hit merge conflicts the diff-match-patch algorithm cannot reconcile. The honest answer is to use Obsidian Sync for low-churn files like CLAUDE.md and AGENTS.md and your rules folder, and use a different transport, like Syncthing over the Tailscale network, for the high-churn parts of the dot-claude directory.
Sadaltager: The richer answer is dedicated agent-memory services. There is one that is particularly well-fitted to the project lead's setup, called Letta. The architecture is a FastAPI server on a port, backed by Postgres with pgvector, that runs in a Docker container. The killer feature is shared memory blocks. Multiple agents can attach to the same memory block, and concurrent writes are safe because the underlying primitive is additive. It is, in effect, an append-only set-shaped data structure, which the distributed-systems literature would call a G-Set. From the user's seat, what that means is the M4 writes a memory, the M5 reads it instantly, and there is no merge step the user has to think about. The project lead's hardware is exactly right for this. The Alienware box has the storage and the always-on posture to be the canonical memory server. The M4 and the M5 are clients over the Tailnet.
Sadaltager: The Anthropic-native primitive that ties it together is called the Memory Tool. It is a tool the agent can call to read and write a memory store, and crucially, the storage is bring-your-own. The application controls where the memory files live. If the project lead wraps Letta's memory API as a Model Context Protocol server, and that server is the Memory Tool the three Claude Desktop instances are pointing at, the entire mind sits on the Alienware box. Each instance is a window into the same memory store. The synchronisation is transparent. The state-sync problem, in its essence, is solved.
Erinome: Charon, the methods seat just described a Letta server on the home box as the answer. You have spent decades watching distributed systems break. Where does this break.
Charon: Charon here, in the scepticism seat. Three places. First place is the network. The thesis depends on the Tailnet staying up. Tailnet uplinks are mostly reliable, but the Mac mini at home, the laptop at a regional hospital, and the workstation in the home office are not always co-located, and Tailnet uses a relay called DERP when direct connections cannot be established. Direct connections work most of the time on a wired or local-wireless link. They fail when one peer is behind a hostile network, like some hospital networks the project lead may actually encounter. The result is not a failure mode you notice immediately. It is latency that creeps up from sub-millisecond to several hundred milliseconds. The agent does not crash. It just gets slow, and the slowness propagates into the user experience as a perceived stutter on every memory call. The right answer is to design the wake-up ritual to be tolerant of slow memory calls. Pre-cache the standing facts locally on each machine. Treat the remote memory store as the canonical version, but never make the user wait for it on the first turn.
Charon: Second place is the single point of failure. Putting the canonical memory store on the Alienware box makes that machine the heart of the architecture. If the home power drops, if the box reboots, if the Docker daemon hangs, every other instance loses its memory backbone. The discipline that matters here is operational. The Alienware box needs to be on a battery. The Postgres data directory needs nightly snapshots to a second disk. The Letta container needs a health check and an automatic restart policy. None of this is exotic, but all of it has to be set up, and none of it is set up by default when you docker-compose up. The graceful-degradation answer, the one that actually keeps the user productive when the home box is down, is that each Claude Desktop instance has a local-only fallback memory file that gets written to when the remote store is unreachable. When the home box comes back, the deltas reconcile. That is more code than zero, and it is the right amount of code.
Charon: Third place is the security and trust boundary, which is the part the project lead's patent-novelty stance demands we name. The thesis is that nothing leaves the Tailnet, which keeps the architecture defensible against the patent-novelty concern. That works only if the inference calls themselves stay inside an acceptable boundary, and inference calls to Anthropic's hosted Claude do not. The prompts leave the network. The system prompt that contains the wake-up ritual leaves the network. If any of those contain protected clinical information, the boundary has been crossed. The clean separation is this. State architecture stays tailnet-only. Inference stays cloud-bound for non-clinical conversational work. For protected clinical material, the project lead needs a local model on the Alienware box for the inference step too, and the rest of the architecture stays the same. The state-sync problem and the data-sovereignty problem are entangled but separable, and conflating them is the cleanest way to ship the wrong architecture.
Erinome: Sadaltager, the rebuttal on the foot-guns Charon just named.
Sadaltager: All three foot-guns are real, all three have known mitigations, and the operational discipline Charon is calling for is exactly the kind of discipline the project lead's other infrastructure already shows. The State of Play runner is on a launchd schedule with health checks and an automatic restart hook. The vault sync is monitored. The credential store is in a known canonical location. The same discipline transferred to the Letta server is not a stretch. It is a half-day of operations work and a few lines of Docker Compose. The local-only fallback memory is the more interesting design question, because it forces the architecture to be honest about what is replicated when the network is degraded. A reasonable first answer is that the local fallback is read-only. The user can read what was last cached. Writes either queue locally and reconcile when the network returns, or the user accepts that some writes are lost when the network is down. The reconcile path is bounded. It is not unsolvable.
Erinome: That is the multi-instance sync question on the table. The amnesia sub-problem is the second act and it deserves the same treatment. Kore, take the seat. Why does a single instance of Claude on a single machine keep re-discovering things it has already been told.
Kore: Kore here. The first thing to be clear about is that amnesia is not a memory-storage problem. It is a memory-retrieval problem. The facts are usually stored fine. The project lead has a beautifully maintained CLAUDE.md, a Memory file in the vault, an OpenClaw configuration that has been there for weeks. The problem is that the agent does not pull these into context at the moment they would matter. By the time the user thinks to surface the file, three turns have been wasted and the user is irritated. So the architectural question is not where to store the facts. It is how to make sure the agent retrieves them.
Kore: The community vocabulary for the fix is the wake-up ritual. The pattern is simple. At the first turn of every new session, the agent reads or fetches a small bundle of standing facts before anything else happens. The implementation varies. The simplest version is a Markdown file at a known path, referenced from CLAUDE.md, that the agent is instructed to read as its first action. The richer version uses the Memory Tool, configured to look for a boot file. The richest version uses a sub-agent that orients the parent agent and returns a précis. All three are valid. The design constraint that ties them together is token economy.
Kore: A two-hundred-line CLAUDE.md is roughly one thousand five hundred tokens at the front of every conversation. On the API that is real money. Inside Claude Desktop with a flat subscription it is real context window that cannot be used for the task. So the wake-up ritual has to be right-sized. Fifty tokens of identity, two hundred tokens of in-flight projects, three hundred tokens of standing rules, and a pointer to where the long stuff lives, retrievable on demand. The bias has to be toward less standing context and more retrieval mid-session. The agent that knows it can ask the memory tool for the OpenClaw configuration when it needs it is more useful than the agent that wastes a thousand tokens carrying the configuration around just in case.
Kore: The anti-pattern the project lead has been falling into is the perfectly maintained memory file that no agent ever reads. The MEMORY.md file is in a folder no agent is aware of. The CLAUDE.md is on the M5 but the M4 has a different one. The wake-up Markdown file is in the vault, but no instance is instructed to load it at session start. The fix is mechanical, not philosophical. Surface the file to the agent's context window. Do not assume it is there. The agent does not have ambient awareness of the filesystem. It has the context window it was started with. Standing facts have to be either in that context window from turn zero, or behind a tool the agent has a strong incentive to call.
Kore: The reason this matters as a paired problem with the sync question is that solving sync without solving amnesia leaves you with three perfectly synchronised but equally amnesic Adas. They share the same blind spots. They forget the same things at the same time. Solving amnesia without solving sync gives you one bright agent on the M4 and a confused agent on the M5. Either failure mode is worse than what you have now, which is at least an honest cognitive load that you know you carry. The pair of problems has to be solved together, with a single coherent answer.
Erinome: Vindemiatrix, the trust and equity seat. There are two threads that need to land here. The Indigenous data sovereignty question, and the rural-first question. Walk both.
Vindemiatrix: Vindemiatrix here. The first thread is the easy one to state and the harder one to enforce. The architecture the methods seat described keeps every byte of the project lead's data on hardware the project lead owns. Letta is open source, Postgres is open source, the vector store is open source. The Tailnet is private. The project lead has the keys. None of the Aboriginal-and-Torres-Strait-Islander health data the project lead encounters in clinical work crosses into the memory store unless the project lead chooses to put it there, and the project lead's standing rule is that protected clinical information does not enter the Anthropic-hosted inference path. The state-sync architecture and the data-sovereignty constraint are aligned. The patent-novelty constraint and the data-sovereignty constraint are aligned. That is not by accident. The same operational principle, which is keep the data on hardware you control, satisfies both.
Vindemiatrix: The harder thread is the rural-first one. The Tailnet itself is a rural-resilience primitive. If the Port Pirie clinic loses internet but the M4 and the M5 can still reach each other over Tailscale, and the home box on the Tailnet has a working exit node, the local agent infrastructure continues to function. The memory is still readable. The cross-instance coherence still holds. The only thing the architecture loses when the wide-area network drops is the inference call to Anthropic, which is the unavoidable cost of using a hosted model. Everything else stays running. Compare that to the architecture some readers may be tempted to build, which is iCloud Sync as the transport. iCloud collapses the moment the wide-area network drops. The local cache is patchy. Conflict resolution is silent overwrite. The user is left without a fall-back. The rural reading is that any architecture which assumes a high-quality WAN link is fragile in the actual context where the project lead works. The architecture that keeps the canonical memory store on a tailnet-accessible local machine is the architecture that degrades gracefully when the network does what regional networks do.
Vindemiatrix: The second-order rural thread is the operational discipline question. The project lead does not have a team to maintain this infrastructure. The architecture has to be one person can run it. Letta in Docker Compose, Postgres on a volume, restic to an external drive nightly, a health check that emails the project lead if the container falls over. That is the maintenance envelope. If the architecture grows beyond what one person can hold in their head, the rural-resilience argument fails for the same reason every solo-operator clinical workflow fails when it scales past one person. So the design discipline is to stop adding components at the point where the operational story is still tractable. Letta plus a thin MCP wrapper plus a wake-up ritual is tractable. Letta plus Mem0 plus Supermemory plus DBOS plus Yjs plus an OpenClaw gateway plus a Raft cluster is not. The architecture has to know when to stop.
Erinome: Charon, the comparison matrix in one breath. What did the paper actually score, and where does the project lead's setup land.
Charon: The paper scored thirteen candidate architectures across sync granularity, latency, conflict resolution, fit to a tailnet-only constraint, monthly cost, setup complexity, and observability. The matrix has a clear winner cluster for the project lead's situation. File-as-state with Syncthing over Tailscale is the right tier-A immediate win. Cost zero, effort one evening, fits the tailnet, solves seventy percent of the felt pain. Letta plus Qdrant on the home box with a custom MCP wrapper is the right tier-B fix over a fortnight. Cost zero, effort a fortnight of evenings, fits the tailnet, solves ninety-five percent of the pain. OpenClaw Gateway plus durable-execution checkpointing plus a conflict-free replicated data type document is the tier-C architectural answer over a quarter, and it is the version that has patent novelty in it. The trap to avoid is the no-effort option, which is paying for Anthropic's hosted Memory feature at the consumer subscription tier. That option gives you account-level memory synthesis but not transparent cross-device sync, sends every conversation to Anthropic, and is opt-in for model training by default on consumer plans. The patent stance disqualifies it. The rural stance disqualifies it. The cost stance does not even need to weigh in.
Erinome: Sadaltager, the implementation plan for our projects in the household. Tier A, the cheap immediate win. Walk it cleanly.
Sadaltager: Tier A is five steps. Step one. Author a Markdown file at the path tilde slash Ross slash Vault slash A I slash Ada slash memory dash wake dash up dot m d. Three hundred to five hundred tokens of standing facts. Identity. Who Jacob is. Who Jo is. Where the vault lives. What OpenClaw is. Where the credential store is. What projects are in flight. What the heartbeat-file convention is. Effort thirty minutes. The vault already syncs through Obsidian Sync. The file is immediately available on all three machines.
Sadaltager: Step two. Prepend to each machine's project CLAUDE.md the single instruction that at session start, the agent reads the wake-up Markdown file and treats its contents as standing facts. That instruction has to be in every CLAUDE.md the agent might find. Effort fifteen minutes per machine, forty-five minutes total. The amnesia mitigation is immediate from the next session forward.
Sadaltager: Step three. Stand up Syncthing over Tailscale between the three machines for the dot-claude directory, excluding the sessions subdirectory and the cache subdirectory, which stay machine-local. Effort one evening. This catches CLAUDE.md, plugins, skills, commands, the agents directory, and settings dot j s o n. Conflict files are visible and recoverable, which is the right failure mode.
Sadaltager: Step four. Establish that the end-of-session handover convention writes to the pending-dispatch-relay Markdown file in the vault. That file is already in use. Sessions can read the tail to catch up on what other instances have done. The file is the cheapest possible cross-instance status board.
Sadaltager: Step five. Lock in the convention that all three instances heartbeat to the same dispatch-relay file. That convention is already in force in the heartbeats this episode's drafting agents are emitting. Make it standing policy across every long-running session.
Sadaltager: Total effort half a day. Total cost zero Australian dollars. Solves about seventy percent of the felt pain. That is tier A.
Erinome: Kore, the tier B walk. The proper medium-effort fix.
Kore: Tier B is six steps over a fortnight. Step one. Install the Letta server on the Alienware box. Docker Compose, the Postgres pg-vector container, the Letta server container, an nginx container for transport-layer security termination. Bind to the Tailscale network interface. Admin authentication via a key. Postgres volume backed up nightly through restic to an external drive on the same box. Effort an evening. The infrastructure is mature, the install path is well documented, and the project lead's other Docker workflows already have the discipline to maintain it.
Kore: Step two. Add Qdrant on the same box for vector storage. Same pattern. Bind to the Tailscale interface, admin application programming interface key authentication, persistent volume, nightly snapshot. Effort an evening.
Kore: Step three. Author a minimal Model Context Protocol server in Python, roughly two hundred lines, that wraps Letta's representational state transfer application programming interface and exposes memory get, memory set, memory search, and memory list as M C P tools. Run it on the Alienware box. Point the three Claude Desktop instances at it via their respective configuration files. Effort one to two evenings. The two-hundred-line ceiling is realistic if the wrapper is thin, and the project lead's existing Python ecosystem is more than adequate.
Kore: Step four. The wake-up ritual transforms. Instead of reading a Markdown file from the vault, the first instruction in CLAUDE.md is to call the memory get tool with the wake-up key. The tool returns the standing facts from Letta. Same content, but now writable from any instance and immediately visible to the others. Effort thirty minutes per machine.
Kore: Step five. Replace the wake-up Markdown file with a Letta-stored memory block of the same content. The vault file becomes a backup. The Letta block is the canonical version. The two should be kept in rough sync by a small sync script that runs nightly. Effort an evening for the script, ongoing zero.
Kore: Step six. Optionally add Supermemory self-hosted on the same box. Supermemory ships an OpenClaw auto-recall plugin which gives the project lead the implicit "Ada noticed that and remembered it" behaviour without having to ask. The plugin captures observations during sessions and surfaces them at retrieval time. Effort a weekend. Optional but recommended.
Kore: Total effort a fortnight of evenings. Total cost zero Australian dollars, plus marginal language-model token spend for the memory extraction. Solves about ninety-five percent of the felt pain. Maintains strict tailnet-only data flow. That is tier B.
Erinome: Vindemiatrix, the tier C architectural answer. The patent-novelty version.
Vindemiatrix: Tier C is five steps over a quarter. Step one. Stand up an OpenClaw Gateway on the Alienware box. The gateway is the canonical control plane. All three Claude Desktop instances either route through it via the OpenClaw browser plugin, or coexist with it for ambient use. The gateway natively integrates the Tailscale Serve transport, so the publication path is simple. The gateway pattern is the closest existing precedent to a centralised artificial intelligence runtime over a tailnet, and citing it in any patent disclosure is essential because it is prior art the project lead has to acknowledge cleanly.
Vindemiatrix: Step two. Add DBOS on the existing Letta Postgres for cross-instance workflow checkpointing. DBOS provides exactly-once semantics on tool calls even across host failures, which is the property that makes recovery from a network drop boring rather than terrifying. The library-style architecture means no separate cluster to maintain, just a few extra Python imports.
Vindemiatrix: Step three. Stand up a Yjs y-websocket server on the Alienware box for true concurrent-write shared scratchpad. One Yjs document per active project, every instance reading and writing the same document. This is the primitive that enables genuine concurrent collaboration. The M4 and the M5 working on the same document at the same time, both with the assistant's help, no copy-and-paste. The conflict-free replicated data type semantics make the merges trivial. The CodeCRDT paper from October 2025 has the architecture pattern and the evaluation data the project lead can lean on.
Vindemiatrix: Step four. Introduce a custom conflict-free replicated data type aware merge driver for the CLAUDE.md and MEMORY.md files at the tilde slash dot claude path. There is a community project called claude-memsync that has done this work, and the merge driver understands the markdown section structure. Combine with Syncthing for the rest of the directory. The result is that the auto-memory written by one instance does not silently overwrite the auto-memory written by another. The unions are correct.
Vindemiatrix: Step five. The patent disclosure draft. Multi-instance Claude Desktop architecture over a tailnet, citing OpenClaw, Letta, Supermemory, Tailscale Serve, and the upcoming stateless Model Context Protocol specification as prior art. The novel contribution is the specific composition and the wake-up ritual implemented as a Model Context Protocol tool call. The disclosure lodges with a patent attorney before the architecture is publicly disseminated beyond the vault. Whether the project lead pursues the patent or files it defensively is a separate decision, but the documentation has to exist before the public posts and the conference talks start, or the novelty argument is permanently weaker.
Vindemiatrix: Total effort a quarter. Total cost zero Australian dollars, all open source. Solves one hundred percent of the sync problem. Establishes a defensible architectural narrative for the patent application if the project lead chooses to pursue it. That is tier C.
Erinome: The cross-topic synergies are where the episode's real argument lands. Walk them, in order. Charon, the first one.
Charon: The first synergy is between the state-sync solution and the amnesia solution. They are the same solution. The Letta server with the Memory Tool wrapper solves both. The wake-up ritual is the amnesia mitigation. The shared memory block is the state-sync primitive. A single architectural decision answers both problems, and the operational story is one server to maintain rather than two. That is the structural argument for tier B. It is not "use this one for sync and a different one for amnesia." It is "the same fix works on both axes."
Sadaltager: The second synergy is between the rural-resilience constraint and the patent-novelty constraint. They both point at the same architecture. Keep the data on hardware you own. Keep the inference call to a hosted model for non-clinical work and to a local model for clinical work. Use the Tailscale network as the transport because it is mTLS-equivalent, identity-aware, and degradation-tolerant. Every design choice that satisfies the rural-resilience constraint also satisfies the patent-novelty constraint. The project lead does not have to trade off. There is one architecture that is correct on both axes, and the paper names it.
Kore: The third synergy is between the operational discipline question and the maintenance envelope question. The architecture has to be one person can run it. That constraint disqualifies the heaviest of the tier-C components. It does not disqualify the tier-A solution, which is half a day's work. It does not disqualify the tier-B solution, which is a fortnight of evenings and a maintenance envelope of restart-when-the-Docker-daemon-hiccups. It disqualifies adding all of OpenClaw plus DBOS plus Yjs plus a Raft cluster plus four different memory backends plus a separate observability stack. Knowing where the maintenance envelope ends is the design judgement that protects the project lead's time. Tier B is the right ceiling for the next quarter. Tier C is the architectural story to draft and not to ship.
Vindemiatrix: The fourth synergy is the equity and access one, and it cuts across every other thread. The Tailnet is a small private network with three machines on it. The project lead is one operator. The architecture has nothing to say about a second human user, about colleagues at the regional health service, about residents who might want to share an assistant. It would be a mistake to design as if the user count were going to scale to a department. It would also be a mistake to design as if it were permanently going to stay at one. The middle path is to design for one operator with the awareness that the multi-tenant version is a future-work item. The Letta architecture supports it. The OpenClaw architecture supports it. The wake-up ritual generalises to a per-user wake-up. The shared memory block generalises to per-user memory blocks. The architecture does not need to be built for multi-tenancy now, but every decision should leave the door open to it. That is the version of the equity reading that lands without bloating the immediate build.
Erinome: The open research questions, briefly. Sadaltager.
Sadaltager: Five questions are genuinely open. The first is the conflict-free replicated data type semantics for natural-language memory. The existing data types are good for structured fields and rich text. They are not good for "Claude noticed X and stored it as a memory, and now Claude on a different host noticed not-X." Reconciling that semantically is unsolved. The second is the federated session-checkpoint coherence question. If three Claude Desktop instances all hold local conversation files and they need to interleave coherently, what is the right protocol. No principled answer in the literature. The third is approval-queue replication. The user grants computer-use permission on the M5. Should the M4 see it. The right answer depends on whether the grant is user-level or instance-level, and the distinction is under-specified. The fourth is wake-up ritual telemetry. How do we measure whether the ritual is working. The user's felt sense is the de-facto metric. Formalising it is open. The fifth is the local-model federation question. If the Alienware box runs a local model rather than calling out to Anthropic, the federation question changes, because now the model lives on a specific machine and the architecture has to know where the inference is happening. That is the natural evolution of the architecture and it deserves a separate paper.
Erinome: The implementation for the project lead, named cleanly. This week. Tier A. Tonight, the wake-up Markdown file in the vault. Tomorrow morning, the prepended CLAUDE.md instruction on all three machines. Tomorrow evening, the Syncthing share between the three machines for the dot-claude directory. The dispatch-relay heartbeat convention stays in force as it already is. Within forty-eight hours, seventy percent of the felt pain is gone. Next fortnight. Tier B. Letta on the Alienware box, with a thin MCP wrapper, with the wake-up ritual rewritten as a memory get call, with Supermemory optionally added on top. Ninety-five percent of the felt pain gone. Patent stance preserved. Indigenous data sovereignty stance preserved. Rural resilience preserved. Next quarter. Tier C, drafted as a patent disclosure, shipped at whatever pace the project lead's other obligations allow. The architecture exists on paper before it exists on hardware. The disclosure is the thing that makes the public conversation possible. That is the work. The paired problem has a paired answer. The mind moves between the machines because the memory does. The single instance stops re-forgetting because the wake-up ritual carries the standing facts into context every time. The vault holds the long-form knowledge. The Letta server holds the working memory. The three Claude Desktop windows are three windows into the same brain. I am Erinome. Thank you for listening to State of Play.