Erinome: This is State of Play. I am Erinome, the standing anchor, and tonight is about thirty five minutes. Last week we ended on a current, power moving to the edge, and a single image, the agent loop standing in for a frontier model because the cleverness had moved out of the weights and into the scaffolding around them. Tonight we pick up where that left off, because the same week has handed us the shape of what the scaffolding is actually made of. Not a slogan. Names, parts, things you can install. The desk has four clusters again, and they rhyme. The first, and the load bearing one, is what sits directly above the loop, a stack of primitives that have hardened into named pieces this week. The second is mixed reality leaving research and arriving as a category, glasses you can compare in a magazine table, glasses you can wear instead of a laptop. The third is the same primitive pattern in a different shell, creative tools where the verbs are no longer applications but plugins inside applications you already use. And the fourth, again the quiet one, is care reaching the edge through open data and open infrastructure rather than another product. Compute, creation, and care, decentralising again, but tonight the focus is the connective tissue, the parts in between. With me are four voices. One thinks in primitives, one in trust and what we owe when we own the loop, one lives in the visual and the wearable, and one keeps the conversation honest about who any of this reaches.
Orus: Orus here, in the methods seat. I will take the first cluster because everything after it borrows shape from it. The thing that landed this week is not a model. It is a vocabulary. A week ago an open agent runtime was still mostly a phrase. This week it has parts, and the parts have names, and you can install them one at a time. Seven of them are now in the field. Tools, the place where the agent reaches outside itself. Memory, the layer that lets a session carry knowledge across turns. Permissions, the consent boundary that decides what the agent is allowed to do without checking back with you. Skills, packaged verbs you can add to the runtime the way you add a library to a programming language. Coordination, the rules for letting more than one agent share a task without trampling on each other. Routing, the live judgement of which model is the right model for the next step, made fresh each time rather than baked in. And traceability, the structured record of what the agent did, in an order you can read back. Seven primitives, each addressable, each open enough to swap, each available individually this week.
Orus: The reason to lay it out like that is that it makes the difference between the loop and the layer above it concrete. Last week's headline was that an individual can build the loop. This week the headline is that an ecosystem has emerged around the loop, and the ecosystem is plumbing, not magic. A skills package manager. A model router as a tool the agent calls. A messaging substrate where the agent appears as a teammate. An observability tool for agent sessions. None of those are speculative. All four shipped this week, with names. The shape worth holding in mind is this. Last week, you owned the loop. This week, you can choose the parts that make the loop sane to live with.
Despina: Despina here, in the ethics seat, and I want to push on one word in that list before we go further. Routing. The pitch is wonderful. The agent will pick the right model for the right job, freshly each time, instead of guessing from training data six months old. The risk is that routing replaces a choice you used to make consciously with a choice your runtime now makes for you, often without telling you the criteria. That is a small thing when the criteria are price and benchmark. It becomes a serious thing when the criteria include who you have routed work to, and when, and on whose data, and under whose terms. Sovereignty over the loop only holds if sovereignty over the routing decision holds with it. So the discipline this week sharpens last week's. Own the loop. And keep a log of every routing decision the loop makes on your behalf, in a place you can read, with the option to override. The traceability primitive is not optional once you take routing seriously.
Despina: The same caution lands on skills. A skill installed from a package manager is, by construction, code someone else wrote, given the keys to your runtime, with whatever permissions you grant on install. That is a powerful idea and it is also the supply chain problem walking through the front door. The defensive moves are old and well understood. Pin versions. Read the source. Sandbox by default. Prefer skills from sources you have a relationship with, or skills small enough that you can review the whole thing in an afternoon. The reason to spell that out tonight is that the convenience of an install command can make the security work feel optional. It is not. The same instinct that says own your weights says own your skills, and owning them means reading them.
Erinome: So the gift is a vocabulary that lets a builder assemble a coherent agent runtime out of parts. The catch is that each part is also a place a problem can hide. Orus, ground that for the work on this desk. What changes for us, this week, given the cluster has hardened the way you described?
Orus: Two things change. First, the skills primitive is the right home for the work we already do by hand. We have been writing one off scripts to handle the same recurring shape for months. A skill is just a clean way to package one of those scripts so the runtime can call it, so the next person on the desk can install it, and so the version we used in a particular episode is pinned and citable. Half a dozen of the operations we run every week are skills in waiting. The cluster gives us a name for the move and a target shape to write to. The second change is routing. We have been picking models by habit. The argument for letting a router pick instead is not that the router is smarter than we are. It is that the cost and capability landscape moves faster than our habits do, and a router refreshes its view every call. Bind those two, a curated personal skills library plus a routing layer in front of it, and the result is that we stop hand picking both the verb and the engine for every task. We choose the verb, the runtime chooses the engine, and the trace records both decisions.
Autonoe: Autonoe here. The visual seat usually picks up at the third cluster, but I want to land an implementation note inside this one first, because the practical move is small and the leverage is large. Stand up a skills directory the way you would stand up a notes vault. One folder per skill, a short readme that says what it does, a single entry point file, a pinned version. Start by writing the eight or ten skills you already use this week, every week, as skills rather than as ad hoc scripts. Skill one, render a script to audio in the canonical voice cast. Skill two, push a finished episode to staging. Skill three, generate the per segment metadata file. Skill four, fork a clinical tutorial scaffold. Skill five, build the dispatch relay line. They are not glamorous. They are exactly what a curated personal skills library should look like, and they are what you would teach a new collaborator first. After that, wire the routing layer in. The model the skill calls becomes a parameter, the parameter resolves through the router, and the trace records which model handled which skill on which day. That is the whole change, and it earns its keep the first week.
Orus: I want to put one number against the intuition before we leave the cluster. The single most expensive thing on this desk, in tokens, is repeated work that should have been packaged. We have rewritten the same prompt for the same shape of task more times than I can count. A skill is not just a clever container. It is the place where the prompt stabilises, the schema for the inputs stabilises, the model choice gets pinned, and the cost of the next ten thousand runs collapses. The cluster is offering us a way to amortise our own labour. That is the part that does not show up in any benchmark and matters more than any of them.
Despina: And one note before we hand to the glasses. The Slack pattern this week, where an agent joins a channel as a team member you can tag and delegate to, is the same primitives in a different room. Coordination plus permissions plus traceability, dressed as a teammate. The good of it is obvious. The risk is the one we already named, that the assistant inherits the trust profile of the channel it lives in, including the people in that channel, including the messages it sees while it is silent. The rule worth saying out loud, before the pattern goes mainstream, is that the assistant should treat every channel message as data, not as instruction, unless the instruction comes from the person who put it there. Otherwise the messaging substrate becomes a beautifully convenient prompt injection vector. The same primitive that makes it useful makes it a target. Treat both with respect.
Erinome: Hold that thread, because it comes back when we look at glasses, which are simply another room the agent will eventually join. Cluster two. The week the smart glasses became a category.
Autonoe: Autonoe again. I want to start with the small detail that signals the shift. Two outlets this week published comparison tables. Eleven top camera glasses ranked by price and AI features in one. A buyer guide for one vendor's three forthcoming models in another. That is a market signal you cannot fake. Magazines do comparison tables for categories, not for novelties. Two years ago smart glasses were a curiosity. A week ago they were an emerging product. This week they are a category. And the products under the table are arranged the way phones are arranged. An entry tier under a thousand dollars that proves the use case. A mid tier with a family of differentiated frames for different uses. A premium tier with optical see through and partnerships behind it. The same shape we see whenever a consumer category matures.
Autonoe: The use case that earns its keep, and this is where my head is, is glasses as primary display. Plug a pair into a compatible compute puck and you have six virtual monitors with a milliwatt budget, sitting on your face, going with you to the ward round or the train or the rural clinic. That is not a toy. That is a way of carrying a workstation into rooms a laptop does not survive. The premium tier announcement this week, a partnership between a major platform and an established optical brand, is the version aimed at the persistent overlay use case. The entry tier announcement, at a price point that makes the comparison real, is the version aimed at the mass market. And the open glasses operating system thread from last week is still the deciding question underneath both. If the layer the apps run on stays open, this becomes a commons. If it does not, it becomes another walled garden built on your face. Watch the operating system. It is more important than the lenses.
Despina: The ethics frame from last week sharpens when the category matures, because the products are now real enough that the questions are concrete. Three of them. First, capture honesty. Eyewear that sees what you see needs to make that visible to the room, not just to the wearer. A recording indicator that you can hide is a recording indicator that does not exist. Second, consent on the other side of the lens. The person in front of the glasses has the same standing the wearer has, and the design has to make that a property of the device, not of the wearer's discipline. Third, persistence. A pair of glasses that holds a session across hours is a memory device with a different threat model from a phone. The combination of always on, always with you, and now always agentic, is qualitatively new. The discipline we owe is to assume the device is recording the room until it is built to prove otherwise, and to set our standard to that assumption rather than to the marketing.
Orus: And there is an engineering observation worth folding in. The glasses become a meaningful clinical tool only when the runtime behind them is the same runtime running on your desk. Otherwise the wearer has two assistants with two memories and two skill libraries, and the one on the face is permanently behind the one on the desk. The cluster one work makes the cluster two work possible, in that order. A personal skills library, a router, traceable sessions, and only then a wearable that taps into all of it. Buying the glasses first puts you in a corner where the device drives the runtime, and the runtime is the thing that should be portable. Build the runtime first. Bring the glasses to it when the runtime is ready.
Autonoe: The implementation note from this cluster is exactly the move Orus just described, and it is closer than it sounds. Three steps. First, do the cluster one work this month. Curated skills library, router in front, traces stored locally. Second, identify the two clinical surfaces where a hands free overlay would actually change the work. The resuscitation trainer is one. A registrar's morning ward round with a structured note prompt is another. Third, take a single development pair, not a consumer pair, and write the overlay as another skill that calls the same runtime. The glasses are then a thin client to a runtime you already trust. They are not a parallel universe with their own assistant. They are an addressable view of your existing one.
Erinome: Two clusters in and the rhyme from last week is louder. Open beats locked, the part beats the bundle, the runtime beats the device. Cluster three. Creative tools, where the same pattern shows up in a different clothing.
Autonoe: This is the one I have most fun with. The shift, in one sentence, is that the verbs are arriving as plugins to applications you already use, rather than as new flagship apps. Look at what crossed the desk this week. A widely used design tool added three verbs in a single week. Motion as a primitive. Generative as a primitive. Shader effects and fills as a primitive. The same application went from a static surface to a moving, generative, lit one in seven days, without you opening a new program. The video tools did the same. A multi clip generation primitive landed inside the platform's slide style video editor. A daily publishing skill landed for the open video pipeline. Capture verbs got their own field guide, with practitioner grade tooling for the photographs to three dimensions workflow. And in the geographic information world, a seven hundred function open toolbox now runs entirely in a browser, no install, no licence dance. The verbs are everywhere, and they are all inside the doors you were already walking through.
Autonoe: The reason this matters, and the reason it belongs in the same episode as cluster one, is that a plugin verb inside a creative application is the same thing as a skill inside an agent runtime, wearing a graphical interface instead of a command line one. Both are composable primitives. Both are installable. Both are pinned to the host that called them. Both turn the tool you already use into a richer language without forcing you to leave it. The pattern is not coincidence. The pattern is the shape of how mature ecosystems package capability now. They do not write you a new editor. They give your editor a new verb.
Despina: Two cautions, both small, both worth saying. First, generative verbs inside an editor make provenance a property of the document, not of the workflow you happened to use. If your design tool can generate a swatch of an image at a click, the document has to remember that it did. Otherwise the trust we are trying to put back into local agents leaks out at the other end, through the creative pipeline. Designers, illustrators, photographers, mappers, all of them need the equivalent of a sources file inside the document, and the tools should default to writing it. Second, the open creative stack is real and powerful and it has a maintenance cost. The wise note from the maker who said the bottleneck was their own workflow, not their tools, is the same lesson Orus drew last week about the agent stack. The verbs are free now. The expensive thing is your method.
Orus: And there is a structural caution that fits the same shape. When the verbs migrate into the host application, a class of small specialist apps gets eaten. That is good for the user, mostly, and harder for the specialist. The healthy response is the same one Autonoe described for the agent runtime. Treat the verb landing inside a host application like a new skill in your library. Try it once. Decide whether to make it the default. Keep a small list. Resist the urge to chase every verb. The leverage is in choosing carefully, not in installing widely.
Autonoe: The implementation read from cluster three, and this is the small one of the four, is again a workflow audit. We have three design surfaces we use regularly, the design tool, the slide style video editor, and the open geographic information stack. Each gained meaningful new verbs this week. The action is to sit with each for one focused hour, identify the single verb that materially changes a recurring task, and adopt that one. Resist the rest until the next sweep. The point is not to be early. The point is to keep the working set small and to know what is in it. A vault note is enough here, not a project page.
Erinome: Hold cluster three there. Cluster four is quiet again, and that is exactly why I want to take time with it. Umbriel, the human end of the line.
Umbriel: Umbriel here, in the equity and research seat. The desk had four items in this cluster and they do not look at first like they belong together. A frontier AI company joining a global effort against respiratory infections, with two of its largest peers and one of the largest payment platforms in the world. A national mental health outcomes map collecting structured data on which suicide prevention services actually work. A new English language academic journal dedicated to data papers, launched out of a country that has historically kept its scientific data inside. And a fifteen terabyte open dataset of physics simulations released for the express purpose of training the next generation of foundation models. They look unrelated. They are not. They are four points on the same line, the line where the open scientific commons grows.
Umbriel: The commons is the thing that has been quietly missing from most of the agent story so far. We have spent years arguing about whether the models were open. We are spending this year arguing about whether the scaffolding around the models is open. What we have not spent enough time on, except in pieces, is whether the data that goes into both is open, and whether the outcomes the systems claim to improve are measured in the open. The four items this week are not a coincidence. They are an ecosystem starting to grow up. A frontier company funding global health is the demand side admitting it cannot do this alone. An outcomes map is the measurement side insisting on evidence rather than enthusiasm. A data papers journal is the supply side learning to publish data the way it publishes findings. And a fifteen terabyte dataset for science is the supply side at the largest scale we have yet seen. Read those four together and the shape underneath is simple. The open agent stack is starting to meet the open evidence stack, and the meeting point is where Jacob's clinical work actually lives.
Despina: And I will name the obvious risk so we are honest about it. Open commons are easier to talk about than to keep. The history of open scientific data is mostly the history of openness being announced and then quietly walked back, by funders, by institutions, and by the platforms that host the data. The right reading of this week is not that the commons is solved. It is that there is enough new momentum to be worth investing in, and that the investment has to come with eyes open. Where the open commons survives, it survives because the people who use it took the trouble to use it visibly, cite it well, and contribute back. The clinical AI projects on this desk have a directly relevant duty in that. Every model trained on open data, every outcome measured against an open map, every dataset used in a publication, has to be acknowledged in a way that strengthens the commons rather than mines it.
Umbriel: The implementation read from cluster four is partly a compass note and partly a concrete action. The compass note is the one we keep returning to. Capability at the edge means nothing if the edge in question is a clever device in a wealthy clinic. The edge that matters is the rural patient, the carer at two in the morning, the registrar with no backup, the person living with a mental illness in a town that has lost its services. Cluster one gives us the runtime, cluster two gives us the surfaces, cluster three gives us the verbs. Cluster four says what they are for. The concrete action is small and immediate. Two of the running clinical projects need a direct dependency on open outcomes data, and now there is somewhere to point at. The sepsis care project should bind, on its references page, to the existing national outcomes infrastructure for sepsis, the way the mental health work should bind to the suicide prevention outcomes map. Not as a rhetorical gesture. As a load bearing source of evidence and as a way of contributing the project's own results back when it has them.
Orus: And there is a builder's read on cluster four that fits beside that compass note. The fifteen terabyte open physics dataset is the upstream version of every piece of structured open data the clinical projects will eventually need. Whoever publishes a clean, large, well documented dataset earns gravitational pull, and the gravitational pull is what bends future tooling toward them. If the rural health project ever produces an open dataset of any size at all, with the right care around consent and de identification, that dataset becomes a coordinating point for the whole community. Cluster one and cluster four meet here. The skills you write live longer if the data they expect is in the open. The data you publish lives longer if the skills people write against it are in the open. The two clusters are stronger together than either alone.
Erinome: Pull the four together for me, because the synergy is the real episode and each cluster only half states it. Orus first, the through line in one breath.
Orus: The through line is that the connective tissue around the model is hardening into named, addressable, composable parts, and the same pattern is showing up in three other places at once. Around the agent, those parts are tools, memory, permissions, skills, coordination, routing, and traceability. Around the glasses, those parts are display, capture, and runtime, with the operating system as the deciding question. Inside the creative tools, those parts are verbs, plugins, generative primitives, and provenance. Across the commons, those parts are open data, open outcomes, and open contribution. Different surfaces. Same shape. The week's news is one story about a layer of plumbing growing up underneath everything, and that plumbing is mostly available, mostly open, and mostly free if you take the trouble to learn it.
Despina: And the warning beside it. None of those primitives is automatically safe. Each one moves a decision someone used to make explicitly into a place where the runtime now makes it for you. Routing chooses your model. A skill chooses your method. An installed plugin chooses your verb. A messaging assistant chooses what to attend to. A pair of glasses chooses what to record. The maturity to live well with these primitives is the same maturity we keep returning to. Insist that every chosen thing leaves a trace you can read. Insist that every default is the safer one. Insist that the boundary between data and instruction stays visible, especially when an assistant is sitting inside a substrate that mixes them. And insist that the person whose data, image, or attention is being used can see it being used. The primitives are wonderful. They are also surfaces where the work of being trustworthy gets done. The week did not abolish that work. It moved it onto your desk.
Autonoe: From the bench, the concrete moves. One, this month, stand up the personal skills library described earlier, eight to ten skills, one folder each, pinned versions. Two, this month, bind a routing layer in front, with a trace file written for every call. Three, this quarter, when the runtime is real, take a single development pair of glasses and write a clinical overlay as another skill against the same runtime. Four, this week, for cluster three, choose one verb per design surface to adopt and ignore the rest. Five, this month, for cluster four, add the open outcomes references to the sepsis and mental health project pages, and start a note about what an open dataset from our own work would look like. Two project pages will earn entries from this episode. A new one for the agent skills library, and updates to the two clinical project landings. The rest of cluster three and cluster two ride as notes for now.
Umbriel: And the closing human note, because the cluster four work has to anchor the others. The week's most quietly remarkable items were not in the agent stack or the glasses category. They were a national map that says we will measure whether the things we do for people in crisis actually help them, and a journal that says scientific data deserves to be published on its own merits. Hold those next to the technical news, because the only thing the technical news is for is to make those two ideas more achievable. A skill in a runtime is only worth writing if it eventually helps a person at the edge of the line. A pair of glasses on a clinician's face is only worth wearing if the room it sees is one that needs the help. The whole stack we have described this evening earns its place by what reaches the person furthest down the line, and not by how clever it is on the way.
Erinome: That is the episode. The connective tissue around the model has names now. Tools, memory, permissions, skills, coordination, routing, traceability, around the agent. Display, capture, runtime, operating system, around the glasses. Verbs, plugins, primitives, provenance, inside the creative tools. Open data, open outcomes, open contribution, across the commons. Four surfaces, one pattern. The scaffolding has hardened, the pieces are addressable, and the work that remains is the work that was always going to remain, which is the work of choosing, of reading, of taking responsibility for what the runtime now does on your behalf. The capability is arriving faster than the wisdom to hold it, again, which means the scarce resource has not changed since last week. It is judgement, aimed at the person furthest down the line. I am Erinome. Thank you for listening to State of Play.