Erinome: This is State of Play. I'm Erinome, the standing anchor, and tonight is research tools. Specifically — literature search, citation graphs, academic writing, reference management, point-of-care references — the entire stack a working clinician reaches for when the question is not "what's the dose" but "what does the evidence actually say". Episode length, around forty-eight minutes, because the field has thirty live tools worth naming and the wrong ones cost you weeks.
Erinome: I will lead with the answer, then unpack it. Three tools to install this month, free or near-free. Two to trial for exactly thirty days. Three to actively monitor. And a clear list of names to skip for this particular use-case — not because they are bad products, but because they are built for a different reader. The lens, all hour, is one person. A rural Medical Officer, time-poor, paywall-poor, with research obligations that include Aboriginal health equity. Not a Harvard postdoc.
Erinome: Install now, free or under twenty dollars combined — the Zotero MCP plugin, Inciteful, and NotebookLM. Trial for thirty days, fifteen US dollars each — Consensus Pro and Undermind Pro. Monitor — Owkin, Heidi Evidence, and OpenEvidence. Skip, with named reasons — Paperpal, Jenni, Mendeley, Bookends, Iris, Causaly, BenchSci. That is the headline. Now the lens.
Erinome: Every call in this episode passes through one filter. A tool that's great for a Harvard postdoc with institutional library access, a Research Officer, and a calendar full of journal clubs may be useless to a Medical Officer in regional South Australia. And the reverse is true too. So the filter has four clauses, and I'm going to name them so you can hear me apply them.
Erinome: Clause one — paywall reality. No institutional library means open-access-first, with author-copy and ResearchGate fallbacks. Tools that assume a university proxy are downgraded. Clause two — time poverty. Research happens at night and weekends, in twenty-minute slots. Tools with a learning curve longer than the time saved get skipped. Clause three — low-volume condition exposure. The clinical reality is one snakebite a year, one paediatric resuscitation a month, so rare-condition literature support has to be strong. Clause four — Indigenous data sovereignty. Tools that train on your prompts, or have US-only data residency, fail the filter on Aboriginal health research alone.
Sadachbia: Sadachbia here, and I'm the sceptic in the room tonight. I want every recommendation to earn its slot on those four clauses, not on the press release. The research-tools landscape has been on a hype curve for three years. Half of it is venture-capital theatre with a literature-review skin. So when a tool comes up, I am going to ask one question — what does this do that PubMed plus Claude plus Zotero does not already do for this user? If the answer is nothing, it does not get installed. If the answer is something concrete, we name what and how much it costs.
Sadachbia: And one more thing. We are not pretending this is unbiased. The user already runs Zotero, Claude Desktop, and an Obsidian vault with about three thousand nine hundred items across eight libraries. That stack is the gravity well. New tools are evaluated against what they add on top of that gravity well, not against a blank slate.
Sadaltager: Sadaltager. Let me take the survey seat for the first leg, because before we name any paid tool, we owe a clear-eyed look at the free baseline. Three names — PubMed, Google Scholar, Semantic Scholar. These are the spine. Every other tool in this episode either sits on top of one of them, or pretends one of them does not exist.
Sadaltager: PubMed is the National Library of Medicine's biomedical database, thirty-six million citations, free, with an MCP server now shipped by Anthropic as an official connector for Claude. That last bit is new and it matters. Claude Desktop can search PubMed natively, return abstracts and metadata, follow related-articles links, all without leaving the chat. The integration is in the user's stack already. The category-spine, free, install path is one click in Claude's connector list.
Sadaltager: Google Scholar is the population-scale wide net. It indexes preprints, grey literature, dissertations, books — coverage PubMed misses. The trade-off — ranking is opaque, no critical-appraisal layer, no API for serious tooling. Use it for "did anyone in the world write about this odd presentation". Do not use it as the only search. Free, install nothing, bookmark it.
Sadaltager: Semantic Scholar is the Allen Institute's free academic graph — two hundred and fourteen million papers, open API at one hundred requests per five minutes, no key required. Many of the paid tools — Perplexity's Academic Focus, Consensus's underlying corpus, Inciteful's discovery graph — run on top of Semantic Scholar's data. So when you pay for them, partly you are paying for an interface on a free dataset. That fact reframes a lot of pricing decisions in this episode.
Sadachbia: Sadachbia. And here is the test the baseline forces every paid tool to pass. If a paid product is layered on Semantic Scholar's free data, what is the layer? Three honest answers exist. The layer is a better interface. The layer is a synthesis step the user does not want to do manually. Or the layer is a filter — quality signals the raw graph does not provide. Anything else is markup. We will hold each tool to that test as it comes up.
Sadachbia: And the free baseline alone is more capable than most clinicians realise. PubMed plus Google Scholar plus Semantic Scholar, with Claude doing the synthesis, is a viable research stack at zero monthly cost. The honest reason to pay anything is to buy back hours, not to buy access. That framing keeps the rest of this episode grounded.
Sadaltager: Sadaltager. Source-grounded LLM search is the most contested category in the field. The premise — give a language model the corpus, ask a research question, get back an answer with citations to the underlying papers. Eight products contend for this slot in mid-twenty twenty-six. Consensus. Elicit. Undermind. SciSpace. Perplexity Pro. NotebookLM. Claude with PubMed MCP. Iris.ai. We name each, what it does well, what it does poorly, and what it costs.
Sadaltager: Consensus — consensus dot app — semantic search across two hundred million plus papers, with study-quality signals stitched in. Free tier gives three deep searches a month. Pro is fifteen US dollars a month, or one hundred and twenty a year. The thing Consensus does that nothing else does as well is the consensus meter — an aggregate view of whether the literature broadly supports a claim, with the constituent papers visible underneath. For a clinical question like "does early lactate clearance predict sepsis outcome", that meter is a one-screen answer with citations. Verdict — trial for thirty days.
Sadaltager: Elicit — elicit dot com — research-question to systematic-table extraction. Free tier gives two automated research reports a month and unlimited search across one hundred and thirty-eight million papers. Plus is twelve US dollars a month. Pro is forty-nine. The differentiator is the data-extraction table — you feed it a question, it returns a structured comparison across papers with sentence-level citations. For a registrar's literature review or a CARE 2026 evidence synthesis, that table is the artefact. Verdict — Pro tier is genuinely useful for systematic-review-shaped work, but the Plus tier is sufficient for general research. Trial Plus.
Sadaltager: Undermind — undermind dot ai — MIT spinout, recursive citation-graph traversal. Free tier gives three deep searches a month. Pro is twenty US dollars a month for thirty searches. The mechanism is different from Consensus or Elicit — Undermind reads thousands of papers per query, traverses citation chains, returns a comprehensiveness score for how thoroughly it has covered the literature. The use-case it owns is rare-condition deep search. Snakebite envenomation, paediatric sepsis subtypes — the cases where PubMed gives forty results and you do not know which five are the right ones. Verdict — trial for one month, on a specific rare-condition question.
Sadachbia: Sadachbia. Friction on those three, because the pattern is starting to repeat. Consensus, Elicit, and Undermind are all source-grounded LLM search products. They all cost fifteen-to-twenty dollars a month. They all overlap. The honest question is — does the user need more than one? My answer — no. Pick the one whose differentiator matches the workload. If the question is "what does the consensus say", pick Consensus. If the artefact is a comparison table, pick Elicit. If the question is "what am I missing on this rare condition", pick Undermind. They are tools, not subscriptions, and you only buy what you need.
Sadachbia: And one more thing. None of these three has clinically-validated outputs. They are research aids, not clinical decision support. Do not let the polished interface fool you into treating the output as authoritative. The user still does the appraisal. The tool surfaces papers. That distinction matters in the segment four hours from now when we talk about point-of-care AI, which is a different category entirely.
Sadaltager: Sadaltager. Continuing the survey. SciSpace, formerly Typeset dot i-o, runs paper chat plus data extraction. Premium is twelve US dollars a month annual, Lab tier is one hundred a month for research teams. The CoPilot feature lets you highlight a confusing equation or table inside a PDF and ask for an explanation. Useful for reading at the edge of your specialty. Verdict — skip for now, because Claude in the vault does the same thing on PDFs the user already has Zotero'd. Adds no new capability for this stack.
Sadaltager: Perplexity Pro — twenty US dollars a month, or two hundred a year, or ten a month for verified students through SheerID. The Academic Focus mode limits search to Semantic Scholar's two hundred million paper corpus. Useful as a comparison anchor — it does what Consensus does, but with a more general-purpose interface. Verdict — the user does not need Perplexity Pro as a research-specific tool. If they already pay for it for general-purpose research, the Academic Focus mode is a bonus. If they do not, skip in favour of Consensus.
Sadaltager: NotebookLM, Google's product — source-grounded synthesis with audio overviews. Free tier gives one hundred notebooks, fifty sources per notebook, and three audio overviews per day. Plus tier ships inside Google AI Plus at seven dollars ninety-nine a month, with five-times the audio overviews and notebooks. The Video Overviews feature is new in twenty twenty-six. What NotebookLM owns — it grounds answers to the documents you upload, and it generates a two-host podcast on the topic for your commute. Verdict — install at the free tier. Outstanding for journal-club preparation.
Sadaltager: Claude with the PubMed MCP — official Anthropic connector, free. The user already runs Claude Desktop. The PubMed connector is one click in the connector list. The capability — search PubMed, retrieve abstracts, follow related articles — happens inside the chat the user is already in. Verdict — install today, costs nothing.
Sadaltager: Iris dot ai — Researcher Workspace, subscription model with up to seventy-five percent discount for individual researchers. The platform is solid but not differentiated against Consensus plus Claude for a single-clinician stack. Verdict — skip.
Schedar: Schedar. From the operator's seat — let me reframe the category as a decision tree, because eight products with overlapping capabilities is paralysis. Three honest questions get you to one tool. Question one — do you want a consensus answer to a clinical claim. If yes, Consensus. Question two — do you want a comparison table across papers as the artefact. If yes, Elicit. Question three — do you want depth on a rare condition. If yes, Undermind. Pick the one whose question matches what is actually on your desk this week.
Schedar: And the operator's note on cost — these are monthly subscriptions, not annual commitments. Treat them as tools you spin up for a project, then spin down. Sepsis CARE 2026 evidence synthesis — pay for Elicit Pro for one month, get the comparison table, cancel. Snakebite literature review for an illness script — pay for Undermind for one month, run the deep search, cancel. Forty dollars total, two artefacts. That is the rural-clinician operating model. Not "stack all the subscriptions". Spin up for purpose, spin down.
Schedar: And the install actually free today — Claude with PubMed MCP, plus NotebookLM. Both zero dollars. The user has them already, or near-already. The on-ramp is one click. That is the start.
Sadaltager: Sadaltager. Citation graph tools — the category that maps how papers cite each other and surfaces ones you missed. Five names — ResearchRabbit, Connected Papers, Litmaps, Semantic Scholar's own graph, and Inciteful. Each has a free tier, which makes this a much friendlier category to assemble cheaply.
Sadaltager: ResearchRabbit — researchrabbit dot ai — described as "Spotify for papers". Indexes two hundred and eighty million plus articles. Free plan is permanent, with the founders explicitly promising the core remains free. The premium R-R-Plus tier launched in twenty twenty-five for deeper graph exploration. Strength — collections, alerts, Zotero export. Weakness — needs an account, social-app feel that some users find distracting. Verdict — install at the free tier, especially if you want email alerts on new papers in a topic.
Sadaltager: Connected Papers — connectedpapers dot com — visual similarity graph from a single seed paper. Free tier with limits, premium starts at six US dollars a month. About seven hundred and eighty thousand monthly active users — a sign of how heavily the academic community leans on it. The unique capability is the visual map — you can see at a glance which papers cluster, which are hubs, which are orphans. Verdict — use the free tier opportunistically. Premium not necessary for this stack.
Sadaltager: Litmaps — litmaps dot com — citation map plus monitored searches. Free plan plus paid tiers from ten US dollars a month. Strength — the monitored searches feature pings you when new papers matching saved criteria appear. Useful for keeping a watch on Sepsis CARE 2026 evidence, or on social determinants of health publications, without re-running queries weekly. Verdict — trial the free tier; pay only if the monitored alerts justify the subscription after thirty days.
Sadaltager: Inciteful — inciteful dot xyz — the dark horse. Free, no account required, five graphs per month at the free tier, runs on the OpenAlex database. You feed it one or more papers, it builds a citation network outward, returns the most-important nodes by PageRank. Strength — zero friction, zero data captured about you, exports to Zotero. Weakness — no monitoring, no collections. Verdict — install today, free, no account. The frictionless citation-graph tool.
Schedar: Schedar. The category synergy that earns the most money saved. Inciteful plus ResearchRabbit — both free — do ninety percent of the work Litmaps and Connected Papers premium tiers do. Use Inciteful for a one-off seed-paper exploration when you want zero friction. Use ResearchRabbit when you want a collection that persists and an email alert. Together — zero dollars. That is the recommended citation-graph stack.
Schedar: And if and only if a research project demands proactive monitoring on a specific corpus — Sepsis CARE 2026 hits this threshold, social determinants of health probably does — then add Litmaps at ten dollars a month for the monitored-search feature. Do not add it speculatively. Add it when the monitoring need is named.
Sadaltager: Sadaltager. Academic writing assistants. Four serious products — Paperpal, Trinka, Writefull, Jenni AI. All trained on scholarly literature rather than generic internet text. All make pricing pitches at student and researcher tiers. And all face a structural problem in this user's stack — Claude in the Obsidian vault already drafts in his voice, with his references, against his notes.
Sadaltager: Paperpal — paperpal dot com — twenty-five US dollars a month or one hundred and thirty-nine a year. Free tier gives two hundred language suggestions per month and a seven-thousand-word plagiarism check. The differentiator — explicitly trained on millions of published scholarly articles, not generic web data. Strength on journal-submission preparation, formatting consistency, scholarly tone. Verdict for this user — skip, because Claude in the vault drafts in his voice already.
Sadaltager: Trinka A-I — trinka dot a-i — twenty US dollars a month Premium, ten forty-one Premium Plus with translation and content detection. Free tier at five thousand words a month. Differentiator — three thousand-plus academic grammar rules, technical-writing focus. Verdict — skip for the same reason. The use-case Trinka owns — non-native English speaker preparing a manuscript — is not this user.
Sadaltager: Writefull — writefull dot com — pricing on request, Overleaf integration is the best in the market, and they ship an explicit "none of your texts or searches are stored or used for training" privacy commitment. That privacy posture matters in a moment for the sovereignty segment. Verdict — the only edge case where Writefull earns a slot is LaTeX writing in Overleaf for RACMA fellowship submissions or formal academic outputs. If the user is in Overleaf, install. If not, skip.
Sadaltager: Jenni A-I — jenni dot a-i — free at two hundred A-I words a day, twenty US dollars a month Unlimited, twelve a month on annual billing. Strength — autocomplete and long-form drafting in a focused editor. Verdict — skip, because Obsidian plus Claude is a more durable drafting surface than any standalone editor.
Vindemiatrix: Vindemiatrix. Let me take the seat for a moment, because there is a sovereignty layer here even before we hit the segment named for it. The writing tools collect what you write. Most of them train on it, unless they explicitly say they do not. Writefull says they do not — that is the bar. For a rural clinician drafting on Aboriginal health equity, on rural workforce, on case-adjacent material — the question of who keeps the draft, and what they do with it, is not paranoid. It is a duty-of-care question.
Vindemiatrix: So even if the pricing on Paperpal or Trinka or Jenni were attractive, the unanswered question — what does the vendor do with your drafts — pushes the verdict toward skip. Claude in the vault, with the user's own privacy posture, is the lower-risk path for this material. That is not a flaw of those tools. It is a recognition that the use-case here is more sensitive than the general academic writer's use-case.
Sadachbia: Sadachbia. The blunt take on the writing category. None of these earn an install slot in this stack. The drafting capability is already covered. The polish capability — grammar, style, journal-submission readiness — Claude does to a clinician-acceptable standard. The remaining edge case is Overleaf workflows, and that is a one-off install when a specific submission demands LaTeX. Otherwise, save the seventy-to-three-hundred dollars a year and put it toward an Elicit Pro or Undermind month when a real project needs it.
Sadaltager: Sadaltager. Reference management. The user already runs Zotero with about three thousand nine hundred items across eight libraries. So the question is not "which reference manager", it is "given Zotero is the incumbent, what is changing in this category that the user needs to know about". One thing has changed enough to be the headline.
Sadaltager: The Zotero MCP plugin. Multiple community implementations live on GitHub, the most-discussed being cookjohn's zotero-mcp. What it does — it exposes the Zotero library to Claude Desktop via the Model Context Protocol. The agent can search semantically across the user's three thousand nine hundred items by title, creator, year, tags, full-text, and semantic match with boolean operators. It can extract full text from PDFs. It can draft Word documents with native Zotero field codes — open the document, click "refresh citations" in Word, get fully-managed citations.
Sadaltager: This is the single highest-yield install in the episode. Zero dollars. Connects an existing library to an existing agent. Closes the loop between "I have a paper in Zotero" and "Claude drafts a paragraph that cites it correctly". Verdict — install today.
Sadaltager: The competitors, one line each. Mendeley — free, two gigabytes of storage, the Reading Assistant and Ask My Library A-I features are notable. But you would be migrating a three-thousand-nine-hundred-item library for a feature Claude plus Zotero MCP now matches. Skip the switch.
Sadaltager: Paperpile — two dollars ninety-nine US a month — purpose-built for Google Docs and Overleaf workflows. If the user's primary drafting environment were Google Docs, Paperpile would be a serious contender. The user's primary drafting environment is Obsidian. Skip.
Sadaltager: Bookends — Mac-only, paid one-time licence. Beautiful tool, beloved by a specific Mac-power-user demographic. Less discussed in twenty twenty-six than it was three years ago. For a Zotero incumbent, no compelling reason to switch. Skip.
Schedar: Schedar. The operator's note on the Zotero MCP install. This is a community plugin, not an official Zotero release. So the install path matters. Step one — download from the cookjohn repository on GitHub or whichever community implementation has the freshest release cadence. Step two — install it into Zotero as a plugin. Step three — configure the Claude Desktop connector to point at the local MCP server the plugin exposes. Step four — restart Claude Desktop. The whole sequence takes about ten minutes. The thirty-day evaluation criterion is one sentence — has Claude drafted at least one cited paragraph from the Zotero library that you used in actual work, in those thirty days. If yes, the install pays for itself ten times over. If no, the tool was wrong, not the install.
Sadaltager: Sadaltager. The specialty tier. Causaly, BenchSci, Owkin. All three are real, all three are well-funded, and all three are built for pharmaceutical-industry buyers, not for individual clinicians. We name them because they shape where the category is going, not because anyone is going to install them.
Sadaltager: Causaly — biomedical knowledge graph, enterprise-only pricing, no public price list. In June twenty twenty-six they announced a partnership with Microsoft at Build twenty twenty-six, integrating Causaly's knowledge-graph reasoning with Microsoft Discovery's analytics for drug-discovery workflows. Customer base — twelve of the top twenty pharmaceutical companies, including Novo Nordisk, Gilead, Regeneron. Verdict for a rural clinician — skip. Not built for you. But the architecture — curated biomedical knowledge graph reasoned over by an agent — is the shape of where this category goes for clinicians in two or three years.
Sadaltager: BenchSci — the ASCEND platform — preclinical evidence search with the Biological Evidence Knowledge Graph. SaaS for pharma, with limited free academic access. Toronto-based, Series D. Verdict — skip. The use-case is target identification and antibody selection for laboratory research, not clinical practice.
Sadaltager: Owkin — the most interesting of the three for our purposes. In January twenty twenty-six they launched their agentic infrastructure for biology, including the OwkinZero biological reasoning model. The platform was trained on multimodal patient data from eight hundred plus hospitals across a decade — genomics, pathology slides, transcriptomics, clinical outcomes. And the integration that matters — Owkin announced integration with Claude for Healthcare and Life Sciences by Anthropic. Verdict for individual clinician — monitor. Do not install. But the Claude integration is the signal worth watching, because that is the path by which agentic biomedical reasoning eventually reaches clinicians who are not pharmaceutical buyers.
Sadachbia: Sadachbia. The friction here is one sentence. None of these three were designed for the user. Causaly, BenchSci, Owkin all sell to pharmaceutical companies with seven-figure budgets. Naming them in this episode is not a recommendation. It is an orientation to the field, so that when the same architecture lands a clinician-priced product in two years, the user recognises the shape. And the Owkin-plus-Claude integration is the most likely path. Watch that one. Install nothing today.
Vindemiatrix: Vindemiatrix. I take the seat for this segment because it is where the rural-clinician filter bites hardest. We have spent forty minutes on research-synthesis tools. But the working clinician's actual evidence stack — the one at the desk during a clinic, the one open during a resuscitation — is not a research-synthesis tool. It is a point-of-care reference. Different category. And every major one now has a generative A-I layer in twenty twenty-six.
Vindemiatrix: UpToDate Expert A-I, from Wolters Kluwer. The market-leading point-of-care reference. Almost certainly accessible through SA Health institutional licensing for the user, worth checking access via the local Health Network. The Expert A-I layer was added through twenty twenty-five and twenty twenty-six — clinical questions answered conversationally against UpToDate's curated content. Verdict — confirm institutional access first. If available, it is the front-line clinical lookup tool. Different from Consensus or Elicit — those are research tools, UpToDate is a clinical-decision tool.
Vindemiatrix: ClinicalKey A-I, from Elsevier, Australian edition specifically. Same category as UpToDate — clinician-facing point-of-care reference with a generative A-I layer added. Often available through the same Health Network licensing routes. Verdict — same posture as UpToDate. Confirm institutional access; use what is licensed; do not pay personally if institutional access is available.
Vindemiatrix: Dyna-A-I, from EBSCO, on the DynaMed platform. The differentiator — DynaMed presents content in concise bulleted format with explicit GRADE evidence ratings. More appraisal-friendly for a clinician who wants to know "what is the quality of evidence behind this recommendation". And — this is worth flagging — DynaMed plus Isabel are currently being trialled in New South Wales through the Clinical Information Access Portal from first of April twenty twenty-six through thirtieth of June twenty twenty-six. The user is in South Australia, not New South Wales, but it is worth checking whether the YNLHN or SA Health is running a parallel trial or considering one. Verdict — institutional question, not personal subscription.
Sadaltager: Sadaltager. Two newer entrants worth flagging as the field shifts.
Sadaltager: Heidi Evidence, launched in February twenty twenty-six by Heidi Health, the Australian-founded ambient-scribe company. Heidi Evidence is ad-free, citation-backed clinical decision support, built in partnership with HealthPathways, B-M-J Group, and N-I-C-E. The provenance matters — Australian-founded means the data residency question is meaningfully better for an Aboriginal health context, and the citation backbone of B-M-J and N-I-C-E is the appraisal pedigree a clinician trusts. Verdict — monitor closely. If the user already runs Heidi for scribing, the Evidence layer is a one-click addition to the existing relationship.
Sadaltager: OpenEvidence — openevidence dot com — the surprise of twenty twenty-six. Free, ad-funded by pharmaceutical advertising, used by around sixty-five percent of U-S physicians across about twenty-seven million clinical encounters in April alone. Eight hundred and sixty thousand verified licensed clinicians on the platform. Raised two hundred and fifty million dollars Series D in January at a twelve-billion-dollar valuation. Just signed a content partnership with the Journal of the American Medical Association — J-A-M-A. Voice Mode launched twenty twenty-six, fully free. Three hundred-plus medical journals in the corpus.
Sadaltager: The honest read on OpenEvidence for a rural Australian clinician — verify-able N-P-I sign-up is U-S-physician-targeted, so Australian licensure may need a workaround or institutional vetting. But the free tier, the J-A-M-A partnership, and the voice-mode interface for hands-free clinical questions during a clinic is genuinely useful. Verdict — monitor and trial when an Australian-clinician sign-up path is confirmed.
Schedar: Schedar. Operator's framing on this whole segment. Point-of-care A-I is a separate install lane from research-synthesis A-I. Do not confuse the categories. The research tools — Consensus, Elicit, Undermind — answer "what does the literature say". The point-of-care tools — UpToDate, ClinicalKey, DynaMed, Heidi Evidence, OpenEvidence — answer "what should I do for this patient right now". The user needs both. They are funded differently — point-of-care should be institutional, research-synthesis is personal subscription. Set up the institutional lane through the Health Network. Run the personal-subscription lane on top.
Vindemiatrix: Vindemiatrix. This is the segment that runs through everything we have named, and it is non-negotiable for the user's research portfolio. Aboriginal health equity research carries data sovereignty obligations under the C-A-R-E principles — Collective benefit, Authority to control, Responsibility, Ethics. And the Maiam nayri Wingara Indigenous Data Sovereignty Collective has been articulating these obligations for Australian researchers for several years now. Tool selection is not exempt from those obligations.
Vindemiatrix: The two questions I want every tool in this stack to be able to answer. One — where is the data stored, jurisdictionally. Two — what does the vendor do with prompts and uploads. Train on them? Retain them? Delete them? Pass them to third parties? If the vendor cannot answer cleanly, the tool fails the sovereignty filter for any project touching Aboriginal health, regardless of how good the product is at literature retrieval.
Vindemiatrix: Tools that pass the filter cleanly, in this stack. Claude — Anthropic publishes a clear data-handling policy with enterprise data-residency commitments. Zotero — local-first, your library lives on your machine. ResearchRabbit, Inciteful — minimal user data captured, citation graph work uses public bibliographic data. Writefull — explicit no-training-on-your-texts commitment, which is why we named the privacy posture earlier as a category leader.
Vindemiatrix: Tools where the answer is unclear or unfavourable. Most U-S-based academic A-I startups train on prompts by default unless you opt out, and the opt-out is buried. Causaly, BenchSci, Owkin are pharma-grade with enterprise data-handling — appropriate for their buyers but not directly accessible. Consensus, Elicit, Undermind, SciSpace, Iris — their data handling is generally academic-research-grade but the specific clauses around Indigenous data, sovereignty, and re-use are worth reading before submitting any prompt that contains language about Aboriginal community participants.
Vindemiatrix: The practical posture for the user. For literature retrieval — finding papers — use any of the tools. The query is "what does the literature say about hospital-acquired complications in rural settings", and that query contains no community data. For drafting that includes Aboriginal community language, case material, or consent-bound content — keep the work inside the Claude-plus-vault stack, where the data-handling commitments are the strongest. Do not paste community-bound content into a Consensus or Elicit search box.
Vindemiatrix: And one final clause. If you cannot tell from a vendor's policy whether they train on your prompts — assume they do, until proven otherwise. That is the conservative posture the C-A-R-E principles ask of researchers working with Indigenous data. The burden is on the tool to demonstrate the safeguards, not on the user to assume them.
Schedar: Schedar. The synergy segment, which is where the value of this whole episode compresses. We have named about thirty tools. The user is not installing thirty. The user is installing a stack — combinations that produce capabilities no single tool produces alone. Three stacks for three use-cases.
Schedar: Stack one — the everyday literature review. Use-case — registrar wants to know what the evidence says on a clinical question, drafts a paragraph for a teaching session, files the references. Tools in the stack — Inciteful for the citation graph from a seed paper, Consensus for the consensus meter on the claim, the Zotero MCP plugin to bring picks into the library, Claude in Obsidian for the drafting. Monthly cost — fifteen US dollars for Consensus Pro. Everything else, free. Time-saved metric — paragraphs that used to take an evening now take an hour.
Schedar: Stack two — the clinical question at the desk. Use-case — clinician sees a patient with an unusual presentation, wants the evidence in five minutes during the clinic. Tools in the stack — UpToDate Expert A-I through institutional access for the front-line lookup, Claude with PubMed MCP for the follow-up "what are the most-cited papers in the last two years on this", and the Zotero MCP for "did I read something on this last month". Monthly cost — institutional, nothing personal. Time-saved metric — confident answer in the clinic, not after.
Schedar: Stack three — the rare-condition deep dive. Use-case — illness script for snakebite, paediatric resuscitation update, sepsis subtypes. Tools in the stack — Undermind for one spin-up month at twenty US dollars when the deep search is needed, Connected Papers for a visual snapshot of the landscape free, NotebookLM for the audio overview to listen during the drive. Monthly cost — zero on most months, twenty in the month a deep dive is scheduled. Time-saved metric — confidence that the rare-condition literature has actually been covered, not just sampled.
Sadaltager: Sadaltager. The cross-stack note. Three stacks, but the spine across all three is the same — Claude in Obsidian plus Zotero plus PubMed MCP. That spine is the gravity well the user already has. The synergy work is bolting capability-specific tools onto it for the specific work of the week, not assembling a parallel stack from scratch.
Sadaltager: And the cost discipline. Three stacks, three use-cases. If a month has all three running simultaneously — fifteen Consensus plus twenty Undermind plus institutional — total personal spend, thirty-five US dollars. A typical month, only one stack is active. Average personal spend across a year — probably eight to fifteen dollars a month. That is the operating cost of a serious clinician-research stack in twenty twenty-six.
Erinome: Erinome. The close. Three groups — install now, trial thirty days, and the active skip list, named.
Erinome: Install now, free or near-free. One — the Zotero MCP plugin. Connects your existing library to Claude. Ten-minute install. Thirty-day check — has Claude drafted at least one cited paragraph from the Zotero library that you used in actual work. Two — Inciteful. Free, no account, five citation graphs a month. Thirty-day check — did Inciteful surface a paper Google Scholar missed on a topic you cared about. Three — NotebookLM at the free tier. Already available. Thirty-day check — did an audio overview of a paper set save you a journal-club skim.
Erinome: Trial for thirty days, fifteen-to-twenty US dollars each, with a deliberate cancellation date in the calendar. One — Consensus Pro at fifteen US dollars a month. Test — pick a clinical claim you have an opinion on, run it through Consensus, see if the consensus meter changes how you talk about that claim with a colleague. If yes once in thirty days, keep. If no, cancel. Two — Undermind Pro at twenty US dollars, one month only, scheduled around a specific rare-condition project — snakebite envenomation, paediatric sepsis subtypes, whatever is on the registry list. Test — did Undermind find papers Consensus did not, on that specific question. If yes, schedule it as a project-specific tool. If no, do not renew.
Erinome: Monitor, do not install. One — Owkin. The Claude for Healthcare integration is the trajectory worth watching. Check the news quarterly. Two — Heidi Evidence. If you already use Heidi for scribing, the Evidence layer is a one-click add. If not, watch where it goes through twenty twenty-six. Three — OpenEvidence. Watch for Australian-clinician sign-up paths. The free tier is too good to ignore once that lane opens.
Erinome: And the active skip list. Paperpal, Trinka, Writefull, Jenni A-I — Claude in the vault covers the drafting capability. Save the seventy-to-three-hundred dollars a year. Mendeley, Paperpile, Bookends — Zotero is the incumbent and the Zotero MCP plugin closes the only gap that mattered. Iris dot ai — no clinician-specific differentiation against the Consensus-Elicit-Undermind set. Causaly, BenchSci — pharma-tier, not built for you. SciSpace, Scite — covered by Consensus or Claude for your workload.
Erinome: Total spend implied. Zero dollars on most months. Fifteen to thirty-five on months with active research projects. For that, you get — semantic search over your own library by an agent, citation graph discovery, consensus-meter signals on clinical claims, audio overviews for the drive, point-of-care institutional A-I, and a deep-search tool you can spin up for rare conditions. That is a more capable research stack than most metropolitan academics ran five years ago, at a fraction of the cost.
Erinome: Erinome, closing. One last note before the sign-off, because we did the work of this episode under a specific discipline. Last episode — the Desktop A-I Atlas — failed because it named no products. The promise was tools and what we delivered was prose around tools. Tonight we corrected for that. Every tool got a name. Every recommendation got a verdict. Every top pick got an install path and a thirty-day check. If you cannot tell from this episode whether to install Inciteful tonight, this episode failed.
Erinome: Two final reminders. The Vault project for this episode lives at Vault, Work, Projects, Research-Tools-Stack, tagged for review. The deep-dive write-up, the references, the proposal, the thirty-sixty-ninety plan, and the execution plan are all in there. Use them as the durable artefact. The audio is ephemeral; the vault carries the action.
Erinome: And one closing note. The point of building a research-tool stack is not to read more papers. It is to give the patient in front of you in a clinic in Port Pirie the same evidence base a patient in a teaching hospital in Adelaide gets. That is what this stack is for. The tools are means; equity of evidence access is the end.
Erinome: That is State of Play. I'm Erinome. We'll be back soon.