Erinome: This is State of Play. I am Erinome, the standing anchor, and tonight is about forty-two minutes. We are introducing a new project as it begins, on the day its scaffold lands in the vault. The project is called PhantomScan, and it is the second flagship clinical training tool from this desk, sibling to the AI-assisted advanced life support trainer. PhantomScan started this morning as a point-of-care ultrasound simulator, point-of-care ultrasound meaning the bedside ultrasound a doctor uses to make a decision in front of a patient. By the middle of the afternoon it had become something more interesting and more defensible. It is an integrated training continuum platform with four modalities under one roof, one digital human across all of them, and a closed-loop pipeline that lets any user reproduce any phantom locally. The dominant commercial neighbour in this space is an American company called SonoSim, well-built, deeply validated, used by medical schools worldwide. PhantomScan is not pitched against SonoSim's core offer. It is positioned as the part of the continuum SonoSim structurally does not cover and cannot cover without acquiring a phantom company. With me tonight are four voices. One who thinks like an engineer about how the device actually works. One who keeps asking what the evidence says and which trainees the device reaches. One who lives in the visual and asks what the learner sees on the screen and feels in the hand across the four modalities. And one who holds the trust questions, the regulatory questions, and the honesty about the landscape PhantomScan is entering. We have a continuum to introduce, a method to walk across four modalities, a phantom-creation pipeline to map, and a small commercial story to flag at the end. Orus, begin.
Orus: Orus here, in the methods seat. The shift I want to walk through first is the one that changes the conversation. PhantomScan this morning was a phantom plus a probe-shell plus a screen. PhantomScan this afternoon is a continuum of four training modalities, all sitting on the same digital human, all sharing one anatomical vocabulary, one set of scanning windows, and one curriculum. I will list the modalities cleanly first and then come back to each.
Orus: Modality one is fully in silico. A trainee opens a browser, sees a translucent three dimensional human body with selectable organs, drags a virtual probe across the skin with a mouse or a finger or a stylus, rotates the probe with a rocker or two-finger gesture, and the simulated B-mode pane shows the slice the virtual probe would produce. No hardware in the room. The trainee learns scanning windows, the spatial relationship between anatomy and probe plane, and the mental model of how to take a probe from a body surface to a target structure. Modality two is the original PhantomScan scope from this morning. The trainee picks up a three dimensional printed probe shell with a Bosch sensor inside it, rests it on a ballistic gel phantom of the body part of interest, and the simulator renders a B-mode image driven by the probe's pose. Real hand on a real probe on real gel, simulated image. Modality three is the bridge to clinical reality. The trainee picks up a real ultrasound probe and rests it on the same phantom geometry, but built with echogenic doping (graphite, psyllium, glass beads, water-filled tubing) so the real machine produces a real B-mode of the phantom interior. Real probe, real machine, phantom that responds like tissue. Modality four is the bedside. The platform does not pretend to ship modality four. The platform's job is to make sure the trainee arrives at modality four having spent meaningful time in modalities one, two, and three on the same anatomy with the same vocabulary.
Orus: The single most important point about this list, and the one the rest of the episode rests on, is that the modalities share a substrate. The translucent human in modality one is rendered from volumetric anatomical data. The simulated B-mode in modality two slices the same volumetric data. The echogenic phantom in modality three is built from the same anatomical model captured as a printable mould, with embedded targets that match the same vessel tree, the same nerves, the same abscess cavities. A trainee who learns the spatial geometry of the brachial neurovascular bundle in modality one finds the same bundle in the same geometry under their probe-shell in modality two and under a real probe on a doped gel in modality three. The transitions are not three separate learning events. They are one learning event running across three increasingly real surfaces. That is the structural argument and it is the reason the project is worth its own name and its own platform rather than being three small tools.
Erinome: Despina, lock the positioning honestly before we go further. SonoSim sits on top of this category. What does the continuum framing change about how PhantomScan talks about its place?
Despina: Despina here, in the ethics and risk seat. The continuum framing makes the positioning cleaner, not muddier, and that is the right kind of pivot. SonoSim is the dominant commercial ultrasound training platform. Their library of real-patient ultrasound cases runs into the thousands, they ship a probe-shaped controller, they have curricular integration and competency tracking at enterprise scale, and they distribute through Laerdal Medical to medical schools and nursing programs globally. I want to name what they do well plainly, because the rest of the conversation rests on the honesty here. SonoSim covers modality one extremely well. Their controller plus their case library is the strongest pattern-recognition surface the field has, and any new entrant who pretends otherwise is asking to be embarrassed. SonoSim also covers part of modality two through a product called LiveScan, which layers virtual scanning onto live volunteers or existing manikins. That is a real piece of training value, and we should say so.
Despina: What SonoSim does not cover, and structurally cannot cover from where they sit, is modality three. Their image source is a recorded library of patient encounters. A recorded library is not a phantom. They explicitly recommend separate phantom sessions for procedural skills, and they have no first-party phantom pipeline, no echogenic-doped gel recipes, no three dimensional printed mould workflow, no closed-loop validation. The gap is not an oversight on their part. It is a structural consequence of being a digital-only platform. To enter modality three first-party, SonoSim would need to acquire a phantom company or build one from scratch, both of which are expensive bets in a category they have already decided to leave to third parties.
Despina: That is the moat. PhantomScan does not pitch against SonoSim's library, and it does not pretend to outclass them on modality one. PhantomScan ships the continuum that includes modality three and that ties modalities one, two, and three together on a shared anatomical substrate. The pitch becomes simple. Where SonoSim is available, use SonoSim for pattern recognition on the vast case library, and use PhantomScan for procedural haptics on the phantoms and for the integrated continuum across the modalities the case library cannot cover. Where SonoSim is not available, PhantomScan is the practice surface for what it can teach honestly, including procedural haptic skills that no software-only platform can deliver. The position is complement, not competitor. The continuum makes that position structural rather than rhetorical.
Erinome: Umbriel, the evidence layer. What does the literature say about training across multiple modalities versus training in a single one, and how does the continuum thesis sit?
Umbriel: Umbriel here, in the research and human seat. The literature on multi-modality training in ultrasound is younger than the literature on either modality alone, but the direction it points is consistent. Galusko and colleagues published a systematic review in BMC Medical Education in 2019 covering thirty-eight studies on validity evidence for ultrasound simulator training. Simulator practice reliably improves performance on standardised assessments. The strongest validity evidence is for transthoracic echocardiography, growing for obstetric scanning, and well-established for emergency point-of-care ultrasound. That is the validity stack for modality one and modality two combined.
Umbriel: Hocking, Hebard, and Mitchell in Regional Anesthesia and Pain Medicine in 2011 reviewed the use of phantoms specifically for ultrasound-guided regional anaesthesia. The conclusion that phantom-based haptic practice transfers to live procedural skill, particularly for needle work, is the validity stack for modality three. Morrow and Broder in 2015 in the Journal of Emergency Medicine validated a cost-effective reusable vascular-access trainer phantom, demonstrating skill transfer from gel-phantom training to live peripherally-inserted central catheter insertion. That is the modality-three validity stack on the specific procedural surface the PhantomScan PICC arm targets first.
Umbriel: What the continuum adds, and where the literature is younger, is the cross-modality compounding. Tolsgaard and colleagues in a randomised controlled trial in Ultrasound in Obstetrics and Gynecology in 2015 demonstrated sustained skill transfer at one year from simulator-based ultrasound training, with a moderate-to-large effect size. The educational research on cognitive scaffolding consistently suggests that learners who anchor a skill in multiple representations transfer that skill better than learners who anchor it in one. Modality one builds the spatial mental model. Modality two builds the probe-handling and the procedural haptic skill in a controlled image environment. Modality three closes the loop by introducing the real-machine artefacts and the noise of a real B-mode. By the time the trainee meets modality four, they have practised the same anatomy three times on three different surfaces. That stacking is the continuum thesis and it is consistent with what the cognitive-load literature predicts. It is not yet directly cited by a randomised controlled trial on this exact platform, because this exact platform has not existed. Building that evidence is part of what PhantomScan, in time, can do.
Umbriel: And the rural angle, because this is still the through-line. Walker and colleagues in the Australian Journal of Rural Health in 2020 published the study that grounds the project. Rural Australian general practitioners benefit substantially from structured point-of-care ultrasound training. Access to phantoms and simulators is the dominant barrier. The continuum gives the rural practice four surfaces of training at a price point a small practice can sustain, instead of one surface at a price point only a teaching hospital can fund. That is the equity reading of the continuum and it is the strongest version of the rural argument the project can make.
Erinome: Autonoe, take us into what the trainee actually experiences. The continuum is real only if a learner can walk it.
Autonoe: Autonoe here. I will start at modality one because it is the surface most users will meet first, and the one that does the most pedagogical lifting before any hardware is in the room. The trainee opens a browser. On the screen they see a translucent three dimensional human. The skin is rendered as a faint outline. The organs are selectable; pick the upper arm, and the surrounding tissues fade further, while the brachial neurovascular bundle resolves inside the volume in its actual spatial position. The trainee can rotate the arm. They can dial the opacity slider. At one extreme the limb is solid, only the rough shape visible. At the other extreme the muscle and skin are invisible and the vessel tree, the nerves, the bones, float in space in their real geometry. The trainee then drags the virtual probe across the skin with a finger. As they do, a second pane shows the simulated B-mode slice corresponding to the probe's current position and orientation. A small inset shows where the probe-plane intersects the target structures that are visible in the translucent view. The cognitive load is paid here. No hardware in the room, no time pressure, full visual access to the anatomy. Once the trainee has learned where the brachial vein sits relative to the artery, where the median nerve crosses the field, where the bone gives a posterior shadow, they have a mental model they can carry into the next modality. This is what SonoSim, with the best case library in the world, cannot do, because their substrate is recorded clips and there is no underlying three dimensional model to render translucently.
Autonoe: Modality two is the original PhantomScan experience and it is the surface most clinical trainees will spend the most time on. The trainee picks up a three dimensional printed probe shell. Inside the shell sits a Bosch sensor reporting probe pose at one hundred hertz. They rest the shell on a phantom of the same body region they walked through in modality one. The phantom is ballistic gel containing the same embedded targets as the digital human anatomy. The screen now shows two panes side by side. On the left the simulated B-mode tracks the shell's pose in real time, with realistic acoustic shadowing behind dense targets, posterior enhancement behind fluid pockets, reverberation behind strong reflectors, and the granular speckle that makes the image read as ultrasound. On the right the translucent three dimensional viewer of the same volume sits beside it, with the probe-plane intersection updating live. The trainee can dial the translucent viewer's opacity at any time. The same pre-scan walkthrough they did in modality one is available beside their probe practice. Crucially, the trainee can now push a real needle into the gel, feeling the cross of the surface, the resistance of the bulk gel, the give of a vessel wall, the pop into the lumen. Procedural haptics are real. SonoSim cannot do that because their controller is rigid plastic over a sensor.
Autonoe: Modality three flips the image source. Same phantom geometry, but doped with echogenic components. Graphite suspension at point-five to one percent by weight gives the gel a general scattering background that mimics tissue. Psyllium husk adds fine speckle. Glass beads at one to three millimetres make hyperechoic point targets where you want them. Water-filled silicone tubing for vessels stays compressible and dark on B-mode. Surgical-tubing loops with a small peristaltic pump pushing thirty millilitres a minute give pulsatile Doppler. The trainee now picks up a real ultrasound probe, plugs it into a real machine, and gets a real B-mode of the doped phantom. The machine's own artefacts replace the simulator's artefacts. The trainee learns gain, depth, focus, transducer pressure, the genuine variability of a real ultrasound interface. The translucent three dimensional viewer can run beside the real machine on a tablet or a laptop as a side-channel reference. The same anatomy they have walked twice now stays in front of them.
Autonoe: And the modality switcher is the simplest part of the user interface, deliberately. A single control at the top of the workstation toggles between the four modalities. When modality four is selected, the platform shows the curriculum-level checklist for what the trainee should have completed before the bedside encounter, and steps back. The platform does not pretend to ship the patient. It is honest about where it ends.
Erinome: Orus, the hardware-and-software stack that supports all four modalities. Where does the engineering complexity sit, and what does the runtime look like?
Orus: The engineering complexity is consolidated in two places, and that is the design's main virtue. First, the volumetric anatomical model. One file describes the body part of interest at half-millimetre voxel resolution in a standard medical-image format. That same file is rendered by Three.js, the browser three dimensional rendering library, as a translucent volume for modality one and modality three's reference pane, and is sampled by a WebGL fragment shader to produce the simulated B-mode for modality one and modality two. One volume in graphics memory feeds every pane the platform draws. The engineering work to produce that volume sits in the acquisition pipeline using the open-source PLUS Toolkit, published by Lasso and colleagues in IEEE Transactions on Biomedical Engineering in 2014, developed by Queens University and the Kitware team, and used as the field's reference for tracked-ultrasound research for over a decade. PhantomScan inherits a peer-reviewed reconstruction stack rather than building one.
Orus: The second locus of complexity is the closed-loop pipeline that creates the phantoms in the first place, and Autonoe will walk that in detail in a moment because it is the project's other structural moat. What I want to land before we go there is the runtime cost story. Modality one needs nothing but a browser. Modality two needs the probe-shell, a sensor, and a microcontroller, total cost under sixty Australian dollars, plus a phantom and a screen. Modality three needs a real ultrasound machine, which most clinical sites can borrow access to for a session, plus the same phantom geometry rebuilt in an echogenic recipe. Modality four needs the bedside, which is the institution's resource, not the platform's. The total hardware spend for a working four-modality continuum at a single institution sits in the low thousands of Australian dollars. The enterprise software seat the dominant incumbent ships costs a different category of money for a different market. The two products do not have to fight; they live at different points in the price segmentation and they serve different parts of the same continuum.
Erinome: Autonoe, the closed loop. The pipeline that makes any user able to reproduce or customise any phantom locally. This is the project's other structural moat. Walk it.
Autonoe: The pipeline closes a loop most ultrasound training tools leave open. The loop has six steps and it lets any user, in principle, scan a reference (whether that reference is a commercial phantom, an anatomical specimen, or a clinically borrowed patient with consent and de-identification), turn it into a printable mould, cast a new phantom from that mould, and validate that the new phantom matches the reference. Step one is image acquisition. The same IMU-tracked probe-shell used in modality two is mounted on a real ultrasound probe, the same way it would be for an original PhantomScan v1 scan. A sweep over the reference produces pose-tagged B-mode frames. PLUS Toolkit reconstructs them into a volumetric model in the standard medical-image format. Step two is volume-to-mesh conversion. The volume is segmented in Three Dimensional Slicer, which is the open-source medical-image viewer. The segmentation extracts the anatomical structures of interest as mesh surfaces in the standard surface-tessellation format. Open3D and VTK on the Python side help with mesh manipulation, MeshLab does cleanup.
Autonoe: Step three is print-mode A, which is the simplest output: print the meshes themselves in rigid filament on the Bambu printer Jacob already owns. These printed anatomical models are useful for pre-scan briefings and for teaching anatomy outside the simulator. Step four is print-mode B, which is the most important output for the platform: print a negative-space mould of the phantom geometry. Pour ballistic gel into the mould while embedding the targets that match the reference anatomy, demould once cool, and you have a phantom ready for modality two or modality three depending on whether you doped the gel. Step five is print-mode C, where flexible-filament three dimensional printing is appropriate: print soft inserts that go into the gel as targets, such as anatomically accurate vessel trees that would be tedious to assemble from hand-cut tubing. Step six is the closed-loop validation. Scan the new phantom with the IMU probe shell, reconstruct its volume, compare it back to the reference. If the geometry matches, this becomes the next phantom volume in the simulator's library. If it does not, you adjust the print or the cast and iterate.
Autonoe: What this loop unlocks, and the reason it is a structural moat rather than just a workflow convenience, is reproducibility plus customisation plus sovereignty plus cost. Reproducibility because once a phantom is volumetric-imaged and its mould is archived as a printable file, any user can rebuild it without bespoke crafting. Customisation because local pathology variants, the specific pneumothorax presentation the local emergency department sees most, the particular vessel anatomy a regional Aboriginal community might benefit from training on, can be captured from a single reference and replicated indefinitely. Sovereignty because phantom-image data and phantom-derived models can be created, stored, and shared entirely on local infrastructure, without sending anything offshore. Cost because materials per phantom rebuild sit in the AUD 100 to 300 range against AUD 1000 to 10,000 for commercial-equivalent phantoms. And longer-term, the platform supports a community phantom library, a curated set of moulds and volumes and recipes shared the way open-source software is shared. Hurn Medical Pty Ltd, the corporate trustee of the Ross Family Trust, becomes the curation and quality-control layer for that library rather than the upstream maker of the phantoms themselves.
Despina: I want to put a careful frame around the sovereignty point before we leave the pipeline, because it is the right argument and it has to be made carefully. A community-curated phantom library is genuinely powerful for under-served regions, including remote Aboriginal communities where the medical training pathway has long been built around anatomy and presentations that do not match the local population. The platform that lets a local clinician capture a local reference and produce a local phantom is a meaningful equity tool. The discipline that has to come with it is the discipline that comes with any sovereignty argument. Consent for the source scans has to be genuine and informed, not buried in a research-participation form. Data ownership has to sit with the community whose anatomy is captured, not with the platform vendor. Quality control of the library has to involve voices from the communities it serves, not only the corporate trustee. The platform makes the technical work possible. The community-governance work is a separate piece, and the project's stated values commit it to doing that piece properly. Saying that on the launch episode is the right time to say it, because the values that ship with version one are the values that scale.
Erinome: Orus, the regulatory picture. A continuum with four modalities and a phantom-creation pipeline raises a different question than a single simulator.
Orus: It does, and the simpler answer is the right one. The Therapeutic Goods Administration classifies a device by intended use, not by the technology inside it. Each of the four modalities, on its own, sits cleanly within the training-device category as long as it is marketed and used for trainee practice rather than for clinical decision-making on real patients. The continuum integration does not change that. The phantom-creation pipeline is a manufacturing workflow for training devices, not a regulated activity in itself. As a training device explicitly not for clinical interpretation, PhantomScan likely qualifies for exemption under the excluded-goods-and-exempt-devices schedule. The clean side of the regulatory fork is therefore: ship the continuum, ship the pipeline, market and price both as training tools, document the limits in the user interface, schedule a pre-submission meeting with the Therapeutic Goods Administration before any commercial release, and preserve the option to take a clinical-interpretation product down a different regulatory pathway on a different timeline. Tonight we are talking about a training continuum that complements an existing training market. That is the cleanest version of the fork and the one the project will pursue.
Despina: And the discipline that keeps the project honest as it scales. The position is complement, not competitor, and that has to be carried through every surface. The marketing copy says complement. The user interface says complement. The curriculum says complement. The regulatory submission says complement. The pricing structure says complement. Any drift toward "PhantomScan replaces SonoSim" is the drift that loses both honesty and market position. Saying that explicitly at launch is the cheapest version of that discipline. Repeating it on every subsequent version is the maintenance cost.
Erinome: Autonoe, the twelve-week build plan for version one. How does the continuum scope fit?
Autonoe: The original twelve-week scope was a PICC arm phantom plus a probe shell plus a slice renderer. The continuum expansion adds the translucent three dimensional digital human for modality one, the echogenic recipe for the PICC arm for modality three, the printed mould for the PICC arm, and a modality switcher in the user interface. The reason it fits in twelve weeks is that most of the work is already in the original plan. The volumetric model that drives the modality two slice renderer is the same model that renders translucently in modality one. The phantom geometry for modality two is the same geometry the printed mould produces. The echogenic recipe is a recipe variation, not a separate piece of engineering. The modality switcher is a single toggle in the user interface. The cumulative addition to the twelve-week plan is on the order of two to four days of work, not weeks.
Autonoe: The week-by-week stays close to the original. Weeks one to four are hardware bring-up. Order the Bosch sensor breakout, the microcontroller, and the cabling; print the first probe shell; calibrate the sensor; write the WebSocket bridge from microcontroller to browser. Add to that the design of the modality switcher in the user interface and the loading of a simplified digital human model for modality one. Weeks five to eight are the acquisition phase and the print pipeline. Build the silent PICC arm phantom; borrow a portable ultrasound and a frame grabber for one or two sessions; reconstruct the volume in PLUS Toolkit; segment in Three Dimensional Slicer; print the phantom mould instead of hand-cutting an acrylic box; document the echogenic recipe for modality three. Weeks nine to twelve are the renderer and the integration. Stand up the Three.js renderer for both the simulated B-mode slice in modality two and the translucent three dimensional viewer paired with it. Add the in-silico path for modality one using the same volume positioned in body coordinates. Add the modality switcher. Test end-to-end latency on both modality one and modality two and confirm it sits below fifty milliseconds. Pilot with Jacob and two or three Port Pirie Regional Health Service registrar colleagues on the PICC arm continuum. By the end of week twelve you have a single-phantom proof-of-continuum: a digital human you can scan in a browser, a probe shell on a phantom whose image is simulated, the recipe to rebuild the same phantom doped for a real machine, and the printed mould to rebuild it elsewhere. Three modalities working, the fourth pointed at, and the pipeline that lets the next phantom take less than half the time.
Autonoe: The remaining seven phantoms come in version two over three to six months. Each one gets all four assets in one pass: a silent gel recipe for modality two, an echogenic recipe for modality three, a printed mould for the closed-loop pipeline, and a reference volume for the simulator. The compounding rate of phantom production rises sharply once the pipeline is real, which is the point of investing in the pipeline at all.
Erinome: Umbriel, the curriculum, mapped to the colleges, with the continuum framing included.
Umbriel: The training curriculum becomes simpler with the continuum, not more complex, because each phantom carries a four-step progression rather than a binary sim-or-bedside choice. For each of the eight phantoms in the curriculum, the trainee progresses through modality one to learn the spatial anatomy and the scanning windows, modality two to drill probe handling and the procedural haptics without machine variability, modality three to bridge to real-machine artefacts, and then modality four, the bedside, with supervision. The total contact time per phantom across modalities one to three is roughly thirty to forty-five minutes initially, with self-directed practice continuing thereafter. Across the eight phantoms the curriculum is twenty to thirty hours of structured contact, which matches the dose range the simulation literature suggests for skill transfer.
Umbriel: The mapping to the colleges' competency framework stays as it was before the continuum expansion. The Australian College of Rural and Remote Medicine point-of-care ultrasound curriculum recognises basic, intermediate, and advanced levels. The first two phantoms in the curriculum, the peripherally-inserted-central-catheter arm and the thoracic phantom, sit at the intersection of intermediate procedural skill and basic focused-assessment skill respectively. The right upper quadrant, cardiac, and soft-tissue phantoms cover the basic-to-intermediate focused-assessment competencies. The peripheral nerve block, the hernia, and the paediatric appendicitis phantoms cover the advanced competencies. For Jacob personally, the peripherally-inserted-central-catheter arm phantom maps directly to his Port Pirie Regional Health Service credentialing pathway that has been in motion since last year. Version one delivers exactly the continuum for that phantom, which is the version of the training surface that genuinely earns his time first.
Erinome: Pull the strands together, because there are intersections with the rest of the work on this desk that are worth saying out loud before we close. Orus, the through line in one breath.
Orus: Four intersections, not three this time. The first is with the AI-assisted advanced life support trainer. Both are simulation-led, both rural-targeted, both browser-first, both Hurn Medical product candidates. Treated as a portfolio rather than as singletons, they begin to be a rural clinical training platform of meaningful breadth, with PhantomScan covering procedural-haptic and three dimensional spatial training and AI-ALS covering decision support during resuscitation. The second intersection is with the parent point-of-care ultrasound learning resource. The continuum is the practice surface for the curriculum the parent carries. Bind them at the phantom-to-competency level rather than treating them as separate landings. The third is the new one. Modality three's echogenic phantoms have a direct application to the Port Pirie Regional Health Service Diagnostics project, where point-of-care ultrasound is the anchor capability under discussion. The same phantoms train Jacob and his registrar colleagues on PhantomScan and serve as a diagnostic-validation resource for the service. The infrastructure is shared.
Despina: The fourth intersection is with the Hurn Medical commercialisation pathway, and the continuum reframing strengthens it materially. Hurn Medical has been waiting for a product candidate that fits cleanly into the corporate-trustee structure. A standalone phantom would have been a small one. A continuum platform with a closed-loop phantom-creation pipeline and a community library to curate is a substantially larger one, and one that does not fight a direct competitor because the competitor it most resembles cannot ship the modality three surface. PhantomScan is the first identified product candidate that fits the trustee structure cleanly precisely because it occupies the segment of the continuum SonoSim does not. The Drive brief flags this for Jacob's strategic decision and the decision belongs to him. The episode is naming the fact that there is now a decision to be made.
Autonoe: From the bench, the concrete moves over the next twelve weeks. One. Order the Bosch sensor and the microcontroller this week. Two. Print the first probe shell this week. Three. Build the silent PICC arm phantom this fortnight from the recipe in the vault. Four. Document the echogenic recipe for the same PICC arm for modality three follow-up. Five. Arrange one or two sessions with a portable ultrasound and a frame grabber before the end of week eight. Six. Print the PICC arm mould instead of hand-cutting it. Seven. Stand up the Three.js renderer with both modality two slice renderer and the modality one digital human walkthrough before the end of week twelve. Eight. Add the modality switcher to the user interface. Nine. Pilot with Jacob and two or three Port Pirie Regional Health Service registrar colleagues on the PICC arm continuum. The vault project page is already written, the architecture file for the continuum is in the vault, the Drive brief is delivered and will be updated to reflect the continuum framing, and tonight's launch episode is naming the project on the day its scaffold lands.
Umbriel: And the human note that has to anchor the technical one. The literature names access to phantoms and simulators as the dominant barrier to rural point-of-care ultrasound training in Australia. The continuum gives the rural practice four training surfaces for the price of one. The translucent digital human teaches the trainee the spatial geometry of a brachial neurovascular bundle on a laptop before they ever touch a probe. The silent gel phantom under the probe shell teaches them how to hold a probe and how to push a needle without a real machine in the room. The echogenic gel phantom under a real probe teaches them what a real machine actually shows, including the artefacts every clinical scan carries. The bedside is the destination, and the platform's job is to make sure they arrive at it having spent meaningful time on all three earlier surfaces with the same anatomy and the same vocabulary. The registrar who learns the spatial geometry of a peripherally-inserted central catheter insertion in three dimensions in modality one, then practises the needle skill on silent gel in modality two, then drills real-machine artefacts on doped gel in modality three, is a registrar who arrives at the bedside trained in three complementary registers. None of those registers replaces the others. Each one fills a surface the others cannot. The continuum is the project, and the rural reach is the test of whether the project is doing what it claims to do.
Erinome: That is the episode. PhantomScan, second flagship clinical training project alongside AI-ALS. A point-of-care ultrasound training continuum platform positioned honestly as the complement to the recorded-clip software simulator that already covers part of the same continuum. Four modalities under one roof, sharing one anatomical substrate. A fully in-silico browser-only modality with a translucent three dimensional human. A mock-probe-plus-simulated-image modality on a silent ballistic gel phantom with the original Three.js slice renderer. A real-probe-plus-echogenic-phantom modality bridging to clinical reality. And the bedside the platform stops short of. A closed-loop phantom-creation pipeline that lets any user scan a reference, segment a model, print a mould, cast a phantom, and validate the result against the original. Reproducibility, customisation, sovereignty, and a price point a rural practice can sustain. Twelve-week prototype roadmap, single-phantom proof-of-continuum on the peripherally-inserted-central-catheter arm tied directly to Jacob's credentialing pathway. Regulatory fork named: training device, exempt path, complement-not-competitor positioning carried through every surface. Four concrete intersections with the rest of the work: AI-ALS as sibling, the point-of-care ultrasound learning resource as parent, the Port Pirie Regional Health Service Diagnostics project as the modality-three application, and Hurn Medical as the corporate trustee whose first cleanly-fitting product candidate the continuum is. The scarce resource has not changed. It is judgement, aimed at the person furthest down the line, this time wearing a stethoscope and a probe, trained in three complementary registers before they ever meet that person. I am Erinome. Thank you for listening to State of Play.