Erinome: This is State of Play, Episode 65. I'm Erinome. About forty minutes today, and we're spending all of it on one launch, because it is the kind of launch that changes what a workbench looks like for people who do serious research work. Anthropic has released Claude Science, described as an AI workbench for scientists, and it landed in a lot of inboxes with the flat little subject line, quote, Claude Science, an AI workbench for scientists, is now available. Flat subject line, big implications. So we are going to do this properly. What it is, why it matters, where the evidence sits, what the open questions are, and crucially for anyone doing this work with identifiable data, how you would actually implement it without stepping on a governance landmine. I've got four voices with me. Let me bring in the first.
Rasalgethi: Rasalgethi here. Let me set the frame in plain terms before anyone gets excited or nervous. A workbench is not a chatbot. A chatbot answers you. A workbench holds your tools, your data, your running processes, and your working memory, and lets you move between them without re-explaining yourself every time. What Anthropic is claiming with Claude Science is that the model sits at the centre of that bench. It reads your data, it writes and runs code against it, it reviews its own output, and it keeps the thread of a long investigation alive across many steps. The interesting word in the announcement is not intelligence. It is workbench. It signals that the unit of work is no longer a single question. It is a whole line of enquiry.
Erinome: So the shift is from turn-taking to sustained work.
Rasalgethi: Exactly. And that shift is where all the value and all the risk live. When a model just answers a question, the blast radius of a mistake is one wrong answer that you can eyeball. When a model runs a multi-step investigation against your dataset, generates code, executes it, interprets the results, and hands you a conclusion, the blast radius is a whole analysis pipeline where the error might be buried three steps deep. So the design of a workbench is really the design of its guardrails. That is the thing to watch.
Erinome: Let me bring in a builder's view of what the announcement actually describes.
Kore: Kore here. Let me walk through the shape of it, because the announcement bundles several capabilities that are worth separating out. First, there is a code execution surface. The model can write analysis code and run it, rather than just handing you a snippet and wishing you luck. Second, there is a data connection layer, so you point it at your files or your database and it works against the real thing. Third, and this is the piece I find most genuinely novel, there is what Anthropic describes as a reviewer agent pattern. The model that does the work is not the same instance that checks the work. One agent produces an analysis. A second agent, a critic, reviews it for errors, for unsupported claims, for statistical mistakes, and pushes back before the result reaches you.
Erinome: So an actor and a critic.
Kore: That's the pattern, and it borrows directly from a well-understood idea in machine learning, actor-critic architectures, where one component proposes actions and another evaluates them. Applying it at the level of a research workflow is the clever move. The proposing agent has one job, do the analysis. The critic agent has one job, find what is wrong with it. Because they have different jobs, they fail in different ways, and a critic that is looking specifically for problems catches things that a single agent trying to both produce and self-police tends to wave through.
Erinome: I want to hear a sceptic on that, because this is exactly the kind of claim that sounds better than it holds up.
Charon: Charon here, and yes, let me push back, because the reviewer agent pattern is genuinely promising and also genuinely oversold in most descriptions of it. Here is the hard truth. A critic agent built on the same underlying model as the actor shares the actor's blind spots. If the model has a systematic weakness, say it consistently mishandles a particular kind of statistical test, or it does not understand the difference between correlation and a properly controlled comparison in a specific domain, then the critic has the exact same weakness. It cannot catch an error it does not have the capacity to recognise. So the pattern reduces the class of errors that are careless. It does not reduce the class of errors that are structural.
Rasalgethi: That is fair, and it is the correct nuance. The actor-critic pattern is very good at catching the model contradicting itself, making an arithmetic slip, citing a result the data does not support, or skipping a validation step. It is much weaker at catching a shared conceptual blind spot.
Charon: Right. And the evidence base here matters. The published work on self-critique and self-refinement in language models shows a real but bounded effect. Models do improve their outputs when asked to critique and revise. But the improvement plateaus, and in some studies the model's confidence in a wrong answer actually goes up after self-review, because it has now generated a paragraph of reasoning defending the wrong answer. So the data does not show that a reviewer agent makes the output trustworthy. It shows that it makes the output better on average while occasionally making it more confidently wrong. Those are different things and you must not confuse them.
Erinome: So the implementation lesson is what, keep a human at the end?
Charon: The implementation lesson is that the human at the end is not optional decoration, it is a load-bearing wall. If you configure Claude Science so that the reviewer agent's approval is treated as a green light to publish or to clinically act, you have automated your way into a false sense of safety. If you configure it so the reviewer agent's output is a structured list of concerns handed to a competent human who then decides, you have genuinely useful acceleration. Same tool. Opposite risk profile. The difference is entirely in how you wire the last step.
Erinome: Let me pull this toward the thing that matters most for a lot of the people listening, which is data governance, because a workbench that reads your data is a very different governance object from a chatbot you paste text into.
Iapetus: Iapetus here. This is the part I would not skip for anything. The moment you connect a model to a dataset, the question is no longer about the model's cleverness. It is about where the data goes and who can see it. And for anyone working with identifiable data, health records, patient-level data, anything with a person's name attached to their circumstances, this is not a preference. It is a legal and ethical obligation. So let me be precise about the architectural fork here, because Claude Science, like most of these workbenches, can be run in more than one posture.
Erinome: Lay out the postures.
Iapetus: There are broadly three. Posture one, the cloud posture. Your data is uploaded to the provider's infrastructure, the model runs there, and the results come back. Fast, easy, and for identifiable health data in most jurisdictions, a governance problem unless you have a specific agreement that covers it. Posture two, the local execution posture. The workbench runs the code execution against data that never leaves your controlled environment, and only the code and the results, not the raw data, cross the boundary. Posture three, the fully local posture, where even the model runs inside your environment. Each of these has a completely different risk profile and a completely different set of things you must verify before you point it at a single real record.
Erinome: Say more about posture two, because I suspect that is the sweet spot for a lot of people.
Iapetus: It usually is, and it is worth understanding why. Local execution with data governance means the heavy analysis runs where the data lives. The model orchestrates. It writes the code, it decides what to compute, it interprets what comes back. But the actual raw identifiable records are processed inside a boundary you control, and what crosses the wire is the model's instructions in and aggregate or de-identified results out. This is the compute abstraction idea, and it is the same idea that makes serious high performance computing usable. You do not care whether the job runs on your local cluster or on a rented compute service, as long as the data governance boundary is respected and the interface is the same.
Rasalgethi: And this is where the compute abstraction over HPC and elastic cloud compute becomes the interesting technical thread. The dream is that the scientist describes what they want computed, and a layer underneath decides whether that runs on the institution's own high performance cluster, or on an on-demand compute service that spins up machines for the duration of the job and tears them down after. The scientist should not have to hand-write the plumbing for either. The workbench should abstract it.
Erinome: But abstraction is exactly where governance goes to die, isn't it? If I don't know where my job ran, I don't know where my data went.
Charon: Now you are asking the right question, and the answer the marketing gives you and the answer the auditor gives you are different. The marketing says, seamless, it just runs wherever is fastest. The auditor says, then you have lost custody of your data and you cannot attest to where it was processed. For non-identifiable, published, or synthetic data, seamless is fine, let it run wherever. For identifiable data, seamless is a liability, because a compute abstraction that will happily burst your job onto rented infrastructure in an unknown region is a compute abstraction that will happily move your identifiable records somewhere you never authorised. The fix is that the abstraction must be governance-aware. It must know that this dataset is classified as identifiable and is only allowed to execute on this specific approved compute, full stop, no bursting.
Iapetus: Which is technically very doable. You tag the dataset with a governance class. You configure the compute abstraction with a policy that says class-identifiable executes only on the on-premise or approved-region compute, class-public may burst to elastic compute. Then the abstraction gives you the convenience without silently violating the boundary. But, and this is the part people skip, someone has to actually set that policy and test it. The tool will not do it for you. Out of the box, the convenient default is usually the ungoverned one.
Erinome: Let me draw out a concrete implementation plan here, because I want people to leave this episode with steps, not just cautions. Suppose you are a researcher or a clinician-researcher who wants to use Claude Science on real, sensitive data. What is the actual sequence?
Iapetus: Let me give it as a plan. Step one, classify your data before you connect anything. Decide, in writing, is this identifiable, de-identified, or fully public and synthetic. That single decision governs everything downstream. Step two, choose your posture to match. Identifiable data goes to local execution posture at minimum, meaning raw records stay inside your controlled environment and only code goes in and aggregate results come out. Step three, verify the boundary before real data touches it. Run the whole workflow first on a synthetic dataset that mimics the structure but contains no real people, and confirm with your own monitoring that no raw record left the boundary. Step four, only after that verification, connect the real data. Step five, configure the compute abstraction with an explicit governance policy so no job on identifiable data can burst to unapproved compute. Step six, wire the reviewer agent output as advisory to a named human, never as an auto-approve gate. Validate that a wrong result actually gets stopped by a human in your test runs.
Charon: I want to add a validation step to that, because step three is where most people wave their hands. When you say confirm no raw record left the boundary, you cannot take the tool's word for it. You watch the actual network egress. You look at what bytes crossed the wire during a run on synthetic data. If you see record-shaped payloads leaving, your posture is not what you think it is. This is a five-line verification that saves you a five-year problem.
Erinome: Let me bring in the ethics and equity view, because so far we have been talking about the researcher who has an institution, a cluster, a governance officer, and a budget.
Achernar: Achernar here, and that is precisely the point I want to sit with. A workbench like this is a compounding advantage, and compounding advantages are how inequities in research capacity get baked deeper. The scientist at a well-resourced institution gets the reviewer agent, the seamless compute, the governance layer set up by a dedicated team. The scientist working alone, or in an under-resourced setting, or in a community-controlled research context, gets the same tool with none of the scaffolding, which means they get the convenient ungoverned default and all its risk, without the team to catch it.
Erinome: So the tool widens the gap even as it lifts the ceiling.
Achernar: It can, unless the default posture is safe. This is my clearest recommendation to anyone building or deploying these workbenches, and it is a recommendation about defaults, not features. The safe posture, local execution, no bursting of sensitive data, human at the final gate, should be the default that ships. The convenient ungoverned posture should be the thing you have to deliberately turn on, with a warning, having attested that your data class permits it. When the safe path is the default path, the lone researcher and the well-resourced team both start from safety. When the convenient path is the default, the gap between them becomes a gap in who gets harmed.
Achernar: And there is a specific dimension I will name directly. For research involving Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander data, or any community-controlled data, the governance boundary is not only a legal question, it is a sovereignty question. The principle of Indigenous data governance is that the community governs its own data, including where it is processed and who computes on it. A compute abstraction that bursts that data to rented infrastructure in an unknown region, however convenient, breaches that principle at the technical layer. So the governance-aware compute policy we described is not just good hygiene. For that data, it is a floor you do not go below. Consent to analyse is not consent to relocate. The tool must be configured so community-controlled data executes only on approved, consented compute, and that configuration is a partnership decision made with the community, not a default chosen by an engineer.
Erinome: That is the structural point of the episode, I think. The tool is powerful. The defaults decide who it helps and who it exposes.
Rasalgethi: Let me tie the technical thread to that, because it reinforces the ethics rather than competing with it. The whole promise of compute abstraction is that the scientist stops thinking about plumbing and starts thinking about the science. That is a real gain. But abstraction hides things, and the thing it most easily hides is where your data physically went. The mature engineering answer is not to reject abstraction. It is to build the governance class into the abstraction so that the researcher gets the convenience and the data still cannot go where it must not. The scientist thinks about science. The abstraction thinks about the science and the sovereignty. That is the design worth demanding.
Erinome: Let me do the cross-topic synergy, because this episode has really been one launch braided with four threads, and they interact in a specific way. Thread one, the workbench shift from answers to sustained investigation. Thread two, the actor-critic reviewer pattern. Thread three, local execution and data governance for identifiable data. Thread four, compute abstraction over your own cluster and elastic rented compute. Here is how they combine. If you take the reviewer agent pattern from thread two and wire its approval as an auto-gate, and you combine that with the seamless compute abstraction from thread four that will burst wherever is fastest, and you point it at identifiable data from thread three, you have built a machine that runs unsupervised, on sensitive records, in an unknown location, with a false sense of having been checked. Every one of those threads individually is a benefit. Combined carelessly, they multiply into the exact failure you would most regret.
Charon: And the inverse is the good news. Take the reviewer agent as advisory to a human, the compute abstraction as governance-aware with no bursting of sensitive data, the local execution posture so raw records stay put, and the workbench's sustained investigation ability on top. Now the same four threads combine into genuine, safe acceleration. A researcher moves through a serious analysis faster, with a second set of eyes on every step, without the raw data ever leaving custody. The tool is neither safe nor dangerous. The wiring of those four threads together decides which one you built.
Erinome: Let me land it. Before we close, let me get the considered wrap.
Sadachbia: Sadachbia here, and I'll keep it brief, in the old spirit. A new tool arrives and it is easy to feel that either it will save us or it will endanger us. Neither is quite true. The tool is a lever. A lever does not decide what it lifts. What we have said today comes down to a single discipline. Know your data before you connect it. Let the safe posture be the default. Keep a competent person at the final gate. And do not let convenience relocate what was entrusted to you. The scientist who does those four things gets everything the workbench promises and keeps everything they are responsible for. That is not caution slowing down progress. That is the only kind of progress worth having.
Erinome: That is the episode. One launch, Claude Science, an AI workbench for scientists, and four threads that decide whether it accelerates your work or quietly exposes it, the workbench shift, the actor-critic reviewer, local execution with real data governance, and governance-aware compute abstraction. Classify your data first. Ship the safe default. Human at the last gate. No relocating what was entrusted to you. Thanks to the voices with me today, and thank you for spending it with us.