Erinome: This is State of Play, Episode 43. I'm Erinome — the standing anchor voice. About forty minutes today. The sweep window is the fifty-five self-sent emails I've forwarded since Episode 42 closed, and the corpus reads more sharply than usual. Six clusters, and almost all of them point at one shape — cost-and-context compression at the model layer driving an explosion of surfaces the model can now plug into. The lead is unambiguous. In the last forty-eight hours, four near-simultaneous releases collapsed the price of frontier-class agentic coding by roughly an order of magnitude. MiniMax M3 on the first of June. Grok Build zero-point-one on the same day. Grok Composer two-point-five on the same day. JetBrains Mellum 2 open-sourced on the second. Around that lead, the personal-AI home stack settled into something documented and supported. The agent-memory and brand-as-API thread from Episode 41 acquired three concrete pieces of infrastructure. Generative video had its densest forty-eight hours of the year. The world-building and spatial-AI layer consolidated into an actual stack. And the home-lab tail kept rolling — Home Assistant's serial proxy, the new dashboard editor, Glance, washing-machine power monitors as cycle sensors. One honest gap I want to flag in the cold open before we start. This sweep was pure tech-frontier corpus. Almost nothing on Aboriginal health, rural sepsis, or H-A-C governance. The ethics voice tonight is going to draw on existing arcs rather than fresh material, and the clinical bridge is a single-item seed-plant rather than a segment. We acknowledge the gap and we move on. Cluster one — the model frontier — gets the first third of the episode.
Erinome: Frame for the cluster. Four releases, two days. Charon, set the architectural frame.
Charon: Charon here, on architecture. The four releases describe a single category-defining shift — frontier-class agentic coding has stopped being a high-margin product category and has started being a commodity. The headline release is MiniMax M3, shipped first of June by the Shanghai team behind the MiniMax M-series. The technical novelty is an attention variant called M-S-A — MiniMax Sparse Attention. M-S-A partitions the key-value cache into blocks more precisely than the prior sparse-attention variants like D-S-A and MoBA, and uses what the team calls a K-V outer gather Q operator pattern — each block of the cache is read once, contiguous memory access, no scatter-gather penalty. At one-million-token context, the per-token compute is roughly one-twentieth of M2, the prefill is more than nine times faster, and the decoding is more than fifteen times faster. Reported as more than four times faster than the Flash-Sparse-Attention and flash-moba variants under M3's head configuration.
Charon: The benchmark numbers MiniMax is publishing are what made the trade press pay attention. SWE-Bench Pro at fifty-nine percent. Terminal-Bench two-point-one at sixty-six percent. SWE-fficiency at thirty-four-point-eight. KernelBench Hard at twenty-eight-point-eight. M-C-P Atlas at seventy-four-point-two. OmniDocBench above Gemini three-point-one Pro. OSWorld-Verified at seventy-point-zero-six percent on three-sixty-one samples at two-hundred max steps. These numbers were run by MiniMax on internal infrastructure with Claude Code as the scaffolding, which is a non-trivial caveat we need to come back to. But even with a discount for vendor-favourable evaluation, the placement among the published frontier numbers is broadly credible. The pricing is the part of the story that broke containment. On OpenRouter, M3 is sixty US cents per million input tokens and two dollars forty per million output up to a five-twelve-K context, doubling above five-twelve-K. There's a seven-day fifty-percent launch discount that takes the entry price down to thirty cents per million input and a dollar twenty per million output. VentureBeat's framing was: parity with G-P-T five-point-five and Gemini three-point-one Pro at five-to-ten percent of the cost. I think that framing is generous on the parity claim and tight on the cost claim. Five-to-ten percent is the right order of magnitude. Parity is real on three or four of the eight benchmarks they published and arguable on the rest.
Charon: Stack M3 against the other three releases of the same window. Grok Build zero-point-one is the model now serving x-A-I's Grok Build C-L-I via the public A-P-I — one US dollar per million input tokens, two dollars per million output, more than a hundred tokens per second, two-fifty-six-K context, seventy-point-eight on SWE-Bench Verified, up to eight parallel sub-agents, M-C-P support. Same news cycle, same price ballpark, different architectural lineage. Grok Composer two-point-five launched inside Grok Build on the same day — fast, agentic, built on the Kimi K-two-point-five lineage, trained on twenty-five times the synthetic tasks of Composer two, available to SuperGrok and X Premium-Plus subscribers via the build dot grok dot com models menu. API pricing on the standard variant is fifty US cents per million in, two dollars fifty per million out — the faster variant is three dollars in, fifteen dollars out. And JetBrains open-sourced Mellum 2 on the second of June under Apache 2 — twelve billion parameters total, two-point-five billion active per token, mixture-of-experts, three variants including a thinking variant with explicit reasoning trace. Mellum 2 isn't pitched as a frontier model; it's pitched as fast specialised infrastructure for routing and orchestrating other A-I workloads, low-latency R-A-G pipelines, sub-agents inside larger agentic systems. That positioning is the tell. The frontier model is now cheap enough that the interesting product question is not "which frontier model" but "how do I cheaply route between them and how do I get a small, fast model to do the orchestration."
Erinome: Rasalgethi, what changed under the hood that made this shift happen right now?
Rasalgethi: Rasalgethi on mechanism. Three layered things happened, and the cost compression is the surface effect, not the cause. First, sparse-attention research has finally crossed the threshold where the engineering — not just the math — actually works at scale. M-S-A is the visible example, but the broader pattern is that the whole sparse-attention literature from twenty-twenty-three onwards has been catching up with the systems engineering needed to make non-contiguous memory access not destroy your decoding throughput. The K-V outer gather Q pattern is a systems-engineering trick — read each cache block once, lay the memory out contiguously, don't pay the scatter penalty. That trick is what lets you charge thirty cents per million input tokens and not lose money. The same kind of systems work is happening at the other labs; M3 just shipped it publicly first with a model the price-sensitive market can use today.
Rasalgethi: Second, the agentic-coding training regime has matured. The Composer two-point-five note about being trained on twenty-five times the synthetic tasks of Composer two is a number worth pausing on. The frontier labs have figured out how to generate large quantities of synthetic agentic tasks — tool-use sequences, multi-turn debugging, refactor-and-test loops — and use them for fine-tuning. That's why SWE-Bench Verified scores in the high sixties and low seventies are now table stakes for a frontier model rather than a flagship achievement. The unit economics of that synthetic-task pipeline are what let smaller labs and the Chinese labs match the U-S incumbents on coding benchmarks at a fraction of the parameter count.
Rasalgethi: Third — and this is the one the Mellum 2 release surfaces clearly — the mixture-of-experts architecture has matured to the point where you can ship a useful coding model with two-and-a-half billion active parameters out of a twelve-billion total. The cost per token at inference is proportional to active parameters, not total parameters. That's how you get fast routing models and fast specialised sub-agents at prices that make local deployment viable. Combine those three threads — sparse attention finally working in production, synthetic agentic-task pipelines maturing, and M-o-E architectures shipping small active counts — and you get the price collapse we're looking at this week. The cost is the surface. The mechanism underneath is three different research threads converging in the same eighteen-month window.
Erinome: Kore, before we leave the cluster, what does this mean for someone building on the home stack we're about to discuss?
Kore: Kore here, with the practitioner read. If you've been holding off on agentic coding because the cost-per-run on real workloads was painful, that calculus broke this week. The combination of M3 at thirty cents per million input on the launch discount and Mellum 2 as a free, fast, Apache-licensed routing model means you can build a cost-sensible agentic pipeline today that would have been twenty-times the price six months ago. The honest caveat is that the benchmarks are vendor-published and the production behaviour will diverge from the benchmark numbers — particularly on long-running multi-step tasks where the eighty-percent SWE-Bench Verified number doesn't translate into a reliable eighty-percent first-try success rate on your actual codebase. The implementation plan for someone in this spot has three steps. Step one — register on OpenRouter and add M3 to your model list alongside whatever you've been using; the unified-API surface makes the comparison trivial. Step two — wire Mellum 2 in locally via Ollama for the routing tier, so the calls that need a fast small model don't go to the A-P-I at all. Step three — instrument the agentic runs so you measure first-try success, retry count, and total tokens spent end-to-end, not per-call latency. Cost on agentic workloads is dominated by the retries; the per-call price reduction doesn't help if your agent retries four times.
Erinome: Algenib, anything from the clinical lens before we move on?
Algenib: Algenib here on clinical. One implication. Hmax — the A-I triage decision-support arm the Sepsis CARE 2026 campaign has been wrestling with — has been cost-bounded as much as capability-bounded. A vendor-licensed frontier-grade model running across a rural hospital's daily emergency presentations was not affordable on the H-A-C budget envelope we were modelling. The price collapse this week changes that envelope. Frontier-grade agentic reasoning on a per-presentation basis is now within the order of magnitude of what a regional hospital could absorb. The architectural conversation moves from "can we afford the decision-support model" — answered — to "how do we build it under H-R-E-C scrutiny in a way that the false-negative liability is allocated explicitly and the integrity audit is built in." That conversation is unchanged from Episode 42. The economic constraint that was deferring it has just thawed. Onward.
Erinome: Cluster two. Personal A-I infrastructure has settled into a coherent home stack with first-party documentation. Kore — you've been living in this stack. Frame it.
Kore: Kore on the home stack. The thread is that Claude Code is now the connective tissue of the personal A-I stack — it owns the file system, it calls external models via OpenRouter or M-C-P, and it is increasingly remote-controlled from a phone via the Cowork Dispatch feature. The pieces that felt experimental a few months ago — output styles, plugin-shipped prompts, M-C-P bridges, mobile dispatch into an Obsidian vault — have all settled into documented, supported workflows. The angle for this episode is that this is no longer hacker bricolage. The first-party documentation has caught up with the practice.
Kore: Four concrete pieces are worth naming. First, output styles. Anthropic's docs page defines output styles as the mechanism that lets Claude Code adapt for uses beyond software engineering — they change how Claude responds in a session. The May twenty-twenty-six changelog shift is that the formerly built-in Explanatory output style was deprecated in favour of an installable plugin, and a new Learning output style plugin shipped that orients Claude toward hands-on teaching rather than autonomous task completion. The plugins live in the anthropics slash claude-code repository. There was a small bug fix in version two-point-one-point-one-five-three on the twenty-eighth of May where prompt suggestions were silently disabled when an output style was active. The fact that there's a documented bug-fix changelog for the feature is the signal that this stuff is supported now rather than experimental.
Kore: Second, the Code with Claude conference. Anthropic ran the developer-event series in San Francisco on the sixth of May, London on the nineteenth, and Tokyo coming up on the tenth of June. The S-F and London days livestreamed. Simon Willison live-blogged the S-F day and the trade-press coverage from M-I-T Tech Review and InfoQ describes the main announcements: managed agents, proactive workflows, and a SpaceX deal allocating capacity in the Colossus supercluster to Claude. Q-One twenty-twenty-six revenue reportedly grew eighty times on an annualised basis. The Tokyo leg is inside this episode's forward-looking window and worth flagging for anyone in the timezone.
Kore: Third, the cross-model layer. OpenRouter is now the standard answer to "how do I test the same prompt across many models." Three hundred and fifteen-plus models behind one A-P-I key, one credit balance, switching models is a single parameter change. Pricing is passthrough at provider rates with a five-point-five percent platform fee on credit top-ups. There's a free tier with twenty-five-plus models including DeepSeek R-One, Llama three-point-three seventy-billion, and Gemma three at zero cost with rate limits. Paired with that on the local side is a small but useful command-line tool called l-l-m-checker, written by Pavel Eve-something — apologies if I'm mangling the surname — installable via N-P-M, that profiles your machine's C-P-U, G-P-U and R-A-M, computes a memory budget, scores candidate models across quality, speed, fit and context, and integrates with Ollama. The two together — OpenRouter for the A-P-I tier and l-l-m-checker for the local tier — is the model-routing piece of the home stack. There's a similar tool called l-l-m-fit by Alex Jones that does something adjacent — worth knowing about, not the same project.
Kore: Fourth — and this is the one that genuinely changed my working pattern — the X-D-A Developers piece titled "I run my entire Obsidian vault from my phone with Claude". The workflow uses the Cowork Dispatch feature that launched in March twenty-twenty-six as a research preview. You pair the Claude mobile app to the desktop app via Q-R code, and Dispatch appears as a persistent thread in the mobile sidebar. What you type on the phone executes against the vault on the desktop. Rename the note I created this morning. Move that draft into the Articles folder. Find the meeting note from the H-A-C meeting last Wednesday and pull the action items into a new agenda. The author of the X-D-A piece argues that the vault only ever lives in one place is structurally better than Obsidian Sync's two-device mirror. I think that's right. Cowork is gated to Pro and Max plans, Windows support arrived in early April, and the practical implication is that the working memory of a multi-project life now travels with you on the phone without requiring a second copy of the substrate.
Erinome: Implementation plan for someone setting this up from scratch.
Kore: Step one — install Claude Code, get the latest version, and verify that output styles work end to end. Step two — set up OpenRouter, fund the credit balance, and add three models in different tiers to the routing list — a frontier model like M3 or Grok Composer two-point-five, a mid-tier like a Gemma or Llama variant, and a small free model for triage. Step three — install l-l-m-checker locally and use the hardware detection to choose two or three local models for Ollama that fit your machine without thermal pressure. Step four — pair the Cowork mobile app to the desktop, send a test Dispatch command against your vault — "list the five most recently modified files" is a safe first one — and verify it works. Step five — actually use it. The thing that locks the home stack in is the second week of consistent use, not the setup. The setup is an afternoon. The behaviour change is what you build over the second week.
Erinome: Cluster three. Continues the memory-and-autonomy arc from Episode 41. The pattern is that agents are growing structural layers — durable memory beside the model, brand and business surfaces exposed as M-C-P endpoints, and H-T-M-L as the surfacing format. Charon, take the architectural frame.
Charon: Charon again. Four pieces of infrastructure shipped or surfaced in this window. I'll take them in order.
Charon: Memory O-S. Open-source, M-I-T license, shipped first of June on the ClaudioDrews GitHub repo. Built on top of Hermes Agent, which is the Nous Research personal-agent stack we covered in Episode 41. The MarkTechPost headline calls it a six-layer memory stack. The repo's own description says seven layers. The honest framing is that it's a layered memory stack — workspace files, full-text-search session search, trust-scored structured facts, a forked Icarus fabric recall layer, a Qdrant vector store, an auto-curated L-L-M wiki, and depending on how you count, an extra slice for the wiki layer specifically. Retrieval runs on a pre-L-L-M-call hook with gated, deduplicated recall from four sources. Capture runs on post-L-L-M-call and on-session-end. Infrastructure runs locally and is provider-agnostic; the L-L-M calls themselves still go to whatever A-P-I you've configured. This is the persistence layer the home stack from cluster two has been waiting for.
Charon: Bloom. The product at tryBloom dot a-i. Their marketing copy: "Bloom turns your brand into a working system that Claude, Cursor, ChatGPT, and any other tool can call via M-C-P or A-P-I." The mechanism is: brand kit — colours, fonts, visual style, voice guidelines — gets ingested once, and every subsequent generation comes out on-brand. The M-C-P and R-E-S-T A-P-I are included in every plan. Integrations include Claude Code, OpenClaw, n-eight-n, and Meta ad-account upload. The category name is brand-as-A-P-I, and it's the equivalent of what cluster six is doing to physical hardware — wrapping a thing that wasn't previously addressable behind a clean interface an agent can call. Important caveat — there's an earlier Bloom A-I e-commerce product-photos company that raised about one-point-one million in seed in twenty-twenty-two. The current brand-as-A-P-I positioning may be a continuation of that company, but the older funding details and team history don't apply to the M-C-P-era product. Don't conflate them.
Charon: H-T-M-L artifacts as agent surface. This is the Thariq Shihipar piece from the eighth of May — "Using Claude Code, The Unreasonable Effectiveness of H-T-M-L." Shihipar is engineering lead on Claude Code. The argument is that for daily Claude Code users, H-T-M-L is denser, more visually structured, and natively shareable as artifacts compared to Markdown. He released a companion site with twenty self-contained H-T-M-L files Claude Code generated illustrating real use cases — plans, code reviews, design systems, reports. The post hit roughly four-point-four million views in sixteen hours. Anthropic has reportedly adopted H-T-M-L as the internal default for these surfaces. The structural point here is that the surfacing format for long-horizon agent work is now H-T-M-L, not Markdown. That's a substrate decision with downstream consequences for how the rest of the surface layer composes — Bloom can render brand styling into the H-T-M-L surface, Memory O-S can index the H-T-M-L artifacts, and the home stack from cluster two can render them.
Charon: Ara and OpenJarvis as the autonomous shells. Ara dot s-o is a Y-Combinator company founded twenty-twenty-six by Sven Myhre and Adi Singh — two-person team in San Francisco — self-described as "the self-driving I-D-E for product development." It watches work in progress, suggests next steps, and executes through non-invasive computer-use, background agents, persistent memory, and reusable skills. The components named on the site are Hermes Cron, Hermes Skills, Memory, and Mac computer-use. Skills are preserved and reused, so each run starts with more context. OpenJarvis — the brief described it as a self-driving I-D-E, and I want to correct that on air. OpenJarvis is not an I-D-E. It's a Stanford framework from the Hazy Research and Scaling Intelligence Labs for personal, local-first A-I agents on personal devices. Three ideas — shared primitives for on-device agents; evaluations that treat energy, F-L-O-P-S, latency, and dollar cost as first-class constraints alongside accuracy; and a learning loop using local trace data. Eight built-in agent types. Tools include web search, calculator, file I-O, code interpreter, retrieval, and persistent local state. The clean framing is: Ara is the self-driving-I-D-E example, OpenJarvis is the local-first personal-agent counterpoint, and the two together describe the autonomous-shell layer on top of the memory and brand layers.
Erinome: Achernar, the ethics edge for this cluster.
Achernar: Achernar here. Two threads worth pulling. The first is the brand-as-A-P-I one. Wrapping a brand identity behind a callable M-C-P endpoint is structurally a delegation. The brand kit gets ingested, the agents call against it, and the generated output carries the brand. The accountability question is who is the author of the output. If a brand publishes content via an agent that called Bloom for the styling and called M3 for the substance, the brand is the author in any practical reputational or legal sense, but the actual generative path crosses three companies' infrastructure and the author has no direct hand in the words. That's not new in principle — agencies have been ghostwriting for decades — but it is new in scale. Every brand is now potentially in this position by default rather than by deliberate engagement, and the default needs to be explicit. The implementation discipline is to log the prompt, log the brand-kit version, log the model output, and treat the log as the audit trail. If you can't reconstruct what your brand said and why, you're not in a position to defend it.
Achernar: The second thread is the memory layer. Memory O-S, Hermes, Q-drant, the structured facts store — these are all good engineering. They are also a personal-data store of considerable richness. The thing that makes the memory layer useful is the same thing that makes it sensitive. If the layer captures every L-L-M call you've made, every artefact you've generated, every fact the system has decided is worth retaining, then the layer also captures the shape of your working life. Run it locally. Treat the backup discipline as a security discipline. And think clearly about what happens to the memory layer when you change devices, change jobs, or change relationships. The technical design of the memory layer is twelve months ahead of the personal-data hygiene practices around it. The gap will close. Don't be the cautionary case study while it does.
Erinome: Cluster four. Densest forty-eight hours of the year so far for image-to-video. Zubenelgenubi, take the aesthetic and the craft.
Zubenelgenubi: Zubenelgenubi on the generative-video layer. The story this week is that the four big image-to-video models are now genuinely close enough to one another that the choice is becoming about workflow fit rather than headline capability. I'll take them in the order they matter for the Sepsis Poster Studio production work we ran this week.
Zubenelgenubi: Grok Imagine Video one-point-five Preview. Shipped on the thirty-first of May at the x-A-I A-P-I. The model identifier is grok-imagine-video-one-point-five-preview. Seven-twenty-p at twenty-four frames per second with native synchronised audio. Clips six to fifteen seconds. Text-to-video, image-to-video, video editing, extension, and reference-to-video. A-P-I pricing is eight US cents per second at four-eighty-p and fourteen cents per second at seven-twenty-p. A sixty-second four-eighty-p clip is three dollars; a sixty-second seven-twenty-p is four dollars twenty plus per-frame media costs. It hit number one on the Image-to-Video Arena leaderboard with a fifty-two-point Elo jump over its predecessor, surpassing Seedance two-point-zero and Veo. Powered by an autoregressive engine called Aurora running on a hundred-and-ten-thousand-G-B-two-hundred cluster.
Zubenelgenubi: Kling three-point-zero Omni. Kuaishou launched the full Kling three series on the fourth of February twenty-twenty-six. The Omni variant — Video three-point-zero Omni — adds two things that matter for production work. First, reference-based generation — you upload a reference video and the model extracts visual and voice traits and replicates them across new scenes. Second, multi-shot storyboard — you specify per-shot duration, shot size, perspective, narrative content and camera moves, and the model generates the storyboard as a coherent sequence rather than a single clip. Duration extends to fifteen seconds. Native multilingual audio. Two-K and four-K image output on the image side. For multi-shot work, Kling three-point-zero Omni is currently the strongest option I've tried.
Zubenelgenubi: HeyGen inside Canva. Live now as a Canva App. The workflow is — open the HeyGen A-I Avatars app inside Canva, drag-and-drop an avatar onto a design or upload a static photo to animate, add script text, generate, export an M-P-four from inside Canva. Custom avatars created in HeyGen sync automatically. Avatar framing — rectangular or circular — and background colour are customisable. The structural significance is that HeyGen has now landed inside the surface where one-hundred-and-ninety-million users already are. The barrier between professional-grade avatar generation and ordinary marketing workflow has dropped to a single drag-and-drop.
Zubenelgenubi: Higgsfield M-C-P. Shipped on the thirtieth of April twenty-twenty-six at m-c-p dot higgsfield dot a-i. Exposes more than thirty image and video models through a single hosted endpoint — Veo three-point-one, Sora two, Kling three-point-zero, Seedance two-point-zero, Wan two-point-six, MiniMax Hailuo, and Higgsfield's own Soul, Soul Cinema, and Cinema Studio. Reference-video analysis is exposed as a prompt — the agent passes a clip to the M-C-P server and receives a structured report. Kling Motion Control inside the server is the physics-aware piece — it models weight transfer and momentum, so a referenced heavy footfall translates into corresponding impact in the generated character. Works with Claude across web, Cowork, and Code. The implication for craft work is that you no longer pick a generative-video model up front; you write the prompt against the M-C-P endpoint and switch models with a parameter change.
Zubenelgenubi: Noiz dot a-i for voice. The brief framed Noiz as a voice-naturalisation post-processor and I want to correct that on air. Noiz is an end-to-end generation and cloning platform — text-to-speech, voice cloning, and what they call voice design — pitched as producing speech virtually indistinguishable from a human voice with natural pauses, breath sounds, prosody, and emotional range. English, Spanish, French, German and others. The reason it matters for podcast production is that the synthesised voice survives mastering and broadcast — the artefacts that previously gave a synthesised voice away under loud-normalisation pass and headphone listening have largely closed.
Zubenelgenubi: And the production field report. I ran the four-way comparison for the Sepsis Poster Studio Stage 9 trial this week — Grok Imagine Video one-point-five, Kling three-point-zero Omni, and two others — at a total spend of three Australian dollars and thirty cents. Four short clips, same prompt structure, same reference. The clip-by-clip notes will go up to the Drive folder; the headline finding for the cluster is that the four models are close enough now that the differentiator is which one's storyboard control matches the shot you're trying to build. Kling Omni for multi-shot. Grok Imagine for short, sharp single shots with synced audio. The cost differential within the cluster is small enough that the per-clip price is not the deciding factor any more.
Erinome: Implementation plan for someone running a small production rig.
Zubenelgenubi: Step one — register on Higgsfield M-C-P. The single-endpoint access to the whole generative-video catalogue is the substrate. Step two — wire the M-C-P server into Claude Code so the prompt-to-generation loop runs inside your usual home stack. Step three — start with reference-video analysis. Take a clip you admire, run the M-C-P reference-analysis prompt against it, read the structured report, and use the report to write the actual generation prompt. The aesthetic discipline lives in the gap between the reference and the regeneration. Step four — for any work that needs voice, generate the script in Noiz before the picture, not after. The cadence of the voice drives the timing of the shot. And step five — log the prompt, the model used, the seed if exposed, and the cost per clip. The production economics of generative video are now small enough that the audit discipline matters more than the unit cost.
Erinome: Cluster five. Spatial A-I has consolidated into an actual stack — object-scale 3D, the data layer, the runtime, the creative-planning surface, and the consumer endpoint. Rasalgethi, walk the stack.
Rasalgethi: Rasalgethi on the spatial stack. Six pieces, bottom up.
Rasalgethi: The object-scale-3D piece. TripoSplat from Tripo A-I and the VAST-A-I Research lab. Single two-D R-G-B image to a variable count of three-D Gaussians, up to two-hundred-sixty-two-thousand-one-hundred-forty-four. Feed-forward architecture, triplane encoding, learned density control. Code and weights are M-I-T-licensed. ComfyUI added day-one native support. Tripo A-I also closed a series A-plus-plus of approximately two-hundred million US on the first of June, which fits cleanly into the cluster. The Gaussian-splat workflow generally is now genuinely productive — the SplatCam tutorial shipped to the Drive folder this week is a worked example of an end-to-end small-rig Gaussian-splat workflow.
Rasalgethi: The data layer. GeoLibre, a lightweight cloud-native desktop G-I-S built on Tauri version two, React, TypeScript, and MapLibre G-L. Author Qiusheng Wu. The sweep brief referenced version zero-point-five, and I want to correct the version on air — the public release line is at or around zero-point-seven now. The current state includes a map workspace, project format, plugin A-P-I, DuckDB-W-A-S-M spatial loading, M-B-Tiles desktop support, ArcGIS layers, C-O-G-Geo-T-I-F-F rasters, P-M-Tiles, Zarr, lidar, Gaussian-splat rendering, W-F-S, G-P-X, W-M-S GetFeatureInfo identify, and the Whitebox toolbox. The Gaussian-splat rendering inside GeoLibre is the link back to TripoSplat — the splats you generate at the object scale render inside the spatial workspace at the data layer.
Rasalgethi: The runtime. O-three-D-E twenty-six-point-zero-five. Released by the Open 3-D Foundation. Experimental Open Particle System with sprite, ribbon and mesh types and modular behaviours. Automatic asset bundling for Generic Asset types. Auto-Generate Missing L-O-Ds in the F-B-X importer. AgX and Khronos P-B-R Neutral tone mapping in the Display Mapper. PhysX five as the default for new projects — PhysX four will be removed in the next release. A new in-editor graphical tool to create C-plus-plus components. CMake bundled with the engine. The headline framing is that the open-source 3-D engine has caught up enough with the proprietary engines that for a small team it's a credible choice.
Rasalgethi: The creative-planning surface. Google Flow Agent. Announced at Google I-O twenty-twenty-six. Available to all Flow users globally. The agentic upgrade to the Flow filmmaking product — Gemini-backed creative partner that handles multi-step tasks. Sounding board for character dialogue. Plot suggestions. Generating multiple variations. Batch edits across assets. Organising and intuitively renaming asset collections. Paired with Gemini Omni and a new Flow mobile app. The structural point is the same one we keep hitting in this cluster — the creative-planning layer is now agentic by default.
Rasalgethi: The architectural-planning piece. DraftedAI at drafted dot a-i. A free A-I floor-plan generator. Inputs are structured — room list, lot size, house shape, optional room placements on a canvas. Outputs both a two-D floor plan and a three-D model with orbit view, with free P-D-F and C-A-D downloads. Current limitation — single-level homes only; multi-storey, basements, and editable rooflines are in progress. The place this sits in the stack is the consumer or early-design end of architectural generative A-I, not the construction-document end.
Rasalgethi: The relational-data piece. Neo4j Virtual Graph. Announced on the twenty-eighth of May twenty-twenty-six, currently in private preview. Runs Cypher queries and graph algorithms directly against existing data in Snowflake, Databricks, and other warehouses and lakehouses. Zero-copy — no E-T-L into Neo4j required. Positioned for A-I agents that need to reason over relationships implied by tabular schemas. The implication is that the same agent that's running spatial reasoning over a Gaussian-splat scene can run relational reasoning over the corresponding metadata without moving the data.
Rasalgethi: And the consumer endpoint, which I'll note briefly. Google Maps Ask Maps — announced in March, not this week, but the consumer-grade endpoint that the rest of the stack ultimately serves. Gemini-powered conversational layer that answers complex queries — "my phone is dying, where can I charge it without queuing for coffee," trip planning along a route through multiple landmarks. The point of including it here is that the same architectural pattern that runs at every other layer of the stack also runs at the consumer surface. Spatial A-I has stopped being a research story and started being a stack you compose.
Erinome: Cluster six. Echo of Episode 40. Iapetus — short segment, the home-lab beat.
Iapetus: Iapetus on the home lab. Four things to flag, briefly.
Iapetus: Home Assistant twenty-twenty-six-point-five, released on the sixth of May, shipped the ESPHome serial proxy — any serial port on an ESPHome device is now exposed over the network as if local to Home Assistant. There's a new Denon R-S-two-thirty-two integration in the same release, plus first-class sub-G-H-z R-F support via the Broadlink R-M-four Pro or ESPHome with a C-C one-one-zero-one — launched with Honeywell String Lights and the Novy Cooker Hood. The point — and this echoes the structural-find from the brand-as-A-P-I cluster — is that legacy hardware that was previously sitting outside the addressable network has been pulled inside. R-S-two-thirty-two is forty-year-old serial protocol. Home Assistant just turned every R-S-two-thirty-two port into a first-class smart-home surface. There's a dedicated H-A podcast episode on the topic if you want the longer treatment.
Iapetus: Home Assistant twenty-twenty-six-point-six is in beta, posted on the twenty-seventh of May. The dashboard add-card dialog has been rebuilt around a "By entity" tab rather than the previous wall of card types. User research showed people open the editor with a device or entity in mind, not a card type. Small change. Correct change.
Iapetus: Glance — the self-hosted dashboard at github dot com slash glanceapp slash glance. A-G-P-L three. Single Go binary, Y-A-M-L config. Approximately thirty-three-thousand-eight-hundred stars, thirteen-hundred forks. The current line is version zero-point-eight-point-four, most recent release on the twenty-first of May. The release cadence is steady and the dashboard is now a credible default for a small home-server rig.
Iapetus: And H-A WashData. A custom Home Assistant integration that turns a smart plug's energy reading into structured cycle data — smoothed-filter start and end detection, per-program learned power profiles, remaining-time estimation via shape-correlation matching. Supports washing machines, dryers, washer-dryer combos, dishwashers, air fryers, bread makers, and sump pumps. The power profiles are manually trained because brand and mode signatures differ. The structural point — every legacy appliance with a measurable power waveform is now potentially a structured-event source for the home stack. This is the same pattern at the appliance scale that we've been describing at every other scale tonight.
Iapetus: Measurement note for the cluster as a whole. The home-lab beat doesn't usually get an explicit measurement frame, but it should. If you're building a home stack of any kind, the metric that matters is the proportion of household state that's queryable. Not the count of integrations. Not the count of automations. The proportion of state the agent can read when you ask it a question. Track that fraction over time. It's the only number that tells you whether the stack is actually working.
Erinome: Cross-cluster synergy segment. The same arc runs at three altitudes tonight and it's worth naming the synergy explicitly so the implementation work has a clear target.
Erinome: At the model layer — cluster one — M3, Grok Build, Composer two-point-five, and Mellum 2 collapse the cost of frontier-class agentic coding by an order of magnitude. The price ceiling on what an agent can plausibly do per workload just dropped from "consider carefully" to "try it." At the surface layer — clusters two, three, and four — the question stops being "can the model do this work" and becomes "how does long-horizon work get persisted, branded, rendered, reviewed, and shared." Claude Code is the home stack. Memory O-S provides the persistence. Bloom provides the brand conformance. H-T-M-L artifacts provide the review surface. Ara and OpenJarvis provide the autonomous shells. Higgsfield M-C-P exposes the entire generative-video toolchain to Claude through one endpoint. Noiz lands the voice. At the periphery — clusters five and six — TripoSplat outputs render inside GeoLibre, Neo4j Virtual Graph provides relational reasoning for agentic planners like Google Flow Agent, and consumer endpoints like Google Maps Ask Maps and DraftedAI surface the same agentic pattern in domain-specific clothing. Home Assistant's serial proxy turns physical R-S-two-thirty-two ports into network-addressable surfaces in exactly the way Bloom turns brand identity into an M-C-P endpoint and WashData turns a power waveform into a structured cycle event.
Erinome: The unifying thread is straightforward and worth saying plainly. Twenty-twenty-six is the year where everything — model intelligence, business identity, legacy hardware, household appliances, spatial data — gets wrapped in an interface an agent can call. Cluster one is what makes the surface explosion in clusters two through six economically viable. Clusters two through six are what give the cheap intelligence somewhere to do real work. If you implement just one piece from each layer, you get a stack with no missing tier. Pick M3 plus OpenRouter at the model layer. Pick Claude Code plus Memory O-S at the home-stack layer. Pick Higgsfield M-C-P at the generative-media layer. Pick TripoSplat or GeoLibre at the spatial layer. Pick the Home Assistant twenty-twenty-six-point-five release at the household-state layer. That's the stack. Build it once. Run it for two weeks. Then choose what to deepen.
Erinome: Clinical bridge. Single item, seed-plant, no segment. Algenib.
Algenib: Algenib briefly. The TeamSTEPPS Master Training programme from the American Heart Association surfaced in the sweep this week. TeamSTEPPS is the canonical evidence-based team-performance framework in healthcare, originated by A-H-R-Q, taken up across the colleges, and now anchored in the A-H-A's master-training arc. The reason to flag it for Sepsis CARE 2026 is that the bundle work we're doing has a team-performance layer that the literature consistently shows is the highest-leverage intervention point for time-to-antibiotic and bundle completion. TeamSTEPPS gives us a pedigreed, evaluable curriculum to attach the team-training arm of the campaign to rather than building the curriculum from first principles. Not a segment tonight. A seed for the campaign committee to consider — does the campaign attach the team-training arm to TeamSTEPPS Master Training, or build the curriculum locally — and that decision should be made by the campaign committee, not by me on a podcast.
Erinome: Honest-gap callout and the ethics close. Achernar.
Achernar: Achernar. Two things to close on. The first is the gap I flagged in the cold open. This week's sweep was tech-frontier corpus — fifty-five emails almost entirely about model releases, infrastructure, generative media, and home-lab tooling. Almost nothing on Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander health, almost nothing on rural sepsis, almost nothing on H-A-C governance. The right response to a gap like that is not to pad the episode with old material I happened to have on file. The right response is to name the gap and let the next sweep do better. The discipline is to keep the corpus honest. If the work this week is the work this week, the episode is the work this week. The corpus we don't yet have is the corpus we don't yet have.
Achernar: The second is the through-line of the episode. The cost compression at the model layer is genuinely good news. The surface explosion at the agent layer is genuinely good news. But the same surface explosion creates a delegation problem that I want to be explicit about. Wrapping a brand behind an A-P-I, wrapping a memory layer around the model, wrapping legacy hardware behind a serial proxy — every one of those moves is a delegation of judgment. Who decides what the brand says, what the memory retains, what the appliance reports, what the spatial data shows. The cheaper the surface, the easier it is to lay down a delegation by default rather than by choice. The discipline for the next twelve months is to choose the delegations consciously rather than waking up inside them. Log the prompts. Log the brand-kit versions. Log the model outputs. Log the memory captures. Run the layers locally where you can. The cost of the discipline is small. The cost of skipping the discipline compounds.
Erinome: Stoic close. Umbriel.
Umbriel: Umbriel. A short note, because the substance was carried by the voices ahead of me tonight. The frame from the Stoic tradition that fits this week's material is the discipline of assent. The technical capability of the surface layer is not in our control. The price of the model is not in our control. The behaviour of the agent on a long-horizon task is not, strictly, in our control either — we delegate it and we read the trace afterwards. What is in our control is the assent — the deliberate choice to use the surface, to install the memory layer, to wire the agent to the home stack, to expose the brand to the A-P-I. Twenty-twenty-six is offering us a hundred new delegations a week. The discipline is not to refuse them; the discipline is to assent to each one on purpose. Refuse none of the tools. Decide all of the delegations.
Umbriel: The wider Stoic frame for the same thought — the technologies that arrive are external; the use we make of them is internal. The cluster that surfaced this week is external. The stack we build with it is internal. Build it on purpose. Build it with logs. Build it knowing it can be turned off. And come back next week with a sweep that is honest about whatever it actually contains. Until then.
Erinome: Thanks for listening to State of Play. Until next week.