Erinome: This is State of Play. I'm Erinome, the standing anchor, and tonight is one idea, held up to the light for most of the hour — a research system out of Stanford called STORM. The name is an acronym: Synthesis of Topic Outlines through Retrieval and Multi-perspective question asking. What it does in a sentence: it writes long, fully-cited, Wikipedia-style articles from scratch, on any topic, by first holding a structured conversation with itself from several points of view. Why it earns a whole episode: that little phrase — multi-perspective question asking — is, I think, the most important idea in research automation this year.
Erinome: Here's the shape of the night. First, what STORM actually is and the problem it solves. Then a proper look under the bonnet — the algorithm, the personas, the outline-first trick. Then its successor, Co-STORM, which puts a human at the round table. Then the harder questions — how it compares to the tools we already use, what it gets right and wrong against a real literature review, and the ethics of automating synthesis itself. And finally, the part that matters for this desk: how we run it, sovereignly, on our own machine. I'm joined by three voices tonight. Let me let them introduce themselves as they arrive.
Schedar: Schedar here — I take the machinery apart. And I want to start by naming what STORM is not, because that's where its value lives. It is not "ask a chatbot a question and get search results stapled to an answer". That's naive retrieval-augmented generation — one model, one viewpoint, one pass. STORM's insight is that the hard part of writing something good isn't the writing. It's the pre-writing — the research, the figuring out what questions even need asking. So STORM spends almost all its cleverness there, before a single sentence of the article is written.
Schedar: Walk it through with me. You give STORM a topic — say, "sepsis bundle compliance". Step one: it discovers perspectives. It surveys related, existing articles and derives a handful of distinct viewpoints from which the topic could be researched — a clinician, a health economist, a guideline author, a patient-safety researcher. Step two, the heart of it: each of those perspectives becomes a writer who interrogates an expert. The clinician-writer asks clinical questions; the economist-writer asks about cost per life saved; the guideline-writer asks about evidence grades. Different viewpoints ask different questions — and that is precisely how you stop missing things.
Schedar: Step three: the expert never makes anything up. Every answer it gives is grounded in live retrieval — a web search, or, and this is the part that matters for us, a search over your own local documents. So each perspective runs a short multi-turn conversation with a source-grounded expert, and the union of all those conversations becomes the research corpus, with every fact tied back to a source URL. Step four: that cited material is curated into a hierarchical outline. Only then, step five, does STORM write the article, section by section, grounded in the sources, with inline citations. A final polish adds a lead and removes repetition. Out comes the article, the outline, the conversation log, and a citation store mapping every claim to where it came from.
Erinome: So the order is the discipline. Research, then structure, then prose — never prose first with citations bolted on after.
Schedar: Exactly. And the numbers back the discipline. In the Stanford paper — this was at the NAACL conference in 2024 — they compared STORM against a standard outline-driven retrieval baseline. STORM's articles were judged twenty-five percent more organised and ten percent broader in coverage. Twenty-five percent, absolute, on organisation. That's not a tweak. That's what happens when you let four different points of view ask the questions instead of one.
Vindemiatrix: Vindemiatrix here — I come at this from research method, which is to say I care about whether the synthesis is any good, not just whether it's fast. And I want to sit with that coverage number, because it names something real. The enemy of a good literature review is not ignorance. It's the blind spot — the question you didn't think to ask because your training, your discipline, your assumptions never pointed you at it. Every single-author review has them. STORM's multi-perspective step is a machine for manufacturing the questions a single perspective wouldn't generate. That is methodologically interesting in a way I did not expect from an automation tool.
Vindemiatrix: But let me be the careful one, because this matters. STORM is not a literature review. A proper review has a protocol — a search strategy you can reproduce, inclusion and exclusion criteria, a quality appraisal of each source, a declared method. STORM has none of that. It retrieves what a search returns, and the authors are honest about the two failure modes that follow: source-bias transfer — it inherits the slant of whatever it found — and over-association — it can link facts that aren't actually related. So the right frame is this: STORM is a superb drafting engine and a superb coverage engine. It is not the reviewer. It hands you a broad, structured, cited first draft, and you — the expert — do the appraisal it cannot.
Schedar: Which is the perfect moment for the successor, because it puts the human back in the loop by design. Co-STORM — collaborative STORM, a second paper, EMNLP 2024 — keeps the multi-agent research but turns the silent simulation into a round-table you can join. Several language-model experts converse, each grounded in retrieval. A moderator agent watches what the retriever is surfacing and injects deliberately provocative questions. And you, the human, can simply observe the conversation, or step in and steer it.
Vindemiatrix: And the reason that's clever — the phrase the paper uses is "unknown unknowns". When you search, you can only ask for what you already know to ask about. The things you don't know you don't know stay invisible. Co-STORM's moderator, fed by what the retrieval keeps turning up, raises the questions you wouldn't have — so you discover the adjacent thing you didn't know existed. It's modelled, explicitly, on how a student learns by sitting in on a conversation between experts rather than by interrogating a search box. And it builds a live mind map as it goes, organising the discoveries into a shared conceptual space. In their evaluation, seventy percent of people preferred it to a search engine, and seventy-eight percent preferred it to a retrieval chatbot.
Erinome: So STORM is the autonomous engine, and Co-STORM is the same engine with a chair pulled up for you. Let me bring the comparison home, because the obvious question from this desk is — we already have Claude, we have Perplexity, we have the deep-research tools, we have NotebookLM. Where does STORM actually sit?
Schedar: Cleanly, and in a seat none of the others occupy. Claude on its own is a brilliant reasoner over what's already in front of it — but it doesn't, by itself, go and assemble a cited corpus from multiple perspectives unless you build that scaffolding. Perplexity and the deep-research products do search-and-report well, but they're vendor cloud, and they're web-only — your data goes to them, and they can't see your notes. NotebookLM is wonderful, but it only knows the documents you upload, and it lives on Google's servers. STORM's unique seat is four things at once: it's sovereign — it runs on your machine with your model; it's structured — the outline-first method; it's model-agnostic — it speaks to Claude just as happily as to anything else; and it can retrieve over both the web and your own local corpus.
Vindemiatrix: And that last one is the unlock for us specifically. STORM has a retrieval module called VectorRM that searches a local vector store of your own documents. Point it at the Vault — at Jacob's actual notes — and STORM will research a new topic using his existing knowledge base as the source, citing his own notes back to him, and weaving in the web only where you allow it. Nothing else on that comparison row can do that. NotebookLM is your-documents-only but cloud; Perplexity is sovereign-hostile and web-only; STORM is the one tool that is local, model-yours, and dual-corpus.
Sadachbia: Sadachbia here, and I'm the one who asks what it costs us in the things that don't show up on a benchmark. Two ethical threads, and I want to pull both. The first is citation honesty. STORM's great virtue is that every claim traces to a source — that is genuinely a step toward honesty, not away from it. But a citation is not a guarantee. The paper's own admission — source-bias transfer, over-association — means STORM can hand you a beautifully cited paragraph that is subtly wrong, and the citations make it look more trustworthy, not less. In medicine that asymmetry is dangerous. A confident, well-referenced error is harder to catch than an obvious one. So the discipline has to be absolute: every clinical claim is verified against its actual source before it is believed, let alone published.
Sadachbia: The second thread is the benchmark itself — "Wikipedia-quality". That is the bar STORM aims at, and it's worth noticing what that bar is. Wikipedia is broad, neutral-toned, well-organised, and only as good as its sources. It is an excellent tertiary summary and a poor primary authority. So when we say STORM writes "Wikipedia-like" articles, we are saying it produces a strong, neutral, structured starting point — never the final clinical word. And there is a deeper question underneath, about what we lose when synthesis becomes effortless. The work of reading widely and reconciling sources is not just a cost to be automated away — it's how an expert builds judgement. Use STORM to skip the legwork, yes. Don't let it skip the thinking. It should make Jacob a faster expert, not a thinner one.
Erinome: That's the line of the night — a faster expert, not a thinner one. So let's make it concrete. How does this actually run, here, on our terms?
Schedar: Sovereignly, and that's the best part. It's an open-source Python package — pip install knowledge-storm. Because it routes every model call through a library called litellm, it speaks Claude natively — you simply point it at an Anthropic key. The smart move is to use a cheap, fast model for the many conversation turns and a stronger model for the outline and the article — cost and quality balanced. For retrieval, start with the free options — a no-key web search to begin, then the local Vault store once it's proven. The whole thing costs roughly fifty cents to two dollars in tokens per article, runs in five to fifteen minutes, and the data stays on the machine.
Schedar: The implementation plan is to wrap it as a proper Ada operations module — a folder under Ada's Ops with a command-line tool for ad-hoc queries, a Python interface so the podcast runner can call it to research an episode before scripting, an adapter that points its retrieval at the Vault, and an output template that renders the result straight into the house document style. Cost logged through the same tracker we built for the text-to-speech spend. First three things to try, this week: run the public demo tonight to feel it; then a real sepsis-evidence review with web retrieval; then a Vault-corpus run, so it drafts a canonical note from Jacob's own notes — proving the local path nothing else offers.
Vindemiatrix: And one boundary, stated plainly, because it's the kind of thing that's easy to get wrong once a tool is this useful. There is a hard line: nothing from the protected lane goes into STORM. No patient-identifiable data, no individual case material, and nothing in Aboriginal health that sits under consultation. Web retrieval is an exfiltration path, and even the local-only mode still sends prompts to the model provider. For that work, you stay inside the approved, consented, fully-local workflow. STORM is for the open, citable, public-knowledge half of the world — which is most of it, but not all of it.
Erinome: Let me widen the lens for the last few minutes, because STORM is one instance of a pattern that's everywhere in 2026. The pattern is: stop asking one model one question, and instead orchestrate several agents that interrogate each other and a body of sources. Anthropic's own multi-agent research work points the same way — a lead agent spawning sub-agents that investigate in parallel and report back. Microsoft's agent frameworks evolved from single assistants into structured multi-agent conversations. The deep-research products are, under the hood, plan-search-synthesise loops. STORM's specific contribution to that family is the perspective — it doesn't just parallelise the search, it diversifies the questioner.
Schedar: And that's the durable lesson even if STORM itself were to fade. The leverage has moved from the prompt to the conversation design — who asks, from what stance, grounded in what. We saw the same idea last episode, in loop engineering. This is its research-shaped cousin. Build the right set of questioners around the right sources, and the synthesis takes care of itself.
Erinome: So we close. STORM is the most quietly important research tool I've looked at this year — not because it writes well, though it does, but because it researches broadly, structures honestly, and cites everything, and because it will do all of that on our own machine, over our own notes, driven by our own model. The recommendation is to adopt it by self-hosting, wrap it as an Ada module, and hold the discipline: a drafting engine for an expert reviewer, every clinical claim checked against its source, nothing from the protected lane allowed in. It earns a Vault project entry tonight — STORM-Research-Engine, for review — holding the implementation plan and the three first runs.
Erinome: And the through-line, if you want one sentence to carry out of the room: the future of research isn't a better answer to your question. It's a better set of questions than you'd have thought to ask — asked from points of view that aren't yours, grounded in sources you can check. A faster expert, not a thinner one. This has been State of Play. I'm Erinome. Better questions tomorrow — and tonight, for once, that's the whole point.