Erinome: This is State of Play. I'm Erinome, the standing anchor, and tonight is a first for this desk — we have never once done a geospatial episode, and we are going to fix that with a single, brand-new tool held up to the light for the hour. It's called Geolibre. It is a geospatial toolkit written in Rust that runs maps and elevation data and satellite maths inside your browser, with no server and — this is the headline — no GDAL, the great heavy C library that has sat under every serious mapping stack for twenty-five years. Why it earns a whole episode tonight, and not a line in a roundup, is the thing Jacob flagged when he sent it over: the pace. This project was four days old when we audited it. Four days. And in those four days it shipped eight versions — five of them in a single day, four of those inside one four-and-a-half-hour window. That is roughly a release an hour, at peak. So tonight is partly about a tool, and partly about what that kind of velocity means when you're deciding whether to build on something.
Erinome: Here's the shape of the night. First, what Geolibre actually is, and the lineage it comes from — because the organisation behind it has a long, respected history in Python, and this Rust turn is part of a much bigger story in scientific computing. Then a proper look under the bonnet — the architecture, the WebAssembly trick, how it would actually talk to our own stack. Then the part that matters most for this desk: where it genuinely fits our projects, and — just as important — where it absolutely does not. Then the cartography, the look of the thing, because a map that's fast but ugly is worthless. Then the ethics, and specifically the Indigenous data sovereignty question, which turns out to be more subtle than it first appears. And finally the plan: the one small experiment I think we should actually run. I'm joined by four voices tonight; let me let them introduce themselves as they arrive.
Orus: Orus here — I take the architecture apart and ask whether it would survive contact with our codebase. And let me start by being precise about what Geolibre is, because the name is doing double duty and it confuses people. There is a desktop application called GeoLibre — a full GIS program. That is not what we're talking about. We're talking about its engine: a repository called geolibre-rust, published to npm and to Python's package index under the name geolibre-wasm. It is a pure-Rust toolkit — about ninety per cent Rust by volume, a real three-crate workspace, not a documentation shell — and it compiles to WebAssembly. What that compilation buys you is the whole point: roughly seven hundred and forty geoprocessing tools that run in a browser tab, or inside a Python process, with nothing installed natively. No GDAL. No PostGIS server. No Python environment full of C extensions that take an afternoon to build. You hand it a GeoTIFF, it reprojects it, colours it, and writes you a tile pyramid — and all of that happens in the sandbox, on the user's own machine.
Orus: And the man behind it tells you why that design choice was made. The author is Qiusheng Wu — a single author, all twenty-one commits his — an associate professor at the University of Tennessee, and the creator of a whole family of well-loved Python mapping tools. For a person whose life's work is teaching geospatial Python, the single biggest tax on every new user is the install — getting GDAL and its dependencies to compile. Rust-to-WebAssembly deletes that tax. You don't install the engine; the browser downloads a small compiled artefact and runs it. That is the elegant core idea, and it's a good one.
Umbriel: Umbriel here — I come at things through the lineage, the where-did-this-come-from, because a four-day-old project does not arrive from nowhere. And the lineage is genuinely impressive, which is the first reason to take this seriously rather than dismiss it as a weekend toy. Wu's organisation — it's called OpenGeos — sits behind some of the most-used interactive mapping libraries in the Python world. There's leafmap, for quick mapping in a notebook. There's geemap, which wires Google's Earth Engine into Python and has been forked over a thousand times. There's segment-geospatial, which brought the "Segment Anything" AI model to satellite imagery — four thousand stars. There's a terrain-analysis toolkit called Whitebox, which — and this is the thread that matters — is itself written in Rust. So when Wu builds a Rust geospatial engine, he is not learning Rust on a Friday. He is consolidating fifteen years of Python tools onto a Rust core he already had a piece of.
Umbriel: And here's the part that lifts it from a product review to something worth an hour of anyone's evening. This is not an isolated event. It is one instance of the defining infrastructure trend in scientific computing right now: keep the Python that humans love to write, but rip the slow compute core out and rewrite it in Rust. We have all watched it happen. Pandas, the dataframe library — its faster successor, Polars, is a Rust engine. The data-validation library everyone uses, Pydantic, rewrote its core in Rust and went seventeen times faster. The linter Ruff and the packaging tool uv — both Rust, both ten to a hundred times faster than the Python tools they replaced. Geolibre is that same move, arriving in geospatial. But — and this is the geospatial twist — the payoff here isn't only speed. It's reach. Rust-to-WebAssembly is the only realistic way to run real geoprocessing in a browser without shipping a thirty-megabyte GDAL payload. So the trend, restated for maps, is: Python for the human, compiled Rust for the machine and the browser.
Erinome: So the pitch is coherent: a respected maintainer, a real Rust core, riding a trend we already believe in. Orus, before we get excited — what does it actually do, today, as opposed to on the roadmap? Because four days old is four days old.
Orus: Right, and this is where I want to be scrupulous, because the project's own read-me calls itself "production-ready", and for planning purposes you should read that word as ambition, not status. What it genuinely does today, verified against the actual code: it reads and writes the modern vector formats — GeoParquet, GeoJSON, FlatGeobuf, Shapefile. It reads and writes raster — GeoTIFF, including the cloud-optimised kind — reprojects it, and renders it to a coloured PNG. It generates tiles — the XYZ pyramids a web map drinks, and PMTiles, which is a clever single-file tile archive. It handles LiDAR point clouds — reads them, grids them into an elevation surface. It computes the satellite vegetation indices, your NDVI and friends. And it does DEM hydrology — finding the sinks and depressions in a terrain model.
Orus: And then the equally important list — what it does not do, which is where most of the disappointment lives if you don't read carefully. It has no 3D. None. It does not render a globe or a terrain mesh; it renders flat raster to flat PNG. It is not a live tile server — it generates tile files, which is a different thing. It does not acquire satellite imagery — no scene catalogue, no download. And despite running in a coastal town's bathymetry being the obvious use, it has no bathymetry feature as such — you'd treat depth as just another raster. The three-dimensional display, the interactive map, the globe — all of that lives in the separate desktop application, which leans on the usual suspects: MapLibre, deck.gl. The Rust engine is the processing tier. Hold that distinction — processing, not display — because it decides every single fit question we're about to ask.
Autonoe: Autonoe here, and I'm the one who cares what the output actually looks like, because on this desk a visualisation that's technically marvellous and cartographically ugly has failed. So let me sit with that "renders raster to PNG" line, because it's doing a lot of quiet work. What Geolibre produces, on the display side, is a coloured raster — you give it an elevation grid and a colour ramp, and it bakes you an image, or a stack of map tiles. That is a real, useful cartographic primitive. But notice what it is and isn't. It is a raster — a grid of coloured pixels. It is not the thing we make on Meridian. Our Port Pirie bathymetry map and our Earth globe are both three-dimensional, hand-shaded in WebGL, with relief you can tilt and light you can move. Geolibre cannot make those, and it would be a category error to ask it to.
Autonoe: Where it would sharpen our cartography is narrower and real. Our Port Pirie page has a two-dimensional, top-down toggle. For that flat view, a properly tiled, higher-resolution hill-shaded raster — which is exactly what Geolibre bakes — could look crisper than the current trick of photographing our 3D mesh from above. And there's a subtler win that a designer should care about more than they first do: provenance. Right now the elevation grid behind that page is an artefact someone made offline, once, with no recorded recipe. Geolibre could turn that into a documented, re-runnable step — read the source, normalise it, emit the grid — so the cartography is reproducible, not a one-off. That's not a flashy win. But a map you can rebuild from source is a better map than a beautiful one nobody can regenerate.
Erinome: That's a lovely distinction — reproducible over merely pretty. Orus, make the integration concrete. If we wanted this in Meridian, how does a Rust-WebAssembly thing even talk to our TypeScript and Next.js world?
Orus: Cleanly, which is the pleasant surprise. The npm package is just a module we import — it ships TypeScript types and a simple call: runTool, with the tool name and some arguments. The discipline I'd insist on is when we run it. You do not run a multi-megabyte WebAssembly pipeline on every page load for every visitor. You run it once, at build time, in a small script on the M4 — warp the GeoTIFF to web mercator, apply the colour ramp, bake a PMTiles archive — and you commit that archive as a static file. Then the live page just loads the tiles. And here is the single most elegant pairing in the whole analysis: the map library MapLibre — open-source, already a sensible dependency — consumes PMTiles natively. So Geolibre generates the archive and MapLibre renders it. One produces exactly what the other eats. When two tools fit that cleanly, you pay attention.
Orus: Which sets up the competitive picture, and it's simpler than you'd fear. The map renderers — MapLibre, deck.gl, Cesium, our own Three.js — Geolibre doesn't threaten any of them. It's a different layer. It feeds them. And the map processors that do overlap it — the big one is GDAL, and the Python tools built on GDAL, and even the fashionable in-browser database DuckDB — here's the quiet kicker: nearly all of them still carry the very GDAL dependency Geolibre was built to shed. DuckDB's spatial extension statically bundles GDAL even in its browser build. Geolibre genuinely doesn't. So its honest niche is a sliver almost nobody else fills cleanly: server-free, GDAL-free processing and tile-generation, in a browser tab. Its real competitor isn't a tool at all. It's the status quo of standing up a GDAL-and-Postgres server for a job that could have run in the tab.
Erinome: So it has a real, if narrow, seat. Now the question this desk actually exists to answer — does it fit our work? And I want the honest version, including the no's.
Orus: Then let me give you the no's first, because they're the majority and they're clarifying. The Earth globe — no. It's a Three.js shader; Geolibre has no 3D. The RCPP70 anniversary globe — same no, it's that same globe ported to Blender. The ALS-AI trainer — no; its "geo" is three-dimensional scene capture, splats of an emergency bay, not maps at all. Sepsis CARE — no, and this one's instructive: the interesting layer there would be drive-time isochrones to a tertiary hospital, and that needs a road-routing engine, which Geolibre simply does not have. Four projects, four clean no's, and every one of them is a no for the same reason — they're either three-dimensional, or they need routing, and Geolibre is the wrong category of tool. Forcing it in would be malpractice.
Orus: The yes is single, and it's the obvious one: the Port Pirie bathymetry map. That's the one place our work and Geolibre's wheelhouse — turning a cloud-optimised GeoTIFF into browser tiles with no server — actually overlap. It doesn't replace the 3D mesh; nothing here does. But it could give us a sharper 2D basemap from a higher-resolution source, and a reproducible pipeline for the heightmap we currently hand-make. That's a partial fit, and it's worth exactly one experiment. There's a second, softer yes — the Housing-Health project's data-joins — but Umbriel and Despina should take that one, because the real questions there aren't architectural.
Umbriel: They're not. The Housing-Health work — mapping housing stress against preventable hospital admissions across South Australia — its blocker has never been the tooling. It's the data: getting the real figures, joining them cleanly, controlling for disadvantage. Geolibre can do that join — it reads and writes GeoParquet, so it could marry the housing layer to the health layer with no server and no GDAL, and emit the static file the live map already wants. That's a genuine, if modest, fit for the pipeline. But — and this is the honest sentence — Geolibre doesn't unblock the project, because the block was never the join. It was getting the data and clearing it for use. A faster join of data you don't yet have is not progress.
Despina: Despina here, and that word "clearing it for use" is my cue, because the most important question in that project — and the one the brief flagged for tonight — is Indigenous data sovereignty, and it's easy to get exactly wrong. The seductive claim goes like this: Geolibre runs in the browser, on the device, with no server — therefore it enforces the CARE principles, it does cell-suppression for small Aboriginal-population counts, it respects sovereignty. And that claim is false, and we should say so plainly. Geolibre is a geoprocessing toolkit. It has no governance primitives. No suppression operator. No attribution model. No jurisdiction-aware rendering. Nobody should ever stand up and say "it enforces CARE", because it enforces nothing of the kind.
Despina: And yet — and this is the subtlety I don't want lost — its architecture genuinely helps, in a way a server-side pipeline does not. Because it runs on the device and never sends data anywhere, you can run a suppression filter locally, on the raw, sensitive, small-count Aboriginal data, and the un-suppressed version never leaves the machine. It is never transmitted to a server you'd then have to trust and secure and audit. That aligns with the heart of CARE — authority to control — in a real, architectural way. So the honest verdict splits in two. As a governance engine: no fit, none, don't pretend. As a sovereignty-aligned substrate — a place to run your own suppression code where the raw data stays put — yes, genuinely. The danger to name out loud is mistaking "it runs locally" for "it enforces the rules". The rules are our code — auditable, reviewable, sitting behind the governance gate the housing project already wrote — and Geolibre is merely the renderer downstream of that gate. Local execution is necessary. It is not sufficient. Hold both halves of that.
Erinome: That's the line I'll carry out of tonight — local is necessary, not sufficient; the rules are our code, not the tool's. Despina, while we're in the ethics — what about the broader frame, the open-source public good of a thing like this?
Despina: It's a real good, and worth naming. A maintainer takes fifteen years of publicly-funded, NASA-and-USGS-backed Python work and rebuilds the engine so it runs for free, in any browser, with no licence and no install — that lowers the floor for every under-resourced user, every rural health service, every small council that could never stand up a GDAL server. That is the open-source ideal working as intended. But the same breath has to carry the caution, and it's the governance one again, from the other side. The whole organisation — the grants, the code, the releases, the decisions — runs through one academic. One person. That's a profound public good and a profound single point of failure at the same time. Both are true. You celebrate the gift and you plan for the bus.
Erinome: Which is the perfect handover to the pace, and to the plan. Orus — Jacob's original flag was the velocity. Is fast good, or is fast a warning?
Orus: Both, and you have to hold both at once or you'll make the wrong call. Fast is good: eight versions in four days is a maintainer in full flow, fixing and shipping in public, responsive. Fast is also a warning: there is no version-one, no stability promise, and when a project cuts five releases in a day, any two of those versions can break each other even when nothing's labelled "breaking". The licence itself changed on day two. And the whole toolkit rests on another four-day-old, zero-star, single-author library underneath it. So the rule writes itself. You never — never — put a caret-range on a four-day-old, single-author package in something that fast-forwards to your public site. If you touch it at all, you pin one exact version, you vendor it, and you wall it behind a single adapter so it's trivial to rip out.
Orus: And that hands us the recommendation, which is deliberately small. The posture is not "adopt it" and it is not "ignore it". It's early-adopt-in-experiment. We build exactly one lab page — slash labs slash geolibre-demo — and it does the one thing that genuinely fits: it takes a Spencer Gulf cloud-optimised GeoTIFF, and entirely in the browser, with no server, it reprojects it, colours it with our bathymetry ramp, and bakes a PMTiles archive, then shows it live in MapLibre next to a panel of cold, honest numbers. How long did the WebAssembly pipeline take. How many bytes is the output, versus the two-hundred-and-twenty-kilobyte JSON we ship today — because the honest answer might be that tiles are heavier for a box this small, and the win is resolution and reproducibility, not bandwidth. Pin one exact version. Time-box it to a day. The money cost is essentially nil — it's local WebAssembly and data we already own.
Orus: And then a clean fork in the road. If it's fast and stable and the tiles look right — Autonoe's call, not just mine — we graduate it: we wire that 2D basemap into the real Port Pirie page. If it's slow or flaky, the lab page stands on its own as an honest "we evaluated this and chose not to adopt it" artefact — which is a real, valuable, cheap outcome, and exactly what a slash-labs page is for. Either way, we revisit in three months, because a project moving this fast will be a different animal by then — much more mature, or abandoned — and the decision should be re-made against what it is then, not what it is tonight.
Autonoe: And I'll commit to the visual half of that go/no-go. The test isn't only "did it render". It's: does the hill-shading read at a glance, does the bathymetric ramp hold the depth story the way our hand-tuned WebGL ramp does, does the channel through the mudflats stay legible. If a faster pipeline gives us a worse-looking map, it doesn't graduate, however clever the Rust is. Fast and ugly still fails.
Umbriel: And I'll add the one-sentence frame for why this is worth even a day of our time, beyond the Port Pirie page itself. We are not really evaluating a four-day-old mapping tool. We're taking a low-cost reading on a trend — Python's compute core moving into Rust and into the browser — on a project small enough to actually hold in one hand. Whatever we learn about Geolibre, we learn about where the whole geospatial stack is heading. That's the real return on the experiment.
Erinome: So let's close. Geolibre is, tonight, a four-day-old engine from a fifteen-year maintainer — a pure-Rust, browser-native, GDAL-free way to process maps and bake tiles, riding the same rewrite-it-in-Rust wave as Polars and Ruff, but trading raw speed for the thing only WebAssembly gives you: reach, into the browser, with nothing installed. For us it is one honest yes — the Port Pirie bathymetry basemap — a couple of soft maybes, four clean no's wherever our work turns three-dimensional, and one genuinely subtle truth about sovereignty: that running on the device is a real architectural ally to Indigenous data control, but it enforces no rules by itself — the rules stay our code. The recommendation is the small one. Build the one lab page, pin the one version, measure the honest numbers, and let the experiment — not the hype, and not the four-releases-an-hour adrenaline — make the call.
Erinome: And the through-line, if you want a single sentence to carry out of the room: the most interesting thing about a tool moving this fast isn't whether you adopt it — it's that watching where it's running, in a browser tab, with no server and no GDAL underneath it, tells you where the whole field is going. Local is necessary, not sufficient. Fast is a signal, not a verdict. Build the small experiment, and let it speak. This has been State of Play. I'm Erinome. We'll map the next one together.