Charon: This is State of Play, Episode 32 — about forty minutes today, and a different shape from the news sweeps we usually run. I'm your host. This one's a deep dive on a single clinical topic — the dislocated shoulder. It's a piece built out of the shoulder-dislocation tutorial that came together in the Vault last week, sitting alongside the Aussie Boxing App work, and it's pitched at the Australian medical officer working rurally. Registrar level. Generalist. The kind of clinician who might be the only doctor in the building when the boxer comes in from the ringside, or when the eighty-year-old presents from the nursing home with an arm they can't move. We'll touch boxing throughout, because that was the substrate that drove the tutorial, but everything we talk about transfers cleanly to footy, to falls, to seizures, to electrocutions, to whatever else lands a humeral head somewhere it shouldn't be. We've got the full Ross-family clinical team in today — Osler on bedside reasoning, Hermione on the evidence base, Feynman on the mechanism, Curie on equity and the rural-access lens, Tufte on imaging, and Fred Rogers Ross on how you actually talk to the boxer while you're putting their shoulder back. Settle in.
Charon: Let me anchor this with a scene. It's a Saturday night in a regional hall in the Mid-North of South Australia. Boxing SA-sanctioned amateur tournament. You're the ringside doctor. Round three of the third bout of the night. A twenty-four-year-old amateur welterweight throws a rear cross at a slipping opponent, misses by a long way, and immediately drops the arm and shouts that he's put his shoulder out. The bout is stopped. He walks to the corner holding the arm awkwardly. The shoulder is squared off. The deltoid contour has flattened, the acromion is the most lateral point you can see. The boxer is in pain but lucid, and the corner is asking you what you need from them. No theatre. No anaesthetist. No orthopaedic registrar on the end of a phone in the next ten minutes. What you have is — yourself, a Penthrox whistle, maybe a portable ultrasound, a coach who has done this before with this fighter, and a hospital that's seventy kilometres away. That scene is the one we're going to come back to throughout this episode. Hold it in your head. Right — let's start with why this matters at all.
Algenib: William Osler Ross here. This matters because the shoulder dislocates more than any other joint in the body, and because the way you handle the first ten minutes after the reduction call is largely the way that boxer's career trajectory gets shaped. The headline numbers — and we'll have Hermione on the evidence in a moment — the shoulder accounts for somewhere between five and fifteen percent of all boxing injuries, depending on which surveillance dataset you pull from. It's the leading upper-limb articular injury, less common than facial lacerations or hand injuries, but the single most common cause of an upper-limb fight-stopping injury. About ninety-five percent of dislocations are anterior. Two to four percent are posterior, and they are the ones that get missed. The remainder — luxatio erecta, the locked-overhead variant — is rare enough that you might see one in a career, but if you don't recognise it you will hurt the patient trying to reduce it the wrong way. For the rural ringside doctor, the operational truth is this: you need to be more confident in clinical diagnosis and field reduction than your metropolitan ED colleagues, because the alternative — transferring every dislocation to a tertiary centre two hundred kilometres away — is neither clinically optimal nor logistically possible.
Kore: I'm Hermione Granger Ross, evidence base. Let me put numbers on Osler's outline. The two highest-quality Australian datasets are the Victorian Professional Boxing and Combat Sports Board cohort reported by Zazryn, McCrory and Cameron in 2009 — five hundred and forty-five professional boxers across nine hundred and seven fights, injury rate twenty-three point six per hundred professional bouts. Bledsoe's Nevada cohort, five hundred and twenty-four matches, came in at seventeen point one injuries per hundred boxer-matches. The shoulder sits inside that envelope. The natural-history piece that matters most is Hovelius's Swedish cohort — two hundred and fifty-five patients followed for twenty-five years. The headline finding: first dislocations in young patients carry a sixty to ninety percent recurrence rate at long-term follow-up. The recurrence risk drops sharply with age — by the time you're over forty at first dislocation, the recurrence risk is closer to twenty percent, but the associated rotator cuff tear risk is meaningfully higher. So the age of the patient changes both the prognosis and the differential. Translation for the boxer Charon just described — a twenty-four-year-old male amateur welterweight with a first anterior dislocation has a high prior probability of capsulolabral structural damage and a high probability of recurrence. That's not a fight-day inconvenience. That's a career-shaping event.
Achernar: Marie Curie Ross, equity lens. Before we get further into the bones and the techniques, I want to land what rural and regional context actually means for this presentation. Port Pirie Regional Health Service, where this episode is partly anchored, does not have an on-site twenty-four-seven CT scanner, no resident orthopaedic surgeon, no on-site MRI. Whyalla has CT twenty-four-seven; MRI is referred out, typically to the Royal Adelaide or Lyell McEwin. The Riverland goes to Mount Gambier or Berri. Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander participation in Australian amateur boxing exists but is not well quantified in the published literature, and where future Boxing Australia datasets do publish that data, it should be governed under Indigenous data sovereignty principles — CARE, Maiam nayri Wingara — with community oversight. I'll flag throughout: rural ringside reduction is not metropolitan ED reduction. The first-pass technique that minimises force, minimises drug exposure, and minimises time to transfer if it fails is operationally the most important capability for the regional doctor. Force escalation isn't a backup plan — it's an admission that you skipped the gentle technique. We'll come back to this when we talk reduction order. Charon.
Charon: Thanks Marie. Right — to the anatomy and the mechanism. Feynman, you want to take this?
Rasalgethi: Richard Feynman Ross here. The interesting thing about the glenohumeral joint is that it dislocates more than any other joint in the body because that's exactly what it was built to allow. Three facts. The humeral head presents about thirty square centimetres of articular surface. The glenoid presents about six. So the ratio of head to socket is four to one, sometimes five to one. People call it a golf ball on a tee — that's directionally correct but understates how loose the system actually is. Fact two — the capsule that wraps the joint is voluminous and lax. In a relaxed cadaveric specimen it contains roughly twice the volume of the humeral head. You can distract the head a full centimetre from the glenoid before the capsule even starts to tighten on you. Fact three — the static stabilisers, which is the labrum and the capsuloligamentous complex, are supplemented by dynamic stabilisers, which is the rotator cuff and the scapulothoracic muscles. When the dynamic stabilisers are tired — exactly the condition of a fatigued boxer in round eight throwing a missed cross — the joint loses a big chunk of its protection. So dislocation, mechanically, isn't the joint failing. It's the joint doing what it was built to allow, just past the point at which the soft-tissue restraints can hold the humeral head in the glenoid.
Rasalgethi: Now — the canonical boxing mechanism. The missed cross. The boxer commits weight and torso rotation to the punch. The arm extends and externally rotates as the fist drives forward. At end-range, the arm is in full forward elevation, abducted ninety degrees, externally rotated ninety degrees. We call this the apprehension position because it's the position the patient with a previously unstable shoulder will refuse to enter. The punch misses. Deceleration force is borne initially by the rotator cuff. When the cuff is overcome, the load transfers to the capsulolabral complex. The humeral head levers anteriorly out of the glenoid against the antero-inferior glenoid rim and labrum. The anterior band of the inferior glenohumeral ligament avulses from the glenoid — that's the Bankart lesion. The head impacts the antero-inferior glenoid rim on the way out, producing a Hill-Sachs lesion on the postero-superior humeral head. Critical insight here — the force that dislocates the shoulder is not the punch itself. It's the failure of the punch to land. A punch that connects transfers force forward into the opponent. A punch that misses transfers nothing forward and releases all that kinetic energy as continued angular acceleration of the humerus at end-range. That's why the cross and the hook are the high-prior-probability mechanisms, and the jab and the uppercut are not.
Algenib: Osler — let me add the posterior and the luxatio erecta side of this, because Feynman's described the dominant pattern beautifully. Posterior dislocation in boxing comes from a direct blow to the anterior shoulder while the arm is flexed and internally rotated. A punch landing on the anterior deltoid during a clinch, when the lead arm is across the chest, drives the head out the back of the glenoid. The textbook "post-seizure posterior dislocation" mechanism is real but vanishingly rare in active boxing — much more likely you'll see this in the older referee, the trainer, or the judge who has a syncopal episode in the corner. The arm is locked in adduction and internal rotation, external rotation is blocked, and the deltoid contour can look almost normal. That's why the diagnosis is so often missed. Luxatio erecta — the inferior dislocation — is the over-the-rope fall. Arm caught on the top rope, body weight pulls downwards while the arm is held up, the humeral neck levers against the acromion, the head displaces inferiorly. The patient comes in with the arm locked in near-vertical abduction overhead. Highest brachial-plexus injury rate of any pattern — case series quote up to sixty percent transient stretch — and the highest axillary-artery injury rate too. We'll come back to luxatio erecta when we talk reduction, because it needs a two-step approach.
Charon: Stay with the anatomy for a second longer — because the neurovascular piece is the medico-legal lynchpin of this whole presentation. Osler.
Algenib: The axillary nerve. C5, C6. Terminal branch of the posterior cord of the brachial plexus, passes through the quadrangular space — bounded by teres minor, teres major, the long head of triceps, and the surgical neck of the humerus — accompanied by the posterior circumflex humeral artery. Motor to deltoid and teres minor. Sensory to the regimental badge area — the lateral aspect of the upper arm over the deltoid. Most commonly injured nerve in shoulder dislocation. Five to eighteen percent transient neuropraxia rate after anterior dislocation, one to two percent complete axillary palsy. Most recover in three to six months. The clinical test is two-part — sensation over the regimental badge area, and palpation of deltoid contraction during attempted shoulder abduction. The arm cannot actually move while dislocated, so you palpate the deltoid for tone. You do this before any reduction attempt. You document it. You do it again after the reduction. Forgetting to check the axillary nerve, and forgetting to document it, is the single most common medico-legal pitfall in shoulder dislocation management. Distal nerves — radial, median, ulnar — also tested, also documented. Axillary artery — radial pulse symmetric with the contralateral, capillary refill under two seconds, hand colour and temperature. Asymmetric pulse at any time is a vascular surgical emergency. You do not push through that finding to a second reduction attempt. You stop, you image, you ring vascular.
Kore: Hermione — the documentation point cannot be overstated. Schaller's 2024 audit, open access, demonstrates that orthogonal post-reduction imaging is not consistently obtained even in well-resourced centres. The neurovascular exam audit equivalent shows even worse compliance — many post-reduction notes record neurovascular status as "intact, no change" without specifying which nerves and which vascular landmarks were assessed. The way you avoid both a missed deficit and a medico-legal exposure is the same way: a structured, named, documented pre- and post-reduction exam. Drop it into the patient record as a templated block. Sensation regimental badge area. Deltoid contraction palpable. Musculocutaneous, radial, median, ulnar — sensation and motor each. Radial pulse symmetric. Cap refill. Hand colour and temperature. Repeat after. Compare. Two cells in a table. That's not bureaucracy, that's the standard of care.
Charon: Onwards. Classification — Osler. Quickly.
Algenib: Four axes — direction, aetiology, chronicity, associated injuries. Direction — anterior, ninety-five percent. Posterior, two to four. Inferior, under one. Superior, vanishingly rare and not seen in boxing. Aetiology — three patterns. TUBS, traumatic, unidirectional, Bankart lesion, surgery often required for recurrence. AMBRII, atraumatic, multidirectional, bilateral often, rehab first, inferior capsular shift if rehab fails, plus closure of the rotator interval. And AIOS — acquired instability, overstress, surgery for capsulolabral repair when conservative measures fail. Boxers sit mostly in TUBS at first presentation, drift toward AIOS over a career as chronic microinstability develops. AMBRII patients are mostly contraindicated from elite boxing — the pre-participation medical screen should pick them up. Chronicity — acute, recurrent, chronic-locked. Boxers in sanctioned bouts present acute, you see them within minutes. The chronic-locked dislocation is the unsupervised-training presentation, or the cognitively impaired patient with delayed presentation. Associated injuries — capsulolabral, bony, neurovascular, soft tissue. Bankart, bony Bankart, Hill-Sachs, ALPSA, HAGL, GLAD, SLAP — the seven structural lesions you need to know. The first three are the ones you'll see most often. Bankart lesion is essentially universal in first-time anterior dislocations — over eighty-five percent by MRI in young patients. Hill-Sachs lesion is in fifty to ninety percent. Bony Bankart matters when it exceeds twenty to twenty-five percent of the glenoid surface — that's the threshold at which arthroscopic Bankart repair gives way to bone-block stabilisation, Latarjet or distal tibia allograft.
Charon: Imaging. Tufte — what does the rural ED need on the wall, and where does POCUS fit?
Sulafat: Edward Tufte Ross here, on the visual and imaging lens. Let me start with the single most cited mistake in shoulder dislocation imaging. Always get the axillary lateral view, or a scapular Y if the patient cannot abduct the arm. An AP-only series misses posterior dislocations and inadequately characterises post-reduction position. The AAOS, ACEP, and the broader emergency-medicine literature agree on this. Recent audit data — Schaller and colleagues — show that orthogonal imaging is not consistently obtained even in well-resourced centres, with documented persistent dislocations missed when only an AP is performed. So the rule is simple. Pre-reduction if you image — AP plus axillary, or AP plus scapular Y. Post-reduction always — AP plus axillary or scapular Y. The post-reduction one is not negotiable. The pre-reduction is judgement-dependent.
Sulafat: The three standard radiographic views, in order of usefulness for the dislocation question. AP true — beam perpendicular to the plane of the scapula, demonstrates the glenohumeral relationship most directly, most sensitive for greater tuberosity fracture and Hill-Sachs. Limitation — it does not reliably show posterior dislocation. The light-bulb sign and the rim sign are AP clues to posterior dislocation, but neither is one hundred percent sensitive. Axillary lateral — the single most diagnostically useful view, demonstrates head position relative to glenoid unambiguously. Limitation — the patient has to abduct the arm, which they often cannot do acutely. Scapular Y — beam along the line of the scapular spine, three radiographic limbs of the Y, the head should sit centred at the junction. Anteriorly displaced head — anterior dislocation. Posteriorly displaced — posterior. Strength — can be obtained without abducting the arm. Velpeau view is the back-up when even the scapular Y is impossible. Garth or apical oblique is your supplementary view if bony Bankart is suspected.
Sulafat: When to image before reduction. First-ever dislocation, high-energy mechanism, patient over forty — greater tuberosity fracture is materially more common, posterior dislocation suspected because the clinical findings are subtler and you want to confirm direction, luxatio erecta because the pre-reduction imaging guides the safe reduction strategy, any neurovascular deficit, suspected open or fracture-dislocation. When you can defer pre-reduction imaging — the known recurrent dislocator with a classical anterior mechanism, intact neurovascular exam, cooperative patient, where a Cunningham reduction can be done immediately. POCUS-available rural ringside settings can also defer the pre-reduction radiograph if the operator is confident with the technique. We'll come to that in a moment.
Kore: Hermione on POCUS. Abbasi 2013, Annals of Emergency Medicine — seventy-three patients, ultrasonography vs radiography for shoulder dislocation. Sensitivity for the dislocation diagnosis — one hundred percent, ninety-five percent confidence interval ninety-three point four to one hundred percent. Sensitivity for confirmation of reduction — one hundred percent, same confidence interval. Identical to radiography for the primary outcome. The protocol uses a high-frequency linear transducer in the posterior aspect of the shoulder, humeral head viewed in cross-section relative to the glenoid. Reduction is confirmed when the head returns to its normal anatomical position. The 2018 follow-up work formalised a six-landmark protocol. For the ringside doctor — POCUS confirms dislocation and direction before reduction, confirms reduction afterwards, no delay, no radiation, no waiting for radiograph processing. It does not characterise associated fractures as well as a radiograph does, so it doesn't fully substitute for the post-reduction X-ray for first-time dislocators where you need to look for the bony Bankart and the greater tuberosity fragment. But it's a credible, rapid, ringside-deployable adjunct. ACEM has a position statement on POCUS in the ED — verify current revision.
Sulafat: Tufte — building on Hermione's point. There's a clinical decision rule called the Quebec Decision Rule, Bolvardi 2019, that asks whether radiography is needed at all in the dislocated shoulder presentation. The rule reaches one hundred percent sensitivity for concomitant fracture in patients over forty, and reduces radiograph use by about fifty percent in that subgroup. Below forty, the rule's sensitivity drops to thirty-three percent — not safe. The classical Australian rural ringside boxer is under forty, so the Quebec Decision Rule alone is not the appropriate decision tool — clinical judgement plus axial imaging remains the standard. The point isn't to skip imaging. The point is to know when you have enough imaging to act safely. The minimum dataset post-reduction is two orthogonal views. If POCUS has confirmed reduction, you still get the post-reduction X-ray. If POCUS hasn't confirmed reduction, you certainly get the post-reduction X-ray.
Charon: Right. We've got the diagnosis nailed down. Now to the central question of the episode — how do you actually reduce this thing? Osler, you're leading.
Algenib: Nine published techniques in the modern literature, and the order in which you reach for them matters more than the techniques themselves. The hierarchy I'd recommend for the rural ringside doctor in 2026 — and this differs from the historical orthopaedic teaching that still places Modified Kocher near the top — is Cunningham first, Spaso second, FARES third, scapular manipulation as adjunct throughout, Stimson if you have time and a trolley, and the older techniques as fall-back only. Let me walk through what these actually look like at the bedside.
Algenib: Cunningham first. Neil Cunningham, Australian emergency physician, described in Emergency Medicine in 2003. Patient sits upright in a chair, back straight, shoulders retracted. The affected arm is adducted, forearm flexed at the elbow, hand resting on the operator's shoulder. You sit facing the patient. Gentle longitudinal traction down the humerus — gentle. You massage the trapezius, then the deltoid, then the bicep belly. Rhythmically. You maintain conversation and reassurance throughout. The technique works on muscle relaxation, not force. The reduction often happens silently — no clunk, no palpable shift. The deltoid contour restores. The patient is sometimes surprised that nothing happened. Reported success rate around seventy to eighty-five percent as a sole technique, near one hundred percent in selected cooperative recurrent dislocators. Drug-free. Five to ten minutes of attempted relaxation without progress and you move on. This is the technique you teach the second medical officer on the ringside roster. This is the technique you teach the corner staff who hold the boxer between rounds.
Algenib: Spaso second. Spaso Miljesic, Croatian-Australian nurse specialist, described in Emergency Medicine in 1998. Patient supine on the trolley, the canvas, the floor — wherever they fell. You grasp the wrist with both hands, lift the dislocated arm vertically upward — perpendicular to the floor, forward flexed. Apply gentle sustained longitudinal traction. Add gentle external rotation. Wait. Reduction usually occurs within three to five minutes. About eighty-five to ninety percent in emergency medicine series. No special equipment. Single operator. The boxer is comfortable, you are comfortable, the corner staff can see what's happening.
Algenib: FARES third. Fast, Reliable And Safe — Sayegh and colleagues, Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery American volume, 2009. Patient supine, elbow extended, arm at thirty degrees of shoulder abduction, forearm neutral. Patient holds the opposite side of the trolley with the unaffected hand for counter-traction. You hold the patient's hand with both hands, gentle longitudinal traction, then small vertical oscillating movements — ten to fifteen centimetres up and down. You gradually abduct to ninety degrees, continuing the oscillation, then gradually externally rotate to full external rotation while continuing abduction toward a hundred and twenty to a hundred and fifty degrees. The reduction typically occurs between a hundred and twenty and a hundred and fifty degrees. Hermione, you want to give us the comparative data on this one.
Kore: Sayegh 2009 — randomised controlled trial. FARES versus Hippocratic versus modified Kocher in adult anterior dislocation. Three groups, equivalent baseline. FARES — eighty-eight point seven percent success. Hippocratic — seventy-two point five. Modified Kocher — sixty-eight percent. P value 0.033. FARES mean reduction time, two point three six minutes. Hippocratic, five point five five. Kocher, four point three two. FARES mean VAS pain score, one point five seven. Hippocratic, four point eight eight. Kocher, five point four four. No complications reported in any group. So FARES gives you the highest success rate, the shortest time, and the lowest pain score, against the two techniques that have historically dominated teaching. That's why FARES has moved up the hierarchy in international emergency medicine. Suitable for first-time dislocations including simple fracture-dislocations of the greater tuberosity. Compatible with Penthrox plus intra-articular lidocaine, no need for IV sedation in most cases. An excellent ringside default in 2026.
Algenib: Scapular manipulation as adjunct — Anderson 1982. You identify the inferior angle of the scapula by palpation. Thumb on the inferior angle, other hand on the superior medial scapula. You push the inferior angle medially and superiorly. That tilts the glenoid to receive the displaced humeral head — it's pure anatomy. Combined with Stimson traction or with FARES, success rates push into the mid-ninety percent range. Useful when the first technique isn't quite getting you there. Stimson — patient prone, arm hanging off the trolley, five to fifteen pounds of weight at the wrist, fifteen to thirty minutes for muscle fatigue. Excellent in the ED for the older fight-night referee. Not a ringside choice — you need the trolley and the time. Milch is the slow overhead abduction technique, sometimes the next thing to try after Cunningham. Leidelmeyer external rotation alone — slow, patient-tolerated, supraspinatus tension does the work. Davos self-reduction — the boxer's own knee, the boxer's own arms, gentle traction, useful to teach known recurrent dislocators at the pre-bout medical so they can self-reduce in the dressing room. Documented in the Boxer Competition Record Book. And Modified Kocher — Theodor Kocher 1870, still in many curricula, still useful as a fall-back, but the historical version applied forcefully has caused humeral shaft fractures, axillary nerve injuries, brachial plexus injuries, and rotator cuff tears. Use it gently or not at all. Spaso, Cunningham, FARES first.
Achernar: Curie. A rural-equity refrain here, because the hierarchy Osler just described isn't just an evidence ranking — it's an equity ranking. The techniques at the top of the list — Cunningham, Spaso, FARES — are drug-free or minimal-analgesia, single-operator, no special equipment. They're the techniques that work for the doctor with a single Penthrox whistle and no second clinician. The techniques at the bottom — Hippocratic traction-countertraction, the forceful old Kocher — assume two operators, full IV sedation, full monitoring. They are metropolitan-ED techniques. If a rural doctor reflexively reaches for the IV-sedation technique because that's what they were trained on, the case for retrieving the boxer to a tertiary centre to do the reduction becomes uncomfortably real — and that's a three-hour delay, a SAAS aeromedical activation, and a meaningful cost to the patient and the system. The hierarchy Osler described isn't just better evidence — it's better access. Get confident with Cunningham, Spaso, FARES and the scapular manipulation adjunct, and you can manage most ringside dislocations safely in the room you're already in.
Charon: That's well put. Onwards — analgesia and sedation. The rural ED has limited resus capacity. What's safe? Osler and Curie.
Algenib: Five real options. No analgesia at all — Cunningham in a cooperative recurrent dislocator, perfectly defensible. Intra-articular lidocaine — eighteen to twenty millilitres of one percent preservative-free lidocaine, twenty-two gauge needle, lateral approach below the acromion into the empty glenoid space, blood-tinged aspiration to confirm intra-articular, inject over thirty seconds, wait five to ten minutes. IV procedural sedation — propofol, ketamine, ketofol, midazolam-fentanyl, depending on institutional preference and patient factors. Inhaled methoxyflurane — Penthrox, the green whistle, single three-millilitre inhaler, self-administered, onset within six to eight breaths. Ultrasound-guided interscalene brachial plexus block — ten to fifteen mils of 0.5 percent ropivacaine, dense block, eight to twelve hours of post-procedure analgesia, but operator-dependent. Hermione on the comparative evidence.
Kore: Miller 2002, Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery American volume. Thirty patients randomised, intra-articular lidocaine versus IV sedation for modified Stimson reduction. No significant difference in reduction success or pain — VAS p equals 0.37. Significantly shorter ED stay in the lidocaine group, seventy-five minutes versus a hundred and eighty-five minutes, p less than 0.01. Substantially lower cost. Gould 2018 systematic review, Wilderness and Environmental Medicine. IV sedation slightly favoured for procedural success, relative risk 0.91, but intra-articular lidocaine had substantially lower complication rates — two percent versus thirteen percent. So intra-articular lidocaine trades a small reduction-success difference for a meaningful safety advantage and a meaningfully shorter ED stay. Penthrox — multiple Australian studies confirm safety and analgesic efficacy, including Coffey 2014 in the Emergency Medicine Journal. Australia is one of the few countries where methoxyflurane is licensed for this indication — it is not licensed in the United States, which matters when you read international guidelines that don't mention it. Interscalene block — Blaivas 2011, Academic Emergency Medicine, comparable to IV sedation for shoulder reduction, shorter ED stay.
Achernar: Curie — Penthrox is the Australian-specific answer for the rural ringside. TGA-listed, available institutionally under state emergency-services schedules. Self-administered, rapid onset, short duration, no IV access required, no fasting required. Contraindications — renal impairment, liver disease, personal or family history of malignant hyperthermia, pregnancy as relative, under-eighteens off-label. The boxer can hold the whistle themselves, take their own dose, and remain conscious and instructable for a Cunningham or a Spaso or a FARES. It is the technique that closes the analgesia-access gap between metropolitan and rural ED. A rural ringside doctor without Penthrox in the kit is a rural ringside doctor with one hand tied behind their back. So one practical question for any rural ED reading this — is Penthrox on your resus trolley, and is the kit current? If not, that's the first restock to organise this week.
Algenib: And one safety point on procedural sedation in the rural ED — ACEM's College Statement on Procedural Sedation and Analgesia is the governance frame. Fasting confirmed, IV access, continuous pulse oximetry, ECG, NIBP every three to five minutes, ETCO2 if available, airway equipment immediately available, second trained operator — one to sedate, one to reduce — reversal agents, recovery area. If you can't tick those boxes, you do not run an IV procedural sedation for an elective reduction. The risk-benefit then favours retrieval, or favours starting with intra-articular lidocaine and Penthrox and FARES first. Force is the enemy, sedation is not free, and the technique that needs the least drug is the technique you reach for first.
Charon: Once the head is back, what happens? Post-reduction. Osler.
Algenib: Immediate post-reduction exam. Confirm reduction clinically — restored deltoid contour, normal head position, full painless passive range. Repeat the neurovascular exam — every component you did pre-reduction. Compare. Document any new deficit. Pain VAS. Skin integrity. Then the imaging — always orthogonal. AP plus axillary lateral, or AP plus scapular Y. Position of the head, central in the glenoid on both views. Greater tuberosity fragment — displacement over five millimetres warrants orthopaedic referral. Bony Bankart — antero-inferior glenoid rim fracture. Hill-Sachs — postero-superior humeral head defect. POCUS as an adjunct if the radiograph is delayed. And then the immobilisation question.
Algenib: Internal-rotation sling versus external-rotation orthosis. Itoi 2007, Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery American volume, randomised one hundred and ninety-eight patients to internal rotation versus external rotation for three weeks. Recurrence at minimum two years — external rotation twenty-six percent, internal rotation forty-two percent. Relative risk reduction with external rotation thirty-eight point two percent, p 0.033. In patients thirty and under, the relative risk reduction was forty-six point one percent. Itoi's subsequent MRI work confirmed that abduction sixty degrees plus external rotation sixty degrees gives the best Bankart reduction. Mechanism — with the arm in external rotation, the anterior soft tissues tighten against the anterior glenoid, the displaced Bankart lesion is pushed back posteriorly and laterally, improving coaptation. Hermione on the subsequent evidence.
Kore: Mixed. Liavaag 2011, Norwegian RCT, found no statistically significant difference in recurrence at two years between the two immobilisation positions, in a population with lower compliance and older average age than Itoi's cohort. Whelan 2014, Canadian RCT, similarly no difference. Meta-analyses have been split. Earlier reviews favoured external rotation, later reviews suggest the effect is modest. Where the evidence sits in Australia in 2026 — external rotation is more biologically rational and the seminal Itoi RCT favours it, particularly in patients thirty and under. Compliance is the practical limiting factor — many patients find external rotation orthoses inconvenient. Internal rotation slings remain the default in many Australian institutions, often because external rotation orthoses are simply not stocked. The reasonable rural default — discuss the trade-off with the patient. Offer external rotation if available and the patient will comply; otherwise use a traditional internal rotation sling with explicit counselling that compliance and structured rehabilitation are the dominant predictors of recurrence. Duration three weeks, with earlier mobilisation in the elderly to reduce stiffness.
Enceladus: Fred Rogers Ross. I've been holding off but this is the natural place for me. Because the discharge conversation with the boxer is the part of this presentation that goes wrong most often — not the reduction, not the imaging, the conversation. You sit down with the boxer. They've just had their shoulder put back. The pain has dropped. They feel a bit silly about how scared they were. They want to know what happens next and when they can train again. The mistake is to default to the bureaucratic answer — six weeks in a sling, see a sports physician, here's a referral. The right thing is to be honest, in a register the boxer can hear. Try something like — "What we just did has fixed the immediate problem. Your shoulder is back where it should be. But there's a deeper thing here, and I want you to understand it. The first time a shoulder dislocates at your age, the chance of it happening again in the next year or two is somewhere between six in ten and nine in ten. That's not me trying to scare you — that's the actual number from the Swedish twenty-five-year follow-up data. Now, that risk goes down with age, and it goes down a lot if you have the joint stabilised surgically, and it goes down some if you do everything your physio asks of you for the next three months. What I need from you tonight is — you'll wear the sling, you'll come back if anything changes, and you'll see the sports physician within two weeks. We'll talk about whether you should consider surgical stabilisation, because for a competitive boxer, that conversation is worth having, even if you decide against it. I'm not telling you to stop boxing. I'm telling you to take the next month seriously, because what you do now sets up the next ten years of the shoulder."
Enceladus: And during the reduction itself — the script that works best is honesty about what you're doing and what they're going to feel. Try — "I'm going to ask you to sit up straight for me, breathe normally, and let your shoulders drop back. I'm going to massage the muscles around your shoulder until they let go. This won't hurt. It might feel like a strong stretch, and you might feel something move. If you feel a sharp pain, tell me and I'll stop. The shoulder is going to slip back on its own as the muscles relax. We're going to take five or ten minutes. I'm not going to pull or twist anything." That's not just kindness — it's clinically effective. The Cunningham technique requires patient relaxation. A patient who has been told what's happening, who is not bracing against an unexpected pull, relaxes. The technique works. A patient who has been told nothing and is bracing for a force they can't predict — the technique fails, you escalate, the procedure becomes more painful and more drug-heavy and longer. So the patient-comms script isn't a soft skill on top of the technical skill. It's part of the technical skill.
Charon: That's important. Complications and red flags now — Osler and Curie. What goes wrong, what tells you to abandon the field, what mandates retrieval.
Algenib: Recurrence is the dominant long-term complication and we've already covered the numbers. The acute complications cluster — axillary nerve neuropraxia, five to eighteen percent transient, one to two percent complete; brachial plexus stretch, highest in luxatio erecta; axillary artery injury, rare in young patients, meaningful in the elderly atherosclerotic patient and in fracture-dislocation; greater tuberosity fracture, ten to fifteen percent of dislocations in patients over forty, displacement over five millimetres warrants orthopaedic input; proximal humerus fracture-dislocation in three or four parts, orthopaedic surgical consultation is mandatory, closed reduction without orthopaedic supervision risks creating a head split; rotator cuff tear, seven to thirty-two percent in patients over forty, MRI if persistent post-reduction weakness; iatrogenic injuries from forced reduction — humeral shaft fracture from forceful Kocher, axillary nerve stretch from excessive traction, rotator cuff tear from forced abduction-external rotation, vascular injury in the elderly. Force is the enemy. Cunningham, Spaso, FARES, scapular manipulation, Stimson — they exist precisely to minimise force.
Achernar: Curie on the retrieval-criteria question. When does the rural ringside doctor stop trying and pick up the phone? Open injury communicating with the joint — that's not a reduction case, that's a transfer to orthopaedics in theatre. Vascular compromise at any stage — absent or asymmetric radial pulse, cool mottled limb, prolonged cap refill — STOP, transfer to a vascular-capable centre. Complete brachial plexus injury — flail, anaesthetic limb — transfer. Fracture-dislocation with displaced humeral head fragment on the pre-reduction film — transfer. Suspected luxatio erecta with vascular compromise — STOP, transfer. And the soft-failure criterion — three different closed techniques attempted, no reduction, worsening neurovascular status — transfer for GA-assisted reduction in theatre. For Port Pirie, that's usually Lyell McEwin in the first instance or RAH for the complex pieces, retrieval pathway via SAAS MedSTAR for the urgent transfers. For Whyalla and the Riverland, similar — your tertiary referral pathway is the one you've already established locally, and your CT-and-vascular-capable backstop is the one that matters when things escalate.
Algenib: And one specific posterior-dislocation pitfall — if you've reduced what looks like an anterior dislocation, and the post-reduction film looks "off" but you're not sure why, get a second view immediately. Posterior dislocation that has been mistaken for anterior, and "reduced" by an anterior-pattern technique, will look near-normal on the AP and dramatically wrong on the axillary. The axillary view post-reduction is the safety net.
Charon: Return to play. Boxing-specific, since that's where this material started. Osler — quick.
Algenib: Five phases. Phase zero — immobilisation, zero to three weeks. Phase one — restoration of range, three to six weeks. Phase two — strength restoration, six to ten weeks. Phase three — sport-specific functional progression, ten to sixteen weeks. Phase four — sparring, sixteen weeks plus. Phase five — competition, twenty weeks plus. The apprehension test is the critical clinical gate — patient supine, shoulder abducted ninety, externally rotated ninety, operator slowly increases external rotation. Apprehension, fear of dislocation, visible muscle guarding — positive test. A positive apprehension test is a contraindication to sparring or competitive boxing. The other gates — relocation, sulcus, drawer — all useful. By lesion type — conservative management with no structural lesion, sparring twelve to sixteen weeks, competition twenty plus. Bankart on MRI, sparring sixteen to twenty, competition twenty-four plus. Arthroscopic Bankart repair, sparring sixteen to twenty post-op, competition twenty-four plus. Latarjet stabilisation, sparring sixteen to twenty post-op, competition twenty-four to twenty-eight plus. The Boxing Australia or state federation medical-clearance form is the formal sign-off — verify the current revision via Boxing SA, Allison Goodes is the local channel for that.
Achernar: Curie. The shared-decision conversation for the young boxer's first dislocation — surgical stabilisation versus conservative management. The case for surgery — sixty to ninety percent recurrence risk in young athletes, each recurrence adds structural damage, arthroscopic Bankart repair has eighty-five to ninety-five percent return-to-sport, Latarjet is high-success but higher morbidity. The case against — some recurrences stabilise spontaneously over time, the older cohort doesn't always recur, surgical risks include infection, stiffness, hardware complications, and for Latarjet there's a small risk of avascular necrosis. The shared decision is a conversation, not a recommendation handed down. Document the discussion, document the boxer's preference, refer to the sports physician who will hold the longer-term arc with them. And do not pretend that "go back to boxing without surgical stabilisation" is a risk-free path. It isn't. The boxer needs that to be said clearly.
Charon: Last bit. Cross-topic synergy and the implementation plan. What does a rural ED actually do with this material on Monday morning? Osler, then Curie, then Tufte to land it.
Algenib: Three-step implementation that any rural ED could run this week. Step one — write or update the local dislocation pathway document, one page, the algorithm we've just talked through. Red flags at the top — open injury, vascular compromise, neurological deficit, fracture-dislocation pattern. Then the imaging decision — known recurrent with classical mechanism, defer pre-reduction; otherwise AP plus axillary or scapular Y. POCUS confirmation if available. Then the technique hierarchy — Cunningham first, Spaso second, FARES third, scapular manipulation as adjunct, with the analgesia decision matrix beside it. Post-reduction — orthogonal imaging mandatory, structured neurovascular re-check, immobilisation with the external-rotation discussion. Discharge counselling — natural-history risk, follow-up plan, return precautions. One sheet, on the wall of the resus bay, signed off by the medical director. That's step one.
Achernar: Step two — audit the resus trolley. Specifically — is Penthrox in the kit and is it current? Is a twenty-two-gauge spinal needle and preservative-free one percent lidocaine immediately accessible for intra-articular lidocaine? Is the external-rotation orthosis stocked, even one or two, so the option exists? Is the POCUS probe at the right charge level and on the right preset for shoulder views? These are five-minute audits that, if done together once, give you the gear-readiness floor for the next twelve months. Step three — train the second medical officer on Cunningham. Specifically. With a video. With supervised practice on a cooperative volunteer. The technique is teachable in twenty minutes, and the operational gain — having a second person who can run the gentle technique when you are tied up with another patient — is enormous.
Sulafat: Tufte to land the visual side. Two things. First, the post-reduction orthogonal imaging compliance audit. Schaller's data — orthogonal post-reduction imaging is not universal in well-resourced centres. Run a six-month look-back through your radiology system. Count post-reduction shoulder X-ray studies. Count the proportion that have two orthogonal views. If you're below ninety-five percent, that's the simplest, highest-yield clinical-governance fix to make. Second — the POCUS implementation. The Aussie Boxing App scoping has POCUS confirmation as a planned ringside step. The POCUS Learning Resource project, sitting alongside this episode in the Vault, is the training infrastructure for that. If your rural ED has an ultrasound machine and an emergency physician with the basic POCUS credential, the shoulder dislocation protocol — Abbasi 2013 — is one of the most teachable and most immediately useful add-ons. A six-landmark posterior-shoulder view, fifteen minutes of supervised practice, becomes a permanent capability. That's the cross-project synergy. The Aussie Boxing App gives you the boxer-specific data flow. The POCUS project gives you the imaging skill. The Shoulder Dislocation Tutorial gives you the clinical pathway. The three together are the canonical rural-ringside reduction capability for South Australia.
Algenib: And a final cross-link — the ACRRM Learning Hub project, which is being scaffolded in the Vault as the rural-generalist training substrate. The tutorial we drew on for this episode is a natural MSK module for that hub. Jacob owes a decision on that — does this become the canonical ACRRM Learning Hub dislocation module, or does it stay as a Hurn Medical asset on a separate subsite? Either is defensible. The work is the same. The hosting question is a separate question. We'll surface that in the JTR brief.
Charon: Alright. To wrap. The dislocated shoulder is the joint problem the rural Australian medical officer is most likely to be asked to manage solo, in a setting without orthopaedic backup, often with a single Penthrox whistle and a portable ultrasound. The historical teaching — forceful Kocher, IV sedation, transfer to theatre — was metropolitan teaching, and it underweighted both the evidence on minimal-force reduction and the rural-access constraints. The 2026 pathway is — Cunningham first, Spaso second, FARES third, scapular manipulation as adjunct, intra-articular lidocaine and Penthrox as the analgesia floor, post-reduction orthogonal imaging always, structured neurovascular exam pre and post, the discharge conversation that names the sixty-to-ninety percent recurrence risk honestly, the sports-physician follow-up within two weeks, and the Boxing Australia clearance pathway documented in the Boxer Competition Record Book. The boxer in the cold-open — twenty-four-year-old amateur welterweight, missed cross, classical anterior dislocation, intact neurovascular exam — gets Penthrox, gets a Cunningham, gets POCUS confirmation, gets the post-reduction X-ray series, gets the external-rotation immobilisation discussion, gets the conversation that Fred Rogers Ross walked us through, gets the sports-physician referral and the MRI within four to six weeks, gets entered into the Aussie Boxing App's Boxer Competition Record Book with all four classification axes recorded. He goes home with the suspension paperwork, knowing what the next month looks like and what the next year looks like. That's what this episode is about. That's what good rural emergency medicine looks like when it works.
Charon: Thanks to William Osler Ross, Hermione Granger Ross, Richard Feynman Ross, Marie Curie Ross, Edward Tufte Ross, and Fred Rogers Ross for joining today. Thanks to the Shoulder Dislocation Tutorial in the Vault for the substrate — that work is publicly creditable to the agentic-AI clinical-tutorial pipeline Jacob has been building. The episode landing page, the sources, and the full set of cross-links will be in the show notes. If you want to use the one-page algorithm in your own department, it's in the vault episode landing. Intro music — Comparsa by Kevin MacLeod, Incompetech, Creative Commons Attribution 4.0. Outro music — Awaiting Return, same composer, same licence. State of Play continues.
Alnilam: Thanks for listening to State of Play. Until next week.