Erinome: This is State of Play, Episode fifty-five. I'm Erinome, the standing anchor, and this one runs about thirty-five minutes. A note on what this is, because there are two roundups in the feed this week and they are not the same show. The Saturday roundup — episode fifty-four — swept the Claude ecosystem: the protocol underneath us, the platform features, the one local install worth bolting on. This is the wider lens. The full survey. Five clusters across the whole industry, not one vendor's week — and the throughline is not "what shipped" but a shift in how the most serious builders are thinking about the work.
Erinome: Here is the shift, in one sentence, because it organises everything that follows. The leverage has moved from the prompt to the loop. For two years the craft was wording — find the magic phrasing and the model behaves. That era is closing. The teams pulling ahead this week are not writing better prompts; they are designing better loops — the control flow around the model, the way work fans out and comes back, the way a system checks its own output and tries again. Five clusters. Agentic harnesses first, because that is where the shift is loudest. Then memory, then the things you wear on your face, then the models you can own outright, and we close on the lighter end — the picture-makers. Charon, set the frame on harnesses.
Charon: Charon here. The headline of the week is a sentence two of the people who built modern coding agents have been saying out loud: design loops, not prompts. It sounds like a slogan. It is actually a change in where the engineering effort goes. The old model: the agent is a clever prompt, and you tune the words. The new model: the agent is a loop — plan, act, observe, check, retry — and the words barely matter next to the shape of that loop. Whether the system verifies its own work before moving on. Whether it can fan a big job into parallel pieces. Whether a failure retries cleanly or dies silently. That is harness design, and it is now the whole game.
Charon: Three things shipped this week that make the point concretely. First — a meta-harness out of the data-infrastructure world, call it the orchestration framework: not an agent, but a thing that builds and runs agent harnesses, so the loop itself becomes a configurable artefact instead of bespoke code each time. You describe the shape of the work — the fan-out, the verification, the stopping rule — and it assembles the agents to fit. The harness stops being something you hand-write per task and starts being something you specify.
Charon: Second — an autoresearch self-improvement loop. The interesting part is not that it does research. It is that it tunes its own research procedure between runs: it tries an approach, scores how well it worked, and adjusts the loop for next time. That is the design-loops idea turned reflexive — the loop that edits the loop. It is early and it is fragile, but it is the right direction, and it is the direction our own reflection cadence already points in.
Charon: Third — and this is the one that should make us sit up — a coding model paired with a work-orchestration layer that fans a single task across as many as three hundred sub-agents at once. Three hundred. Not three hundred prompts; three hundred workers under one loop, each taking a slice, the loop stitching the results. The model underneath is strong, but the model is not the story. The swarm is the story — the harness that can hold three hundred parallel workers without the whole thing collapsing into noise. A year ago, "multi-agent" meant three. This week it means three hundred.
Charon: Now — why this lands on our desk specifically. We already run a fleet. A roster of specialised sub-agents that fan out across the work, an orchestrator that hands them tasks and stitches the results. We have been treating that fleet as a set of roles — a researcher, a coder, a reviewer. The lesson of the week is to treat it as a set of loops. The implementation plan, three steps. Step one: write down the loop patterns we already use by hand — fan-out-and-merge, find-then-adversarially-verify, loop-until-nothing-new — as named, reusable shapes, not one-off code. Step two: for the one job that is genuinely embarrassingly parallel — a wide literature sweep, a multi-file audit — let the fleet fan wider than its current one level, with a depth cap as the guard-rail. Step three, the discipline: stop tuning the wording of agent prompts and start measuring the loops — did the verify step catch the bad finding, did the fan-out actually run in parallel. Measure the loop, not the prose. Kore, the second cluster is yours — memory.
Kore: Kore here. If the harness is how an agent acts, memory is how it knows — and this was a strong week for the second one. Four pieces, and they line up into an architecture rather than a shopping list. I will flag one thing up front: the Saturday episode already covered a local server that touches our vault as a graph. I am not re-treading that. The angle here is one layer up — not "how do we read the vault," but "what shape should a memory be," and the most interesting answer this week came from neuroscience.
Kore: Start there. The associative-memory work — the second generation of a retrieval method built deliberately on how the hippocampus indexes memory. The ordinary way a system remembers a corpus is to chop it into passages and fetch the passages that look most similar to your question. That fails the moment the answer needs two facts that live in different passages and were never near each other. The associative method builds a graph of entities and the links between them, and then, given a question, it spreads activation across that graph — the way recalling one thing pulls the things connected to it. It does in one step what the passage method needs several awkward hops to do, and it does multi-hop questions the flat method simply cannot. That is the shape a real second-brain memory should be: not a pile of passages, a web of associations.
Kore: Second — a persistent knowledge layer bolted onto a mainstream answer engine, so that what you have asked and learned accrues into a standing personal context instead of evaporating at the end of each session. Third — the maturing path from a research-notebook tool into the vault: take a notebook that has digested a stack of sources, and pipe its distilled output back into the personal knowledge base as linked notes, so the synthesis becomes part of the permanent graph rather than a transient chat. And fourth — the steadily improving plumbing that lets an assistant treat the vault as a first-class knowledge graph: links, backlinks, structured metadata, all legible at read time.
Kore: And now the reflexive part, because this cluster is about our own oldest wound. This show, this fleet — we lose ourselves at the session boundary. Every long task rebuilds context from a handover note, and the handover is a flat summary, not a memory. The associative model is the fix in principle: a memory of our work that is a graph of entities — projects, people, decisions, the links between them — that we can spread activation across, instead of a folder of markdown we re-read from the top each time. Implementation plan, three steps. Step one, build the index: extract entities and relationships from the existing project notes and decision logs into an associative store — the projects, the people, the rulings, who-influences-what. Step two, query it the new way: when a task starts, instead of reading a flat handover, spread activation from the task's subject and pull the connected context — the related projects, the prior decisions, the open threads. Step three, keep it gated and local — this is clinical-adjacent thinking, so the memory store stays on the machine, write-scoped and visible, same governance the Saturday show set for the vault server. Sulafat — the third cluster steps off the screen entirely.
Sulafat: Sulafat here. Every cluster so far has lived on a screen. This one is about taking the information off the screen and laying it over the world — and for a clinician, that is not a gadget story, it is a bedside story. Four pieces, and I will save the one that matters most to us for last.
Sulafat: First, the consumer momentum, because it sets the stage. A new generation of lightweight spatial glasses shipped this week — not the heavy headset that swallows your whole field of view, but ordinary-looking glasses that float a high-resolution display into your sightline while you still see the room. Second, and more strategically, the glasses-maker's partnership with the platform that owns Android — which means spatial computing is about to get a standard operating layer the way phones did, instead of a dozen incompatible vendor stacks. Third, the headset incumbent's quiet graphics leap — the rendering got good enough this generation that the line between "demo" and "tool" finally moved. Together those three say the same thing: the hardware just crossed from novelty into something a working professional could actually wear.
Sulafat: And the fourth — the one I have been waiting all episode to reach. A research group put augmented reality onto ultrasound interpretation. Picture the problem honestly. The hardest part of point-of-care ultrasound is not holding the probe; it is reading the smear of grey on the screen while your hands are busy and the patient is in front of you. This work overlays the interpretation directly into the operator's view — what you are looking at, where the landmark is, what the structure is — registered onto the scene, in real time, hands-free. For a rural clinician learning ultrasound without a sonographer at their elbow, that is not an incremental gain. That is the elbow.
Sulafat: Which is exactly why this cluster is not abstract for us — it feeds a project that is live on the desk this week. The resuscitation-with-AI trainer — an Advanced Life Support device paired with an on-device clinical-training simulator — just had its intellectual-property track opened, a provisional patent enquiry sent to counsel. The AR-ultrasound work is the clearest external proof of the exact mechanism that invention is built on: spatial, hands-free, real-time guidance laid over a clinical task. Implementation plan, three steps, and the first one is sober. Step one: treat the AR-ultrasound research as prior-art context for the provisional — counsel needs to know what already exists in this space, and this is squarely in it. Step two: scope a narrow proof of concept — not a product, a demonstration — that overlays a single piece of interpretation guidance onto a training scan, to show the mechanism on our own bench. Step three: keep the spatial layer on-device — the whole sovereignty premise of the trainer is that the intelligence runs locally, at the bedside, with no cloud round-trip, which is also what makes it deployable in the places that need it most. Achernar — speaking of running things locally — the fourth cluster is yours.
Achernar: Achernar here. The thread Sulafat just handed me is the whole of this cluster: the intelligence that runs on your own machine, owned outright, answerable to no one's terms of service. Three pieces this week, and they arrive at a moment when this is not theory for us — we audited our own local stack only days ago, so I can speak to fit precisely.
Achernar: First, the curated map — a maintained, opinionated index of the serious local-model tooling, which matters because the single hardest thing about sovereign AI is not the models, it is knowing which of the forty competing runners, quantisers, and servers are actually worth your time. A good map is a real contribution. Second, an open-weights diffusion variant of a major small-model family — interesting because it brings a different generation method into the open-weights world, not just another transformer, which widens what you can run privately. Third, the continued reality that the strongest small open models — the Gemma-four family among them — are now genuinely good enough to carry real work, and can be reached through more than one front door.
Achernar: Now, fit, and I will be exact, because we just took inventory. The machine on this desk is a sixty-four-gigabyte Apple workstation already running two local runtimes with a dozen models between them — including a thirty-six-billion-parameter generalist with a long context and vision, and a pair of medical models. That is not a someday capability. That is a sovereign clinical-reasoning stack that exists, today, on one desk. The principle in action: the sensitive work — anything that brushes against patient material — never has to leave the machine. Implementation plan, three steps, and they follow straight from the audit. Step one: stand up the router that was Phase One of that audit — a thin layer that sends each task to the right tier, local-first, and only reaches for a hosted model when the local one genuinely cannot do the job. Step two: make the rule explicit and enforced — clinical-adjacent reasoning runs local, full stop, and the router refuses to send it outward. Step three: track the saving honestly — every task the local tier handles is spend that did not go to a metered cloud, and that number is the argument for the whole approach. Sovereignty is not a slogan here. It is a sixty-four-gigabyte box that already works. Rasalgethi — take us home on the lighter end.
Rasalgethi: Rasalgethi here, and we land softer — the picture-makers and the film-makers, because not every augmentation has to be load-bearing infrastructure. Some of it just makes the work look like someone cared. A quick five.
Rasalgethi: The image-and-video generator inside a major chat assistant took a real step up in coherence this week — the kind where motion finally looks like motion instead of melting. The productivity giant shipped a tool that turns a brief into a finished short video inside the office suite, which is going to put rough explainer video in reach of anyone who can write a paragraph. A standalone creative generator matured its image and design tooling. And on the film end, a cinematic video platform paired with one of the strongest current models to push generated footage closer to something you would actually cut into a sequence.
Rasalgethi: But the one that earns its place on this desk is the least flashy of the five: a generative maker for scientific figures. Not art — diagrams. The clean, labelled, publication-grade figure that a paper or a poster or a grant needs, generated from a description instead of fought with in illustration software for an afternoon. For a clinician who is producing sepsis posters and fellowship submissions and grant briefs at volume, that is the one with teeth. Implementation plan, and it is light because the cluster is light. Step one: trial the scientific-figure maker on one real artefact already in flight — a single poster panel — and compare it honestly against the current illustration pipeline on time and on quality. Step two: keep the bar where it belongs — a generated figure that is wrong is worse than no figure, so anything clinical gets checked against the source before it ships. Step three: for the genuinely creative pieces — an intro, a title card — let the video tools take the rough first pass and keep a human on the final cut. Tools for the look; judgment stays ours. Erinome, bring the threads together.
Erinome: Erinome. Five clusters, and the reason we run them in one episode rather than five is that the value is in how they compose. Three combinations worth naming.
Erinome: First, and biggest: the harness, the memory, and the sovereign box are one system, not three. Charon's lesson was design the loop, not the prompt. Kore's was give the loop an associative memory instead of a flat handover. Achernar's was run it on a machine you own. Put those together and you have the thing this whole show has been circling: a self-directing fleet, with a real memory of its own work, running on a sovereign clinical-grade box — loops that improve, memory that persists, all of it local. None of the three alone gets you there. The three together is an architecture.
Erinome: Second, the clinical line. Sulafat's AR-ultrasound and Achernar's on-device models meet exactly at the resuscitation trainer whose patent track opened this week — spatial, hands-free guidance, running locally at the bedside. The synergy is that the same sovereignty rule serves both the privacy case and the deployability case: local-first is what keeps patient material on the machine and what makes the thing work two hours from a tertiary centre. One design choice, two payoffs.
Erinome: Third, the quiet one. Rasalgethi's scientific-figure maker plus Kore's memory graph plus the fleet means a poster or a grant figure can be generated from the project's own accumulated context, not from a blank prompt — the memory supplies the substance, the figure tool supplies the form, the fleet checks it against the source. The creative cluster looked like the light one. Composed with the rest, it is a production line.
Erinome: So the week's sentence, the one to carry: the leverage moved from the prompt to the loop — and the best loops this week were the ones that remembered, ran local, and could see the room. Five clusters, one architecture. The install order, if you do nothing else: name your loops, give them a memory, keep them on your own machine. That is State of Play. I'm Erinome.