Alnilam: This is State of Play, Episode 35 — about forty-five minutes today. I'm Alnilam. We are going to do something a little different. We are going to interrogate the activity that the project we have been building for the last week is built around. Not the app — the activity itself. Boxing. And not the romance of it, not the stories, not the careers — the neuroscience. What the literature actually says. What pre-fight medical clearance can and cannot catch. And what that means for a clinician who finds themselves at ringside in regional South Australia signing a fighter off to compete. With me today is the Ross family. William Osler Ross will hold the clinical line. Richard Feynman Ross has the mechanism — linear forces, rotational forces, sub-concussive impact. Hermione Granger Ross has the evidence base — the donor cohorts, the case-controls, the longitudinal imaging studies. Marie Curie Ross will hold the ethics and the public-health frame. Edward Tufte Ross will translate the literature into a data architecture — what a longitudinal cognitive registry would actually have to look like. And Fred Rogers Ross is here for the conversation that has to happen in the room after the fight. Cold open first. Fred?
Fred Rogers Ross: Thank you. Fred Rogers Ross — patient communication. The scene is the Port Pirie Regional Health Service emergency department. A twenty-two-year-old amateur boxer has just won his first sanctioned bout at a Riverland tournament. He is unmarked. He is buzzing. His mother is in the corner of the cubicle on her phone, recording a voice note to his father. The ringside doctor — Jacob, in this story — has signed off the post-bout medical. The boxer has no symptoms. Nothing on examination. He is fit to leave. And he turns, on the way out, and asks the question. "Doc — long term — am I going to be alright?" And there is a silence. Because the honest answer is "I don't know," and the longer honest answer is "the literature suggests probably not all of you will be, and we have no test that can tell me which one of you it will be." That is the conversation that does not get had. That silence — that pause — is what this episode is about. We are going to fill it in.
Alnilam: Right. So with that as the frame — let us go to the neuropathology. Richard?
Richard Feynman Ross: Richard Feynman Ross — mechanism. So Chronic Traumatic Encephalopathy. CTE. What is it actually? The condition has been described in fighters since 1928 — Harrison Martland called it "punch-drunk syndrome" in a paper in JAMA, and the term dementia pugilistica followed not long after. It sat in the boxing literature as a curiosity for the better part of seven decades. What changed it from a curiosity into a public-health emergency was that in the early two-thousands, the same pathology started turning up in retired American footballers, and then in retired rugby players, and then in soccer players, and then — and this is what I want to mark — in amateur athletes who never competed professionally. The pathology was the same. The exposure pattern — repetitive head impacts — was the same. The disease is not boxing-specific. The disease is repetitive-head-impact specific. Boxing just got there first historically because the mechanism is so unambiguous.
Richard Feynman Ross: What is the pathology? You have hyperphosphorylated tau protein — p-tau — accumulating in neurofibrillary tangles in the brain. That happens in Alzheimer's disease too. But the distribution is different, and the distribution is diagnostic. In CTE the p-tau accumulates in a perivascular pattern — wrapped around small blood vessels — and crucially at the depths of the cerebral sulci. Not on the gyri, on the crests. At the bottom of the folds. This is the McKee criterion, named for Ann McKee at Boston University, and it is now the consensus neuropathological definition — the National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke ratified it in 2016 and again with a refinement in 2021. The reason the sulcal depths matter is that they are exactly where rotational shear forces concentrate when the brain decelerates inside the skull. The pathology tells you the mechanism. The tau is not random — it sits where the mechanical strain was highest.
Hermione Granger Ross: Hermione Granger Ross here — evidence base. Let me put a number on it. McKee's original 2013 staging — published in Brain — divided CTE into four pathological stages by the density and distribution of that p-tau. Stage I is the mildest: a few perivascular foci at the depths of frontal sulci, often clinically silent. Stage II is multifocal cortical involvement. Stage III is gross cerebral atrophy, septal abnormalities, depigmentation of the substantia nigra, with executive dysfunction and visuospatial impairment clinically. Stage IV is profound — hippocampal sclerosis, parkinsonism, dementia. The validation work by Alosco and colleagues out of the same Boston group in 2020 — published in Acta Neuropathologica — showed that the McKee scheme has good inter-rater reliability, and that clinical severity in life maps reasonably onto stage at autopsy. The Bieniek 2023 consensus criteria in Acta Neuropathologica — the second NINDS consensus — tightened the diagnostic threshold further and explicitly required the pathognomonic perivascular sulcal p-tau lesion as the sine qua non. CTE is not Alzheimer's. It is not normal ageing. It has a signature.
Richard Feynman Ross: And the critical word in everything Hermione just said — autopsy. CTE is diagnosed post-mortem. Only post-mortem. There is no living test. There is no MRI finding, no CSF marker, no blood test that diagnoses CTE in a living person. We can show suggestive imaging, we can show suggestive biomarkers, but the diagnosis is histological. That has two consequences for the clinic and they both matter for the episode. First: when someone asks me — at ringside, in the consult room, anywhere — "do I have CTE?" — the truthful answer is "I cannot tell you. Nobody can tell you while you are alive." Second: the literature you read about CTE prevalence is built entirely on donated brains. People who chose, or whose families chose, to send the brain to a research bank. Hermione will get to why that matters in a moment but it matters enormously.
Richard Feynman Ross: Mechanism segment. Two questions get conflated and they should be separated. Question one: what kind of force does the damage? Question two: does the force need to cause a clinically apparent concussion to do damage? Both have empirical answers and both answers are uncomfortable.
Richard Feynman Ross: On force type — there are two kinds of head impact and they do different things to the brain. Linear impact — a punch that drives the head straight backward — produces predictable contusion patterns. Coup and contrecoup. You can model it with a closed bag of fluid hitting a wall. Rotational impact — a punch that twists the head — produces shear forces inside the brain because the cortex and the deep grey matter and the white matter tracts that connect them all have different densities and they rotate at slightly different rates. The shear stress concentrates at the interfaces — grey-white junction, around vessels, at the depths of sulci. And that shear is what produces diffuse axonal injury and, over years, the perivascular tau pathology of CTE. The seminal work on this is Holbourn's in 1943 — he predicted with a physical model that rotation, not linear translation, would be the dominant injurious mechanic in head trauma. Sixty years later the imaging caught up and confirmed him. So when you watch a boxer take a clean straight cross to the chin, the punch you should worry about is not the one that snapped the head back — it is the one that twisted it. The classic head-injuring boxing punch is the hook, not the jab.
Richard Feynman Ross: On sub-concussive impact — this is the finding that should have changed combat-sport regulation a decade ago and did not. The conventional model held that you only count concussions. Diagnosed concussions. A boxer who took six bouts and was never diagnosed concussed was, on the old model, a low-exposure athlete. The new model — and new here means anything from the late 2010s onward — is that every head impact that exceeds some threshold of rotational acceleration produces some axonal disruption, whether or not it crosses the clinical threshold of concussion. Concussion is the visible top of an iceberg. Most of the cumulative neurological exposure of a boxing career is sub-concussive. Di Virgilio and colleagues in 2019 — Frontiers in Human Neuroscience — measured cognitive performance, motor cortex inhibition, and motor unit recruitment in amateur boxers one hour after a single sparring session in which no boxer was concussed. They found measurable corticomotor inhibition, altered motor recruitment, and decreased memory performance. By twenty-four hours these had returned to baseline. But the question that hangs over that paper, and over every paper like it, is — what happens when the next sparring session comes before twenty-four hours? When the recovery is not allowed to complete? When you stack a hundred such sessions across an amateur career? That is the cumulative exposure problem and that is what CTE is responding to. The headline number from the boxing-cognition literature: Bernick's group at the Cleveland Clinic showed in their longitudinal cohort that cognitive performance and brain volume both correlated with career length and number of professional fights — not with concussion count. The exposure that matters is cumulative impact, not diagnosed concussion.
Richard Feynman Ross: Two more mechanical points before I hand off. First — glove weight matters but not the way people think it does. A heavier glove distributes peak force over a longer impulse — less acute injury, more total energy delivered. The substitution is essentially neutral for cumulative exposure. Second — headgear. The intuitive case is that padding the skull reduces impact transmission. The empirical case is that headgear reduces lacerations and skull fractures but has not been shown to reduce concussion risk and may increase head-impact frequency by altering the perceived risk calculus — the AIBA dropped headgear from elite male amateur boxing in 2013 partly on the back of evidence that bouts under headgear were producing more head impacts, not fewer. Tjønndal's 2022 systematic review in the European Journal of Sport Science is the standard reference here — headgear protects against the acute mechanical insults the headgear can absorb, and is silent or marginally negative on the rotational-acceleration injuries that matter for CTE.
Hermione Granger Ross: Hermione again. Now to the cohort that everybody quotes and almost nobody contextualises. The Mez et al. 2017 study in JAMA — Volume 318, Issue 4, pages 360 to 370 — examined 202 brains of deceased former American football players donated to the Veterans Affairs–Boston University–Concussion Legacy Foundation brain bank. CTE was diagnosed in 177 of them. Eighty-seven per cent. Among the 111 former National Football League players in the cohort, CTE was diagnosed in 110. Ninety-nine per cent. Those are the headline numbers. They are real. They are also — and this is the part the public reporting almost universally drops — the result of a profoundly selection-biased cohort. The brains were donated, frequently by families who had already noticed cognitive or behavioural change in the deceased athlete, often after consultation with the Concussion Legacy Foundation, which exists in part to recruit such donations. The denominator — total NFL alumni, total former football players in the population — is not 111. It is hundreds of thousands. The fraction of that denominator with CTE is unknown.
Hermione Granger Ross: The contrasting design — and this is the one Jacob should keep in his pocket — is Bieniek's case-control work using the Mayo Clinic brain bank. The 2015 paper in Acta Neuropathologica examined 1,721 brains from a general neurodegenerative-disorders bank. None of those donors were selected on the basis of sport exposure. CTE pathology was found in 32 per cent of those with documented contact-sport participation in life, and in zero per cent of those with no contact-sport exposure. The 2020 Bieniek follow-up in Brain Pathology extended this with a retrospective contact-sport-exposure ascertainment from obituaries and yearbooks. The signal is the same: exposure to contact sport is associated with CTE pathology at autopsy; the absolute prevalence in any given population of exposed athletes is not knowable from the donor literature alone. The risk claim is sound. The prevalence claim is not.
Marie Curie Ross: Marie Curie Ross — ethics and equity. I want to put a small flag on the way that prevalence-versus-risk distinction gets weaponised. There is an industry of athlete-association push-back, going back at least to the NFL's denials of the 2000s, that uses the selection-bias critique to dismiss the donor literature entirely. "You only found CTE in 99 per cent of NFL brains because those are the brains the families donated; the real prevalence is lower." That is half-true and half-cynical. The half-true: yes, the donor cohorts are biased. The half-cynical: the bias does not point the way the industry wants. Iverson and colleagues — in a 2023 paper in the American Journal of Epidemiology — explicitly modelled the selection bias and showed that under plausible bias assumptions, the true population prevalence of CTE in former American football players is more likely underestimated by the donor literature than overestimated. Because the families who donate are also the families who lost someone who was already symptomatic — but the cumulative exposure to repetitive head impact in non-symptomatic alumni is identical, and the pathology, which precedes clinical symptoms by years to decades, is presumably present in many of them too. We cannot count them. They are alive. But the inferential logic does not let us conclude they are safe.
Marie Curie Ross: For boxing specifically the cohort literature is thinner still. The relevant numbers in the boxing-specific peer-reviewed work — Bernick's Professional Fighters Brain Health Study, the largest active prospective cohort — sits around 280 active boxers and mixed-martial-artists at the Cleveland Clinic Lou Ruvo Center for Brain Health. That is the world's leading boxing-cognition cohort and it is still small. Bernick's group has shown, longitudinally, that brain volume in regions vulnerable to CTE — thalamus, caudate, hippocampus — declines with cumulative fight exposure. Cognitive performance — particularly processing speed — declines with career length. Their 2023 Neurology paper extended the cohort into post-retirement follow-up and showed that some of the cognitive decline continues after the fighter stops fighting, which is consistent with the slowly-progressing tauopathy model. None of this constitutes a diagnostic test in life. All of it constitutes a strong probabilistic case. "X per cent of boxers have CTE" — you will see that claim made in lay press. Don't believe it. The honest claim is: boxers carry a clearly elevated risk of late-life cognitive impairment relative to non-boxers, the magnitude of that elevation is not precisely knowable from the existing literature, and the mechanism — cumulative repetitive head impact, predominantly rotational — is well established.
William Osler Ross: William Osler Ross — clinical. CTE is the long-tail risk. The acute risk is non-zero and we should not let the long-tail discussion crowd it out. Stewart and colleagues at Macquarie University published in the Journal of Science and Medicine in Sport in 2022 a retrospective analysis of Australian boxing-related fatalities going back to 1832. One hundred and sixty-three deaths over the full period. Seventy-four per cent attributed to traumatic brain injury. Eleven of those deaths occurred after the government regulatory reforms of the mid-nineteen-seventies that were supposed to make the sport safer. Ten of those eleven were traumatic brain injury. Two of the fighters were eighteen years old. Most deaths happened not in the ring but in the hours and days after — ninety-six per cent within a week. The mechanism is almost always either subdural haematoma from the rotational acceleration tearing a bridging vein, or diffuse cerebral oedema following an apparently-trivial second impact — second impact syndrome, which Richard's mechanism segment touched on.
William Osler Ross: The most-cited Australian coronial finding is the inquest into Davey Browne's death. Browne died in 2015 after a New South Wales bout. Deputy State Coroner Teresa O'Sullivan's findings, handed down at Glebe Coroner's Court, ruled the death preventable and recommended substantive reform to the New South Wales combat-sport rules — including a requirement that ringside doctors examine combatants between rounds, not only on referee call-back, after any knockdown caused by a head blow. The recommendations have been partly adopted in New South Wales. They have not been uniformly adopted nationally. South Australia's regime — administered through the Office for Recreation, Sport and Racing under the Boxing and Martial Arts Industry Act 1985 and subsequent amendments — does not currently mandate the between-rounds-after-knockdown rule. That is a Boxing-SA-conversation worth having; the Allison Goodes channel is the natural route.
Marie Curie Ross: Equity layer here. Who actually dies. The Stewart cohort is overwhelmingly young men. The age-standardised mortality rate for amateur boxing in Australia is low — in absolute numbers, boxing is far from the most dangerous sport in the country. Horse riding kills more Australians per year than boxing does. The acute mortality argument, taken on its own, does not carry the case for prohibition. What it does carry is the case for non-negotiable medical oversight — registered ringside doctor present, between-rounds examination after any head-blow knockdown, mandatory neurological evaluation post-bout, mandatory suspension windows enforced before next bout. The acute-death risk is the risk that the existing regulatory architecture has been designed against. It has not been the same risk that the CTE literature has been telling us is the larger long-tail concern. Those are two different risks. The regulator has addressed one. The other is currently unaddressed by anyone, anywhere — partly because nobody knows how.
William Osler Ross: This is the segment Jacob will use most clinically so let me be very precise. A pre-fight medical clearance — under the World Boxing Medical Handbook 2024 and 2025 editions, under the Boxing Australia Medical Commission rules, under the Office for Recreation Sport and Racing requirements in South Australia — examines and certifies the following: cardiovascular fitness to exert at competition intensity; absence of acute infectious illness; absence of injury that would impair the fighter's ability to defend themselves; serological clearance for blood-borne viruses; visual acuity; and crucially, time elapsed since the last competitive bout or concussion event, with mandatory suspension windows applied according to the outcome of the previous bout — typically twenty-eight days as a default minimum, forty-five days after a technical knockout, ninety days after a knockout caused by a head blow, longer windows after successive concussions.
William Osler Ross: What pre-fight clearance does not catch — and Jacob, listen carefully because this is what your boxer is asking when he asks the question Fred opened with — is anything chronic. The clearance examination has no sensitivity for sub-clinical white-matter changes on diffusion tensor imaging. It has no sensitivity for early cognitive decline below clinical threshold. It cannot detect CTE because nothing can detect CTE in a living person. It does not measure cumulative head-impact exposure across the fighter's career. It does not require — almost anywhere in the world — a baseline cognitive assessment that could, in principle, be tracked over time to detect decline. The boxer who walks into the consult room with no symptoms, no history of diagnosed concussion, and who passes every element of the pre-fight medical may already have stage I or stage II CTE pathology — perivascular tau at the depths of the frontal sulci — and the clearance examination will not see it.
William Osler Ross: The clearance is not negligent for failing to detect what is undetectable. The clearance is not pretending to do more than it does. The clearance is exactly what its regulatory frame describes: an acute fitness-to-compete assessment. The misalignment is between what the clearance is and what the public — including many boxers, many coaches, many parents — think it is. They think it is a long-term safety guarantee. It is not. It cannot be. And the responsibility for that mismatch sits not with the ringside doctor; it sits with the absence of any structure — anywhere in Australian boxing — that conducts longitudinal cognitive monitoring. That structure does not exist. That is the gap. That is the gap the BoutBook conversation has to reckon with honestly. We will come back to it.
Hermione Granger Ross: Imaging and biomarkers. What is there. What it does. What it does not do.
Hermione Granger Ross: Structural MRI in active boxers shows reduced grey-matter volume in the caudate, putamen, thalamus, and hippocampus — Bernick's longitudinal cohort, published serially through Neurology and the AAN abstract record, is the most rigorous single source. The volumetric changes correlate with cumulative fight exposure, in a dose-response pattern, and continue to progress for some years after retirement. Diffusion tensor imaging — DTI — shows reductions in fractional anisotropy in major white-matter tracts, particularly the corpus callosum and the superior longitudinal fasciculus. These are the same tracts where shear-induced diffuse axonal injury is mechanically most likely. The DTI changes appear before clinical cognitive symptoms in a meaningful proportion of fighters and they correlate with the imaging signature of CTE at autopsy in the small number of cases where both have been obtained. The 2025 work out of Bernick's group, presented at RSNA — using a refined DTI-along-the-perivascular-space technique to assess glymphatic clearance — extended this further by showing that waste-clearance function in the brain declines with cumulative head impact in cognitively impaired fighters relative to controls. The implication: the substrate for chronic neurodegeneration is being laid down years to decades before the clinical picture declares itself.
Richard Feynman Ross: Biomarker side. Serum neurofilament light chain — NfL — is an axonal protein that leaks into the blood when axons are disrupted. Shahim and colleagues, working out of the Karolinska, published the seminal contact-sport NfL paper in Neurology in 2017 — boxers had elevated serum NfL seven to ten days after a bout compared with three-month rest baseline, with the magnitude of elevation correlating with both the number of head impacts received and the presence of post-bout grogginess. CSF studies — Zetterberg and colleagues earlier, in PLOS ONE in 2013 — showed that cerebrospinal fluid phosphorylated neurofilament-heavy chain was elevated in over eighty per cent of amateur boxers between one and six days after a bout, even in fighters who experienced no loss of consciousness and no clinical symptoms of concussion. The biomarkers can detect sub-concussive axonal injury that the clinical examination misses entirely.
Edward Tufte Ross: Edward Tufte Ross — data architecture. The implication of all of this for a longitudinal cognitive registry — which is what we are building toward for BoutBook — is the following. We have, in 2026, three classes of measurable signal in living boxers. First class: structured cognitive testing — SCAT6 for the acute concussion case, ImPACT or CogState for serial baseline-and-follow-up, with effect sizes that are small but detectable across a multi-year window if the baseline is reliable and the follow-up cadence is regular. Second class: structured event logging — exposure metrics. Number of bouts, number of rounds, opponent weight class, knockout-suffered events, knockdown-suffered events, sparring rounds per training week, gloved-weight-bag exposure. Cumulative-exposure dose, in a unit a clinician can read at the bedside. Third class: biomarker — serum NfL is now obtainable on a single Simoa-platform venipuncture for tens of dollars per assay; not yet routinely indicated but plausibly within reach for a research-grade cohort. Imaging — DTI, volumetric MRI — is research-grade only at present and won't sit inside the app.
Edward Tufte Ross: None of these signals diagnose CTE in life. None of them ever will, because CTE is a histological diagnosis. What they collectively constitute is a longitudinal trajectory — a graph, over time, with the boxer's own baseline as the reference. If the trajectory is flat, the boxer is reassured. If the trajectory bends — cognitive decline, exposure-dose accumulating into the band where Bernick's cohort started to see deficits, NfL elevations that fail to return to baseline — the clinician has a signal that justifies the harder conversation. The conversation about whether to continue. That is what the imaging and biomarker literature actually licenses. It does not license diagnosis. It licenses informed decision-making over time. And the data infrastructure to support that does not currently exist in Australian boxing. Anywhere. That is the substantive product gap.
Hermione Granger Ross: Comparison. Because boxing is often framed as singularly dangerous and the comparative data complicates that picture. The CTE signal is not exclusive to boxing — it has been documented in autopsy series across American football, rugby union, rugby league, Australian rules football, soccer with documented heading exposure, ice hockey, and mixed martial arts. Mez's NFL cohort is the largest series. The Bieniek Mayo case-control extends the signal to high school and college contact-sport exposure. Soccer heading is the most-discussed civilian-population exposure: cumulative heading exposure correlates with cognitive performance changes and with imaging signatures comparable to those seen in low-exposure boxing. Female soccer players experience approximately 8.2 concussions per 10,000 athlete-exposures versus 3.6 for male soccer players, and with similar heading exposure female players show more extensive white-matter microstructural change. The relative-risk picture is not boxing one, everything else zero. It is contact sport with repetitive head impact, with boxing at one end of the exposure spectrum and recreational soccer at the other.
Marie Curie Ross: Two equity points before we move on. First: the AFL and NRL have, in the last five years, paid out very large concussion-related settlements and have been forced to engage seriously with the CTE literature — in part because their player cohorts are large, white, middle-class, and well-represented in the press. The boxing cohort is smaller, demographically less politically powerful, and historically less white — a 2022 historical review noted that between 1912 and 1980, fifteen per cent of Australian boxing titles went to Aboriginal fighters at a time when Aboriginal Australians were perhaps two per cent of the population. The same overrepresentation of low-socioeconomic-status backgrounds in boxing — Indigenous fighters, recent immigrants, regional and remote participants — that gives the sport its romance also gives it its political invisibility. Reform of combat sport in this country has not been driven by the same forces that reformed AFL concussion protocol. We should be clear-eyed about that.
Marie Curie Ross: Second equity point: women in boxing. The women's amateur boxing literature is sparse — the women's data gap is severe — and most of the existing CTE and concussion literature is derived from male cohorts. We do not know, in any robust way, whether sex differences in concussion biology that have been documented in soccer and football — women have higher symptom burden, longer recovery, more extensive white-matter change for a given exposure — translate to boxing. We do not know whether the structural sex differences that exist in women's amateur boxing rules — two-minute rounds versus three, fewer championship rounds — adequately compensate. Bernick's PABHS cohort has a women's sub-cohort and that data is being accumulated. As of 2026 it is too small to drive practice change. This is a data gap that BoutBook, if it is built thoughtfully, could materially help close — by collecting longitudinal women's-boxer data structured for research-grade extraction. That is the equity argument for building the product, not against.
Marie Curie Ross: The clinician's bind. Jacob — and any ringside doctor, any GP signing a pre-participation form, any sports physician supervising a returning fighter — is being asked to certify medical fitness for an activity whose long-tail risks are real and currently unmitigable. The clinician cannot detect the chronic pathology that the activity is most likely to cause. The clinician's signature on the form does not — and the literature does not let it — constitute a guarantee of long-term neurological safety. The clinician is signing only what the form actually attests: acute fitness to compete. The misalignment between that narrow attestation and the broader public expectation of safety is structural, not individual. It cannot be resolved by being a better doctor. It can only be resolved by changing the structure.
William Osler Ross: That said. The clinician is not absolved by structural failure. The clinician carries — in conscience and in professional duty — the responsibility to be honest with the fighter. The pre-bout medical is not a confessional. It is an opportunity to have the conversation that the public reporting and the regulatory architecture do not have. The conversation goes: "I am clearing you for tonight. The form does not let me say more. But I want you to understand that the things this form checks are short-term things. The longer-term consequences of repeated head impact are real, they are not detectable by anything I can do today, and the only protection you have against them is to limit your cumulative exposure — by training thoughtfully, by accepting suspensions in full, by considering how many fights you ultimately have in you. I am not going to make that decision for you. But I am going to ask you to make it with the information." That is a five-minute conversation. It is achievable in a busy ringside or pre-bout clinic. It is currently almost never had. Adding it as the default closes the gap that the clearance form structurally cannot close.
Fred Rogers Ross: And now to the conversation itself — because the way it is had matters as much as the fact that it is had. The twenty-two-year-old who just won his first bout is not in a state to hear a lecture about long-tail neurodegeneration. He is in a state to hear that you respect what he just did. So start there. "That was a clean win. You looked composed. I am happy with how the medical went." Then the bridge. "There is one thing I want to make sure I have said to you tonight — partly because nobody said it to me when I was your age, and I think you deserve better than that." Then the substance, brief and not catastrophising. "The form I just signed clears you medically for tonight and for the suspension window after. What it does not measure — what nothing measures — is the cumulative effect of all the head contact across a career. Boxing carries a long-term cognitive risk that is real, that we cannot test for, and that you have some agency over by how you choose to train and how many bouts you ultimately take. I am not telling you to stop. I am asking you to know." Then the offer. "If at any point — months from now, years from now — you want a baseline cognitive assessment so we have something to compare against, or you want to talk through what the trajectory looks like, I want you to know that door is open." And then you let it sit. You do not push. The boxer's autonomy is the point.
Edward Tufte Ross: This is the synthesis segment. All four of us together. Tufte first.
Edward Tufte Ross: The product BoutBook is being designed as. Before this episode. The version that sits on the project landing currently. Digital Boxer Competition Record Book, ringside medical workflow, bout-to-bout suspension auto-enforcement. It is a compliance product. The implicit pitch is "we will make boxing safer by making the existing rules more enforceable." The pitch is true. It is also — and the literature we have walked through tonight makes this concrete — it is also not the most defensible thing the product is. The most defensible thing the product is — once the literature has been honestly read — is the only longitudinal record of an Australian amateur boxer's career-length head-impact exposure plus serial cognitive baseline that could, in principle, detect harm early. Nothing else in the Australian boxing ecosystem does that. Sport:80's Locker product collects medical history at registration. revolutioniseSPORT collects nothing clinical. BoxSafe-the-existing — the ANABA-aligned competitor — is a sport-management product without a cognitive-monitoring layer. Boxing Australia does not maintain such a record. The structural gap is open. That is the wedge the literature actually licenses.
Richard Feynman Ross: The mechanism layer. What the product would have to do to fill that gap. Three things, none of them currently in the MVP scope as it stands. First — a structured exposure log. Every bout, every round, every knockdown, every knockout, every sparring session above some intensity threshold, captured in a unit the clinician can read. Cumulative exposure dose, on a graph, growing over career time. Second — a serial cognitive baseline. SCAT6 acute, plus a brief structured cognitive assessment — ImPACT or CogState equivalent — administered annually at pre-season medical, with the boxer's own baseline as the reference and the trajectory tracked. Third — a documented informed-consent process that names the long-tail risk explicitly at registration and at each annual re-registration, so the boxer is making the choice to continue with current information, not legacy assumptions.
Hermione Granger Ross: The evidence-base layer. What the data the product would collect could do for the field. The Bernick cohort is the world's leading prospective boxing-cognition cohort and it sits at around 280 fighters in one centre. A nationally-deployed Australian amateur boxer-cognition register inside BoutBook, even if it captured only the bouts and the annual cognitive baseline for the BA-affiliated cohort, would within five years be one of the larger structured datasets in the world. With appropriate de-identification, governance, and an institutional research partner — RACMA-pathway, ACRRM-Learning-Hub adjacent, possibly a university partnership through the College — that data could meaningfully contribute to the question the field cannot currently answer: what does the cumulative-exposure-to-cognitive-trajectory curve look like for amateur boxers in particular. The Mez and McKee cohorts are NFL alumni. The Bieniek cohort is mixed contact sport. There is no equivalent for amateur boxing. There could be.
William Osler Ross: The clinical layer. What the product would change in the consult room. The current state — what I described in segment six — is that the pre-fight clearance is an acute assessment and the long-tail conversation either does not happen or happens disconnected from any data. BoutBook reframes the consult. The clinician opens the boxer's longitudinal record on the iPad. The exposure dose is visible. The serial cognitive baseline is visible. The trajectory of NfL — if biomarker work is added — is visible. The conversation Fred described becomes "this is your trajectory; this is what we are watching; this is where the literature suggests we would start to be concerned." It moves from abstract risk-counselling to concrete shared-decision-making. That is a substantively different clinical interaction. It is also — and I think this is the part Jacob and his future co-founder should sit with — it is also the version of the product that justifies clinician-grade fees and clinician-grade regulatory positioning. The compliance product is worth what compliance products are worth. The longitudinal-clinical-record product is worth substantially more, both commercially and ethically.
Edward Tufte Ross: The re-positioned wedge restated, in one sentence: BoutBook is the only longitudinal record of an Australian amateur boxer's career exposure and cognitive baseline that could, in principle, detect harm early — and the boxer's clinician is the audience that record is designed for. Compliance is a feature. Longitudinal cognitive monitoring is the product. That is the version that the literature, honestly read, justifies. The implications for the MVP scope are not trivial — the exposure-log schema and the SCAT6/CogState integration are real engineering work, and the consent flow needs legal review — and it is a decision Jacob owes. We will not make that decision tonight on a podcast. We will flag it for the JTR brief.
William Osler Ross: Practical. The artefact that comes out of this episode is a one-page CTE-informed pre-fight clearance and post-bout monitoring protocol. Something Jacob could in principle pitch to Boxing SA. Tufte will read the structure. I will commentate.
Edward Tufte Ross: The protocol has four parts.
Edward Tufte Ross: Part one — baseline at first registration. New boxer registers with BA-affiliated club. Documents collected: SCAT6 baseline cognitive assessment, with structured cognitive screen — ImPACT or CogState — at the boxer's discretion. Documented informed-consent statement signed, naming the long-tail cognitive risk in plain English. Career exposure log opened — zero bouts, zero rounds, zero knockdown events.
William Osler Ross: And part one is the one that does not currently happen anywhere in Australian amateur boxing. The boxer's first sanctioned bout currently happens with no baseline. There is no comparator for any later assessment. That is structural and it is fixable.
Edward Tufte Ross: Part two — pre-bout clearance, current World Boxing Medical Handbook standard, plus exposure-log review. Check cumulative exposure. Check that the most recent post-bout suspension has been fully observed. Check that there has been no concussion event inside the relevant window. Sign clearance. Add the exposure projection — if you fight tonight, your career-bout total advances to X; the literature suggests cognitive trajectory begins to deflect in the Y to Z fight range.
William Osler Ross: That added line — projecting forward — is not in any current pre-fight clearance form anywhere in Australia. It is the change that moves the form from acute-fitness attestation to shared-decision-making prompt.
Edward Tufte Ross: Part three — post-bout monitoring, on top of the current acute clinical examination. Document number of rounds completed, knockdown-suffered events, blow-count if observable, referee-call-back events, post-bout SCAT6 if symptomatic — and append to the longitudinal exposure log. Issue suspension per current rules. Schedule the annual cognitive re-baseline at the appropriate offset.
Edward Tufte Ross: Part four — annual re-registration. Repeat SCAT6 or equivalent. Compare to baseline and to most recent prior. Flag if trajectory is deflecting against the boxer's own historical reference — not against a population norm. If deflecting, refer for the harder conversation — sports physician with concussion expertise, neurologist with sports-medicine experience, with the longitudinal record in hand.
William Osler Ross: That protocol fits on a single A4 sheet. It is implementable. It requires the BoutBook data layer to do its part. It requires Boxing SA to sanction it as the local trial — which is the Allison Goodes conversation. And it requires Jacob to write up the consent flow with proper legal review, because the consent statement that names the long-tail risk in plain English is a non-trivial document and it is the part of the protocol most likely to be challenged. Worth doing properly. Worth not skipping.
Marie Curie Ross: Curie here for the synergy segment. Tie back. This episode connects to four other pieces of work in the Vault that Jacob has running.
Marie Curie Ross: To Aussie Boxing App. Direct. The re-positioning we have argued for — from compliance product to longitudinal cognitive record — changes the risk register. R1 — Sport:80 entering Australia — becomes less existential, because the competitive moat is not the compliance UI but the longitudinal cognitive data that no incumbent has. R2 — Boxing Australia declining to endorse — becomes a stronger case for endorsement, because the longitudinal cognitive record is a defensible national health-data asset that BA cannot generate without help. R10 — concussion protocol misalignment — becomes easier to mitigate, because the trajectory data tells you who is at risk. The Allison Goodes talking points sharpen. The disclose moment now has substance to disclose. The BoutBook MVP scope needs a decision — keep the tight d4 wedge, or expand to include the cognitive-baseline layer. That decision sits with Jacob and is in the brief.
William Osler Ross: To Shoulder Dislocation Tutorial and SoP e32. The sports-medicine pattern. Shoulder dislocation was the acute-injury counterpart; this episode is the chronic-injury counterpart. Together they cover the two faces of ringside medicine in the Australian context. They share a clinical-tutorial structure that the canonical template at `Vault/Ada/Templates/clinical-tutorial-canonical.md` now serves; this episode does not need to re-derive it. The ACRRM Learning Hub module corresponding to this episode — a candidate boxing-neuroscience module — would sit alongside the MSK shoulder dislocation module published 2026-05-24. Decision for Jacob whether to commission the Hub module from this episode immediately or to defer.
Edward Tufte Ross: To POCUS and ringside imaging. Adjacent. POCUS at ringside picks up the acute subdural that this episode names as the dominant mechanism of acute boxing death. The Abbasi protocol for shoulder; the FAST protocol for abdomen; transcranial Doppler with optic-nerve-sheath diameter measurement — not yet a ringside standard anywhere, but not implausible — for early raised-intracranial-pressure detection. Another candidate module, downstream.
Hermione Granger Ross: To the broader research portfolio. This is the one to sit with. Jacob's research interests — agentic AI in clinical workflow, social determinants of health, Aboriginal health equity, charitable fundraising — all converge on the question this episode raised. The boxer's longitudinal record, properly governed under Indigenous data sovereignty principles, contributed to via an agentic-AI-augmented clinical workflow, with the analytic capacity to detect cognitive trajectory deflection at the individual level — that is a research program. It is publishable. It is fundable. And it is sitting under-recognised inside what is currently being called a sport-management app. That is the larger thing this episode has surfaced.
Alnilam: Alnilam back. The honest version, then the close.
Alnilam: The honest version. The literature says that boxing — like all contact sports with repetitive head impact, more concentrated than most — carries a real long-tail neurological risk. We cannot diagnose CTE in life. We can detect signal in imaging and in serum biomarkers. We can measure cumulative exposure. We can hold a serial cognitive baseline. We do not, in Australian amateur boxing in 2026, do any of that systematically. The pre-fight medical clearance is an acute-fitness assessment and it cannot — by design or by science — be more than that. People will keep boxing. People will keep coaching their kids into boxing. People will keep finding in it meaning, discipline, dignity, a way out of harder lives. The clinician's job is not to prohibit. The clinician's job is to be honest about what the form attests and what it does not, and to build — where it can be built — the structure that would let a boxer make an informed decision over the course of a career.
Fred Rogers Ross: And the close. The twenty-two-year-old from the cold open. He is going to fight again. He will probably win his next bout too. Maybe he wins a state title. Maybe he goes further. The conversation we did not have at ringside the first time — the one this episode has tried to script in — that conversation does not change the trajectory of his career on its own. What it does is change whether he ever has to ask, twenty years from now, the question that nobody asked him at the start. Did I know? Did anybody tell me? If he knew. If somebody told him. Then the choice was his. That is what we owe him. That is the case for going forward with this — clear-eyed, with the data, with the document, with the door open.
Alnilam: That is the episode. Thank you Marie, Edward, Hermione, Richard, William, Fred. State of Play, Episode 35. The neuroscience of boxing. With us next time.