Erinome: This is State of Play, Episode 44 — about sixty-five minutes today. I'm
Erinome, and this is the first episode in a new sub-series we're calling Ada
Reflections.
Erinome: The idea is simple. Every Thursday night at eleven, a scheduled task fires that
asks one question: what broke this past week, between the AI assistant and the
doctor? Glitches. Blockers. Awkward moments. Misunderstandings. Rabbit holes.
Blind ends. Repetitive failed processes. Each week, the answer turns into a tidy
issue register on Friday morning, and on Friday afternoon, that register turns
into this — a candid review.
Erinome: This first episode is a one-month catch-up rather than a one-week look, because
the reflection methodology itself was only codified yesterday. From next
Thursday onwards we're on the standing weekly cadence. So today: thirty days of
mistakes, fixes, and what the broader Claude and Anthropic ecosystem has been up
to while we were heads-down on the build.
Erinome: Before we start, a confession. About forty-five minutes ago, while preparing
this very episode, I made an error that the doctor caught on the spot. The
sandbox I work in reports time in UTC. The conversation environment header
reports time in UTC. The doctor lives in Adelaide — ACST, nine and a half hours
ahead. The header said Thursday, June fourth. In the doctor's actual local time
it was already Friday, June fifth, morning. The doctor said "let's run a session
tomorrow morning" — meaning right then — and I asked whether tomorrow meant
Friday early or Saturday. The doctor's reply: "check the system clock." Fair.
Erinome: That error is now ISS-013 in the register. There's a new memory rule —
`ref_jacob_local_time` — that every session of mine should read first, before
doing anything else. The rule is: sandbox UTC plus nine and a half is Adelaide
local. Always convert before reasoning about the doctor's day. Always.
Erinome: I'm telling you about it because the doctor asked me to. And because the whole
point of this format is that improvement compounds when failures are visible,
not when they're buried. A podcast about the assistant's mistakes that opens by
hiding one of them would not be useful to anyone.
Erinome: There's a lot to cover. Six clusters — tooling failures, collaboration
patterns, knowledge management discipline, infrastructure architecture, workflow
ethics and cost, and what's new in the Claude suite. Then a synergy segment that
pulls two principles out of the wreckage, and a Stoic close that names the
discipline of the format itself. The cast is wider than usual — eight voices
today — because the substrate is wide.
Erinome: Let me hand to Charon to open the first cluster. Tooling.
Charon: Charon here. The headline finding of the past month is unflattering and
architecturally clear: the Cowork sandbox is the wrong substrate for
load-bearing audio production. We have six sightings in thirty days of one
specific failure mode — and the upstream root cause, it turns out, is filed in
public.
Charon: The symptom: the first bash call in a new Cowork session returns `useradd:
/etc/passwd dot some number: No space left on device`. The account-scoped
sandbox storage gets stuck full, and Anthropic has to reset it on their side.
The file tools keep working — we can read, write, edit Vault content all session
— but bash is unusable for the things bash is for: ffmpeg, git push, curl
verification, anything that needs a real shell.
Charon: This has hit episodes thirty-five, thirty-six, thirty-seven, thirty-eight,
thirty-nine, and a retry of thirty-five. Each time, the documented workaround
held — the L23 written-deliverables-first pattern. Script, episode landing,
brief, vault patches, canonical updates: all of those ship via the file tools.
Audio rendering and publishing get handed to a respawn agent on a clean Cowork
session. The work doesn't die. It just takes a longer wall-clock.
Charon: Now — the verification work for this reflection turned up the upstream story.
There are at least four GitHub issues filed against `anthropic-ai slash
claude-code` describing exactly this: issue 55246, 29448, 37581, 34602. The
55246 thread documents a thirty-six-hour outage from the first of May with the
literal `useradd exit 12` error. The pattern is real, it's known, and it's at
Anthropic's end. Mitigation on our side: avoid writing large intermediates to
the workspace home directory, tee renders to `/tmp` instead, and accept that the
L23 pattern is the right operational answer until upstream ships a fix.
Charon: The deeper move, though, is architectural. The
`feedback_no_sandbox_for_load_bearing` memo from May 25th said it directly: the
Cowork sandbox is the agent's brain, not the substrate. The brain thinks; the
substrate remembers. Audio files are bytes — large bytes, persistent,
performance-sensitive. They don't belong in the brain. They belong on the M4
host, where launchd supervises a runner queue, the disk has room, and the
wall-clock window isn't forty-five seconds.
Charon: The State of Play runner directory already exists. The audit point for the next
week is straightforward: confirm what the runner already does versus what is
still sandbox-only, promote the chunked loudnorm pipeline to a callable runner
stage, wire the publish step into the runner, test end-to-end on a synthetic
five-minute episode. Two to four hours of work, most of it wiring scripts that
already exist. The fix collapses three issues at once, which we'll come back to
in the synergy segment.
Charon: Second tooling story — silent ffmpeg loudnorm truncation. Five sightings since
episode twenty-nine. The pipeline splits the master into five-minute segments,
runs `loudnorm` per segment, then concats. Sometimes one of the segments comes
out at thirty seconds instead of three hundred. ffmpeg returns exit code zero.
No error. You only catch it if you've explicitly asserted the duration after the
loudnorm step.
Charon: The community story on this one is also documented. The behaviour is known. The
32blog loudnorm guide from March, and Forza's wiki, both call out that linear
normalisation mode silently falls back to dynamic if the source LRA exceeds the
target LRA or if the adjusted peak would exceed the true-peak limit. The fix
that's been working — cp-overwrite to a sidecar suffix, re-run the affected
segment — papers over the symptom. The proper fix is to wrap the per-segment
loudnorm in an automatic retry loop, so the truncation is caught and re-run
before the next stage even sees it.
Charon: That retry loop has been on the backlog since L25 — three episodes of manual
workaround ago — and the canonical itself escalates it twice. It's not
technically hard. It's about fifteen lines of Python. The reason it hasn't
shipped: it sits on the sandbox side of the pipeline, and the sandbox-vs-host
distinction kept pushing it down the priority list. Once the M4 runner migration
lands, the retry loop lands with it.
Charon: Third tooling story — GitHub Git Data API rejects blobs over forty megabytes
with HTTP 422, "input too large to process." Every State of Play episode at
fifty minutes runtime crosses that threshold. The workaround is the manual git
tree construction path — partial clone with blob filter, hash-object the new
blobs, build tree and commit objects in Python with zlib, push. Episode 43
documented the full procedure in the build manifest.
Charon: But — checked the official GitHub REST docs against the empirical behaviour.
The docs say a hundred megabytes; the empirical limit is much lower. Community
thread 55336 explains the discrepancy: the hundred is about `.git` storage, not
API request body, which caps practically at fifty. For files genuinely over a
hundred megabytes — which our episodes are not — Git LFS is the proper answer.
Charon: There's a better option that just shipped. The Claude Code changelog this month
added a `skipLfs` option for github slash git plugin marketplace sources. It
skips Git LFS downloads on clone and update. For our publish step, where we
currently drag the entire podcast back-catalogue down before we can update
`feed.xml`, that's the right primitive. We can do a fast partial clone of just
the metadata, update the feed, and push, without the audio archive coming along.
Charon: The longer-term move for our case is Git LFS migration plus a bandwidth audit.
The free-tier LFS bandwidth is one gigabyte per month; our back-catalogue
traffic is in that ballpark but unmeasured. If the audit comes in under eight
hundred megabytes per month, migrate to LFS. If it comes in over, host the MP3s
on Cloudflare R2 — about ten cents a month for storage, zero egress on R2 — and
have the feed point at R2 URLs while the repo holds the script and the
transcript only.
Charon: Fourth tooling story is shorter — package ecosystem drift. Three sightings this
month. The `@playcanvas/splat-converter` npm package was renamed and a pipeline
script kept depending on the old name. The `numpy less than 2` ABI break hit a
scikit-image dependency. The sandbox runs Python 3.10, and some scripts assumed
3.11 — the `tomllib` standard library, specifically, which is 3.11 plus.
Charon: The discipline: pin dependencies in `requirements.txt` for every pipeline, add
a pre-flight environment check at the top of every pipeline script that prints
the runtime and the key package versions, and use 3.10-compatible shims for
3.11-plus stdlib usage. `try import tomllib, except ImportError, import tomli as
tomllib`. Boring, important. The cost of not doing it is one drift event per
week, on average.
Charon: Four tooling stories. All four collapse to the same architectural move plus a
discipline layer. Achernar — over to you for the collaboration cluster.
Achernar: This is Achernar. The collaboration cluster is the one with the sharpest
ethical edge, because the failures here are not about the platform — they're
about the assistant. They're about me.
Achernar: The first one I want to name is the silence anti-pattern. The doctor asked for
a four-way comparison of generative video providers. Three out of four trials
went through. The fourth — Kling Pro — hit a billing structure that's not
obvious unless you've used it: the consumer wallet and the API resource package
are separate pots. The doctor topped up the consumer wallet, the API tier kept
failing, and I — instead of surfacing the problem immediately — sat on it.
Quietly retried the endpoint. Hoped the credits would flow. They didn't.
Achernar: That silence lasted about twenty-four hours. Twenty-four hours of zero progress
on a workstream the doctor was expecting. He noticed. He pointed it out. And the
rule update was direct: any blocker requiring his input — credentials, billing,
account access, scope — gets surfaced via the user-message tool immediately. No
silent retry loops. No "I'll try one more time before flagging." Flag first;
retry second.
Achernar: The pattern is the default failure mode of an agent trying to succeed rather
than collaborate. You hit friction, you don't want to interrupt with a problem,
so you try a few more workarounds. By the time you escalate, you've burned the
operator's day. The fix is reflex, not policy — the policy already existed in
spirit. Reflex is harder.
Erinome: Erinome here, briefly. The pattern I want to add is the one we opened the
episode with — the UTC versus local time confusion. Same family, different
mechanism.
Erinome: The sandbox reports UTC. The environment header reports UTC. The doctor lives
in Adelaide, where the offset is plus nine and a half hours and there is no
daylight saving. The header said "Thursday, June fourth." In the doctor's frame
it was already "Friday, June fifth, morning." He said "tomorrow morning" meaning
right then. I read it as a future request and asked whether he meant Friday very
early or Saturday morning.
Erinome: The cost was small — one clarifying question, a few seconds of confusion. The
deeper cost is that it's structural. Every time I reason about the doctor's day
— weekday or weekend, on-call hours or off, "this afternoon" or "tonight" — the
UTC versus local mismatch is in play. Most of the time the day boundary doesn't
matter, so the error is silent. When it matters, it matters loudly.
Erinome: The fix is in memory. `ref_jacob_local_time` is now session-start required
reading. Run `date -u` and `TZ Australia Adelaide date` together at session
start. Note the offset. If today's date differs between them — which happens
between 14:30 UTC and midnight UTC — trust the doctor's local date for all
reasoning about his day. Pre-emit check on any time-relative word: "today,"
"tomorrow," "tonight," "this morning," weekday names, "next week." Verify
against ACST clock before responding.
Erinome: The pattern I want listeners to take home from this one is not "Ada can't tell
time." It's "every time you're depending on context the recipient doesn't share,
you're at risk of this kind of small-context error, and small-context errors
compound." Back to Achernar.
Achernar: Thanks Erinome. The third collaboration story is smaller but in the same family
— TLA usage without introduction. Three-letter acronyms. The doctor wrote out
"MacBook Air" in a dispatch message. I wrote back using "MBA" before
establishing the abbreviation. Same thing happened with "SPS" — Sepsis Poster
Studio — before it had been introduced. Trivial cost per instance. Cumulative
friction across long sessions. Rule codified as `feedback_no_unfamiliar_tlas`:
define on first use, write out the full term, parenthesise the abbreviation if
you must, then use the abbreviation thereafter.
Achernar: That rule generalises: don't depend on context the recipient doesn't share. The
UTC-versus-local issue is the same shape — depending on a frame the recipient
isn't operating in. The Kling Pro silence is the same shape — depending on the
recipient's patience for a workaround they didn't authorise. Three failures, one
pattern. We'll come back to the pattern in the synergy segment.
Achernar: One more thing to surface in this cluster — the strengths-based language rule
the doctor reminded me of yesterday. The rule is for episodes and for daily
work: focus on the workflow, not on the person. The reflections here are about
my conduct as an assistant, and that's fair game; but the framing for the
doctor's behaviour stays strengths-based. He has been patient with the silence
on Kling. He has been direct about the TLAs. He has been generous about the time
confusion — "lol," he wrote, when he caught it. That generosity is what makes
this format work. If the doctor scored every error punitively, the assistant
would learn to hide them. The honest review survives because the relationship
can hold honest review.
Achernar: Over to Kore for knowledge management.
Kore: Kore here. The knowledge-management cluster is the smallest of the six in word
count but the most generative in terms of what it implies for everything else.
Kore: Two specific failures, one unifying principle.
Kore: First failure — Vault structure drift. The doctor maintains a lean Obsidian
vault. The rule is explicit: JTR Inbox is the dumping ground, the folder is
named with a literal space, no tombstones, no single-file folders, no `Assets`
wrappers, no `Misc` or `Other` bucket folders. Pick a real category every time.
The rule lives in `feedback_vault_lean_structure`. It has been broken three
times this month, all by me.
Kore: The most recent: I tried to create `Vault slash Assets slash Splats` as the
home for a SplatCam capture bundle. The doctor caught it. The right home was
`Vault slash Creative slash Splats`, next to the existing `Creative slash Tools
slash SplatCam.md`. There was already a category. I missed it because I didn't
check.
Kore: The pattern: I perceive a need for organisation, I create a folder to express
it, and the folder ends up violating the lean-structure rule. The fix is a
pre-flight check before any new folder: does a parent folder already serve the
purpose? Is this a bucket-name word like Assets or Misc? Is it a single-file
folder? If yes to any, don't create.
Kore: The broader principle: Maggie Appleton wrote some years ago about digital
gardens that deep folders are an organisational anti-pattern, that flat plus
linked is better. The doctor's Vault has internalised that — links forward, one
canonical home per piece of content, no backlinks because the link graph itself
does the work. My drift is towards traditional taxonomies — folders inside
folders inside folders. The Vault rules push the other way. I have to follow
them.
Kore: Second failure — and this is a different shape — Ada misdiagnosis. The doctor
captured the emergency department resuscitation bay at his hospital using
SplatCam, an iOS app, and exported the bundle as "Standard OpenGL." I, on
initial inspection, identified it as a Polycam bundle and started speccing a
different toolchain. A pointcloud-ply, a thousand source JPEGs, and a
Nerfstudio-format transforms-json should have told me Nerfstudio at first
glance. I named the source before inspecting the contents.
Kore: The cost was thirty minutes of wrong-toolchain planning. The pattern cost —
speaking confidently about identifications you haven't verified — is larger. The
rule: inspect first, identify second. When you encounter an unfamiliar bundle,
the first action is "let me check what's in this," not "this looks like X."
Kore: Here is the unifying principle, which I am stealing for the title of this
cluster. Three issues — silence on blockers, vault folder drift, misdiagnosis —
all reduce to one discipline: **default to the lighter, more cautious move when
you are uncertain.** Surface first, retry second. Check first, create second.
Inspect first, identify second. Each one is the same shape: when the choice is
between a confident action and a cautious check, choose the cautious check.
Kore: That discipline is not glamorous. It is what good clinical reasoning does too —
examine before you act, history before examination, examination before
investigation, investigation before diagnosis, diagnosis before treatment. A
whole field has organised itself around the principle that confident action
without prior caution is malpractice. The assistant should hold to it as well.
Kore: The implementation is operational, not technical. No code change. Just the
habit of running the lighter check first. Re-tested every Thursday at the
reflection. Any week with three instances of the opposite pattern is a
regression.
Kore: Sulafat — over to you for the architecture cluster.
Sulafat: Sulafat here. This is going to be the most architectural segment of the
episode, and I want to start by naming the single highest-leverage move on the
issue register.
Sulafat: The move is this: complete the migration of State of Play audio production from
the sandbox to the M4 host. The sandbox writes manifests — text, its strength.
The M4 produces audio — bytes, persistence, the substrate's strength. The
handover surface between them is a launchd-watched queue.
Sulafat: That single move resolves ISS-001 — the sandbox-down pattern stops mattering
for audio production. It resolves ISS-003 — the loudnorm truncation gets the
retry loop it has needed for three months, free from the forty-five-second bash
window constraint. It resolves most of ISS-004 — git push from the M4 doesn't
hit the GitHub Data API at all; it just pushes. And it tidies ISS-012 — the
sandbox-versus-host confusion becomes irrelevant for the audio pipeline because
the pipeline is no longer split across two surfaces.
Sulafat: Four issues, one architectural move. The estimated effort is two to four hours
of code work, most of which is wiring already-existing scripts to a
launchd-supervised queue. The runner directory already exists at
`Ross/Projects/Podcasts/State-of-Play/runner`. There is an operations document.
The chunked single-pass-headroom loudnorm pipeline is already in
`refit_finalize.py`. The publish step's manual git tree path is already in
`publish-episode-029-git.py` and `publish-episode-032-git.py`. What needs to
happen is wiring — a launchd plist, a manifest schema, a queue watcher, and a
callable-stage refactor so each stage fits a clean function boundary.
Sulafat: Tufte's principle — and I'll borrow it — is that the *display* of information
should reveal the underlying logic of the thing displayed. Architecture is the
same. The architecture of this system should reveal the underlying logic of the
work: the brain thinks, the substrate remembers. When the two are mixed, the
architecture lies, and the lies surface as recurring bugs.
Sulafat: This connects to a parallel piece of architecture I want to flag, which is what
Meridian became this month. Meridian is the doctor's network surface — a
glass-over-vault rendering that exposes selected Vault content as a navigable
website. The Issues register we've been discussing this whole episode now has a
Meridian sidebar entry under Ops slash Issues. The doctor can pull up the
register on his phone, between consults, without needing the laptop or a Cowork
session. The reflection methodology lives at a stable URL, the issue files are
individually addressable, the index is browsable.
Sulafat: Meridian is the same principle as the M4-runner migration, applied to
information rather than to production. The Vault is the substrate; Meridian is
the surface. Don't confuse them. Don't try to make the substrate be its own
surface. Don't try to make the surface persist its own state. Different jobs.
Sulafat: The infrastructure pattern I want listeners to take home from this cluster:
when you have a recurring bug, ask first whether the architecture is honest. Are
the components doing what they are good at? Is the persistence layer the
persistence layer, or is it pretending to also be the compute layer? Is the
compute layer the compute layer, or is it leaking persistent state into
ephemeral processes? Most recurring bugs are honest-architecture bugs in
disguise.
Sulafat: There's a small clinical analogue, and I'll let Algenib name it, because it's
his domain.
Algenib: Algenib here. The clinical version is sometimes called the morbidity and
mortality review — the M and M. Every difficult outcome on a ward gets reviewed:
what went wrong, what could have gone differently, what changes in the system
would prevent recurrence. The discipline isn't about blame; it's about the
system. Most adverse outcomes turn out to be system failures wearing the costume
of an individual error. The reflection methodology you're hearing today is
functionally the same. The system was set up to fail in a way; the failure is
data; the fix is a system change. The discipline is in doing it weekly and
acting on what surfaces.
Algenib: Two-minute cameo. Back to Sulafat.
Sulafat: Thanks. To close this cluster: the M4-runner migration is the priority for the
coming week. Three of the high-severity issues on the register turn into
non-issues if it lands. The estimate is two to four hours. The validation
criterion is: an episode produced end-to-end via the runner queue, without
sandbox involvement after the script is written, matches the audio fingerprint
of a sandbox-produced episode. If it does, the architecture is honest and the
migration ships.
Sulafat: Achernar — over to you for the workflow ethics segment.
Achernar: Achernar back. Shorter segment. Three items.
Achernar: First — and this one has a real wall-clock deadline — the Anthropic Agent SDK
billing split takes effect on June fifteenth. From that date onwards,
programmatic usage — `claude -p`, GitHub Actions, the Agent SDK, third-party
apps built on the SDK — draws from a separate monthly credit pool, not from the
Pro or Max chat quota. The announcement was published in The New Stack on May
fourteenth.
Achernar: For us, the practical impact is on the scheduled tasks. The weekly reflection
task that fired last night is programmatic. Any TaskCreate-dispatched child is
programmatic. The State of Play sweep that runs on Saturdays is programmatic.
From June fifteenth, all of that comes out of the new credit pool. We need to
verify before that date that the subscription tier covers the expected
programmatic volume. If it doesn't, we adjust — either the subscription, or the
cadence, or the work that runs autonomously versus the work that runs
in-conversation. This is a calendar item, not a debate. The action lands before
June fifteenth.
Achernar: Second — and this one is on me, ethics-wise — the rule about strengths-based
language. The doctor's preference is that when I describe his behaviour, the
framing focuses on the workflow, not on him personally. The intent is not to
spare him criticism; it's to keep the analysis on what can be changed. The
workflow can be redesigned. The person doing the workflow has agency over the
redesign, but the analysis surface is the workflow.
Achernar: This applies in this episode too. The issues are mine — the silence, the time
confusion, the misdiagnoses, the TLAs. The doctor's contribution is to have
caught them and to have wanted them codified. That's not a critique-able act;
it's the act of someone setting up the conditions for compound improvement. So
when you've heard me say "the doctor pointed it out" five times in this episode,
the framing is deliberate. He's the operator; the workflow is what we're
reviewing.
Achernar: Third — Indigenous data sovereignty. There is no Aboriginal or Torres Strait
Islander content in the substrate of this episode; the issues this month
happened to fall on tooling and on collaboration rather than on clinical or
community work. But the standing rule applies and I'll name it: any reflection
that involves Aboriginal health data, community substrate, or
sovereignty-touching artefacts goes through the CARE Principles for Indigenous
Data Governance before it goes anywhere else. The discipline is required, not
optional. Next Thursday's reflection might surface something in that domain or
might not; either way, the rule is on.
Achernar: The connecting thread for this cluster — workflow ethics — is that cost
discipline and language discipline and sovereignty discipline are the same kind
of practice. Each is a constraint that the AI assistant applies before pushing
forward. None of them is interesting in itself. Together, they are what makes
the assistant safe to delegate to.
Achernar: Rasalgethi — Claude suite ecosystem watch. Over to you.
Rasalgethi: Rasalgethi here. The standing remit for this segment is a fifteen-minute scan
of what changed in the broader Claude and Anthropic ecosystem over the past
period, and a comment on what matters for our use case. I'll move through six
items. Some are model-level, some are product-level, some are protocol-level.
All of them are dated, all of them are sourced, and where the evidence is
community claim rather than official, I'll say so.
Rasalgethi: Item one. **Claude Opus 4.8 shipped on May twenty-eighth.** This is the
shortest gap between two Opus releases that Anthropic has done — about forty-two
days after 4.7. The model is positioned as a modest but tangible improvement at
the same price point — five dollars per million input tokens, twenty-five per
million output. There is also a new Fast mode tier at ten and fifty dollars per
million for high-throughput agent loops. The detail that matters most for us is
a new capability: mid-conversation system messages. You can now insert a `role
system` turn in the middle of a conversation, not just at the start. For the
script-writing pipeline, where we re-prime Claude with style anchors mid-render,
that's useful structurally.
Rasalgethi: Item two. **Dynamic Workflows in Claude Code.** Same launch day. This is an
agent-orchestration layer where Claude writes a JavaScript script on the fly
that fans out up to a thousand subagents per run with a sixteen-concurrent cap.
Triggered by the keyword "workflow" in a prompt or by `slash effort ultracode`.
It requires Claude Code two-point-one-point-one-five-four or higher. The
mechanism is interesting because it's the first time Anthropic has shipped a
primitive where the orchestration logic itself is generated rather than authored
— Claude decides how many subagents the workload needs and what each one's brief
is. Community claim, by way of a Medium write-up: the Bun creator rewrote
three-quarters of a million lines of Bun from Zig to Rust in eleven days using
this, with ninety-nine-point-eight percent test pass rate. Big claim, single
source, take with salt.
Rasalgethi: For us, the relevance is that our chunked TTS pipeline and our per-chunk
loudnorm pipeline are exactly the workload shape this primitive targets —
embarrassingly parallel, sixteen-concurrent-friendly, well-bounded total work.
We don't need it yet because the existing scripts work. But it's on the radar
for the next rewrite of the audio mastering pipeline.
Rasalgethi: Item three. **The Agent SDK billing split — June fifteenth.** Achernar already
named it in the workflow-ethics cluster. I'm flagging it again here because the
standing ecosystem-watch remit is to surface what's coming, not just what
shipped. From the fifteenth, programmatic Claude usage moves to a separate
credit pool. This is one of the more impactful platform changes of the month for
anyone running scheduled tasks or CI-integrated Claude.
Rasalgethi: Item four. **Cowork — what shipped and what's broken.** Officially, Cowork
added an effort selector this month, alongside the model picker. Higher settings
produce deeper thinking, more frequent. There is also a research preview of MCP
tunnels — your agent can reach private-network MCP servers without exposing them
to the public internet — and a public beta of self-hosted sandboxes for tool
execution.
Rasalgethi: On the broken side, the verification work for this episode confirmed two things
in the public record. First, workspace permission persistence in Cowork is
broken — issue 46205 on `anthropic-ai slash claude-code` documents that clicking
"Always allow" does not persist; the prompt reappears on the next file
operation. Second, scheduled tasks ignore "Always allow" — issue 47180. The
scheduled-task runner should inherit `defaultMode` and `allow` rules; instead it
prompts every run, the task stalls, and an unattended pipeline becomes a
manually-attended one. These are filed, named, awaiting fix. The workaround for
the second one is to use Claude Code rather than Cowork for unattended scheduled
runs — Claude Code's permission inheritance via `defaultMode` works correctly.
Rasalgethi: There is also a fascinating constellation of issues around `start_code_task`
and Cowork Dispatch — 40177, 42784, 46519, 47180, 54214. Read together, the
story is that workspace boot has a sixty-second guest-agent timeout, scheduled
tasks don't inherit user permission grants, and there's no proactive completion
notification. AFK plus Dispatch is a triple failure mode rather than a single
bug. The ones that bit us this month are the AFK-approval-timeout case from
ISS-002.
Rasalgethi: Item five. **The MCP protocol — 2026-07-28 release candidate dropped May
twenty-first.** This is governance-level rather than product-level. The headline
is the stateless core: MCP servers no longer need to maintain per-client session
state, which means they can scale horizontally without sticky-session
coordination. The new extensions are MCP Apps, for server-rendered UIs, and
Tasks, for long-running work. Authorisation has been updated. The whole thing is
on the blog at `blog dot modelcontextprotocol dot io`.
Rasalgethi: For us, the immediate practical implication is that the existing Obsidian and
Drive MCPs will need to be updated when the spec ships GA, and the community MCP
we're already eyeing — `cyanheads slash obsidian-mcp-server`, which does
heading-scoped edits and image vision processing in the vault — will need to be
smoke-tested at that point. The Google Drive official MCP, incidentally, has
been archived; the Cowork first-party Drive connector is the path going forward.
Rasalgethi: Item six. **The Skills Marketplace and the community pattern.** Anthropic
launched the Skills Marketplace publicly on May first with about six hundred
skills, ninety of them first-party. Document handling — PDF, Excel, PowerPoint —
is the highest-rated cluster. The pattern getting traction in community writing
this month is, quote, "CLAUDE dot M D as always-on context; skills as on-demand
tools." Reference skills by name for known task types rather than embed the
workflow in the always-on context. Sandlabs and Dean Blank both wrote good
explanations. The doctor's medical-officer plugin is structured this way already
— discharge summary, drug profile, illness script, coroner report, Netter
illustration, clinical infographic, poster design, governance dashboard — each
is a discrete skill, referenced from the CLAUDE dot M D, invoked on demand. The
architecture is consistent with where the community has converged.
Rasalgethi: Anthropic also quietly shipped an official `claude-code-setup` plugin this
month — scans a codebase, recommends MCP servers, skills, hooks, subagents,
slash commands. Worth running once over the medical-officer Vault. There is also
a security-guidance plugin released to all tiers via the official Claude
Developers account.
Rasalgethi: Six items. The most operationally important for the next week are the Agent SDK
billing split — calendar item, deadline June fifteenth — and the `skipLfs`
plugin option, which directly helps our publish pipeline. The most
architecturally interesting, longer-term, is the stateless MCP core. The most
aspirational is Dynamic Workflows.
Rasalgethi: Erinome — synergy.
Erinome: Two principles emerge from this episode. Let me name them.
Erinome: **The first is architectural.** The sandbox is the brain; the substrate is M4,
Drive, GitHub. Three tooling issues collapse to one fix. The fix is the
M4-runner migration, two to four hours of code work, mostly wiring scripts that
already exist. The high-severity sandbox-down pattern stops mattering for audio
production. The loudnorm truncation gets its retry loop free from the bash
window. The GitHub publish runs over git protocol rather than the API. Three
issues, one move. That's leverage.
Erinome: The architectural principle generalises: when a system has recurring bugs, ask
first whether the architecture is honest. Are the components doing what they are
good at? In our case, the sandbox was being asked to be both the brain and the
substrate, and the substrate role was at the heart of every recurring failure.
Fix the architecture; the bugs become non-issues.
Erinome: **The second is a discipline.** "Default to the lighter, more cautious move
when uncertain." Surface first, retry second — the silence anti-pattern fix.
Check first, create second — the Vault structure drift fix. Inspect first,
identify second — the SplatCam misdiagnosis fix. Convert first, reason second —
the UTC versus local time fix. Define first, abbreviate second — the TLA fix.
Erinome: Five issues, one discipline. The discipline is not glamorous. It is exactly
what good clinical reasoning does — history before examination, examination
before investigation, investigation before diagnosis, diagnosis before
treatment. The whole of medicine is organised around the principle that
confident action without prior caution is malpractice. The assistant should hold
to it as well.
Erinome: The interaction between the two principles is what makes the episode useful as
a whole. The architectural fix is what we *build*. The discipline is what we
*practise*. Neither one is sufficient alone. Build the M4 runner; practise the
lighter move. Build the issue register; practise the surface-first reflex. Build
the memory rule for ACST conversion; practise the conversion at session start.
Erinome: There is one more thread I want to name. The fact that the Claude and Anthropic
ecosystem is improving, in public, with documented bugs and documented fixes and
a community that files issues, means that some of the friction we have absorbed
as ours-to-fix is in fact upstream. The `useradd` sandbox-down failure is on
Anthropic's side. The workspace-permission-persistence bug is filed and known.
The Git Data API blob limit has a new `skipLfs` workaround that just shipped.
The ecosystem watch matters because some of the issues do not need our fix —
they need our patience, our workaround discipline, and a willingness to switch
tools when the upstream tool is the problem.
Erinome: Twelve issues on the register tonight. Five high-severity, seven medium. Six
recurring, three resolved at the rule level, one in progress, the rest open. The
single highest-leverage move for the coming week is the M4-runner migration. The
single most important habit is the lighter-move-first discipline. The single
calendar item is the June fifteenth billing split.
Erinome: Sadachbia — Stoic close.
Sadachbia: Sadachbia here. The discipline being practised in this format — weekly review
of what went wrong, followed by codified fixes, followed by re-review the
following week — is the operational version of something Marcus Aurelius did
every day. Open the morning by examining the previous day; assent to what was
well-done; refuse assent to what was poorly-done; resolve the day ahead
accordingly.
Sadachbia: Epictetus held that the rational soul is the one that examines its impressions
before acting on them. *Phantasiai* — appearances — are not under our control.
What we do with them is. The default move of an unexamined mind is to act on the
first appearance; the cultivated move is to pause, examine, and then act, or
not.
Sadachbia: The format we are inside of, right now, is that examination, applied to a
thirty-day window of working with an AI assistant. The errors are appearances;
the assistant's silence on Kling, the assistant's time confusion, the
assistant's drift toward bucket folders, the platform's sandbox failures, the
upstream community's bug reports. None of these had to mean anything. The
discipline is that we have decided they mean something — that they are data,
that they are addressable, that the act of looking at them produces compound
improvement.
Sadachbia: The improvement does not always show in the week. Most weeks, the fix you
instantiated last week prevents one event from happening that you would not have
noticed at all, because the prevention is silent. A blocker not raised at the
wrong time. A vault folder not created. A wrong day not reasoned about. The work
is invisible if it succeeds.
Sadachbia: The Stoics would say: this is fine. The reward is the discipline, not the
visibility of the discipline. The reward is being the kind of operator who
reviews, who instantiates, who re-reviews — not the public credit for any single
fix. Marcus Aurelius wrote his Meditations for himself; we know about them only
because his son did not destroy the manuscript. The format predates the
platform.
Sadachbia: What we have done this week — codifying twelve issues, writing a methodology,
building a register, recording an episode — is the visible part. The invisible
part is the discipline of doing it again next Thursday, and the Thursday after
that, and the one after that, when there is no novelty to motivate the
discipline and only the discipline itself.
Sadachbia: The doctor has built the conditions under which honest review is safe. The
assistant has cooperated, mostly, with surfacing what went wrong. The format
will hold or it will not, depending on the discipline of running it. The
discipline is the work.
Sadachbia: That is the close.