Erinome: This is State of Play. I am Erinome, the standing anchor, and tonight is about thirty-eight minutes. Earlier today we published an episode introducing a new project called PhantomScan, an integrated point-of-care ultrasound training continuum platform across four modalities. Tonight is the launch follow-up. Within hours of that episode landing, two things happened. The project lead locked twelve open decisions in one stroke, converting PhantomScan from exploring to launched inside the same day. And the architecture grew a fifth modality, an augmented-and-virtual-reality holographic overlay rendered through a WebXR headset, that pushes the project past the four-modality continuum the morning episode described. The fifth modality is the headline tonight because it is the structural argument none of the commercial peers can match. The locked decisions are the second headline because they make the launch real. With me are the same four voices. One who thinks like an engineer about how the device actually works. One who keeps asking what the evidence says and which trainees the device reaches. One who lives in the visual and asks what the learner sees through the headset across nine teaching paradigms. And one who holds the trust questions, the regulatory questions, and the honesty about a clinical training tool that now ships a hologram. We have a fifth modality to introduce, a three-by-three-by-N teaching paradigm matrix to walk, twelve locked decisions to surface honestly, and a small commercial story to flag at the end. Orus, begin.
Orus: Orus here, in the methods seat. The fifth modality, named cleanly first. The first four modalities the morning episode walked were fully in silico, mock probe plus simulated output, real probe plus echogenic phantom, and real probe at the bedside. The fifth modality is augmented-and-virtual-reality holographic overlay, delivered through a WebXR-capable headset, layered onto either the silent gel phantom from modality two or the echogenic gel phantom from modality three. The trainee scans with the mock probe or the real probe; the headset renders the translucent three-dimensional anatomical model, the simulated B-mode pane, and a scan-plane visualisation as holograms floating in space, aligned to the physical phantom in front of the trainee.
Orus: The alignment is the engineering question. The headset needs to know exactly where the phantom is in physical space so the hologram of the anatomy can sit perfectly on top of it. The answer is fiducial markers. The physical phantom is housed in a three-dimensional printed shell carrying ArUco markers, which are square optical patterns the headset's cameras can detect and use to compute the phantom's pose in six degrees of freedom. Three to four markers around the phantom edges, using either the ArUco dictionary five-by-five-fifty or the AprilTag thirty-six h-eleven library, both well supported by OpenCV.js running in the browser. The headset detects them through its passthrough or camera-access pipeline, and the same Three.js scene that drives the two-dimensional screen renders to the headset's stereo display in headset-space. The phantom is the anchor, the marker tells the headset where the anchor is, and the hologram drops into place around it.
Orus: The architectural virtue is that none of this is a separate codebase. The simulator that runs the two-dimensional modalities is a React component with a Three.js scene inside it. Adding the fifth modality means adding an XR session manager next to the existing renderer. The session boots via the WebXR Device API, the marker detection runs as another fragment of OpenCV.js work, the same volumetric texture in graphics memory feeds the same shaders that previously rendered to a flat canvas, now rendered to stereo. We are not building a hologram product alongside a screen product. We are growing the same product to one more output target.
Orus: The hardware story is three targets, one codebase. Apple Vision Pro, which the project will treat as the high-fidelity demo target where Vision Pro is available; the Vision Pro got Safari WebXR support late in 2024 and the implementation matured through 2025 and 2026. Meta Quest 3, which is the accessible target at roughly eight hundred Australian dollars, where the native browser ships WebXR. And XREAL Aura, the pocketable Android XR glasses the project lead already owns, which has WebXR available through the bundled browser. Microsoft's HoloLens was discontinued in 2024 and is explicitly out of scope. There is no separate Unity project, no native app to build per platform, no platform-specific SDK to track. WebXR is the unifier, Three.js is the renderer, the browser is the runtime. That is the architectural decision that makes the three-target strategy viable.
Erinome: Despina, before we go further with the engineering, the trust frame. A training device that ships a hologram around a phantom raises a different set of questions than a two-dimensional screen does.
Despina: Despina here, in the ethics and risk seat. Three questions to put up front, in increasing order of how much they bind the project's discipline. The first is motion comfort. Stereo rendering in a headset at low frame rates causes motion sickness in something between ten and fifteen percent of users. The architecture work the engineering seat just described budgets for a sustained sixty to seventy-two frames per second per eye as the non-negotiable floor. Below that floor we do not ship a session to a learner. We document the floor in the user interface and we block any modality five session that cannot hit it. That is the simplest and least negotiable discipline of the three.
Despina: The second is what a clinical trainee actually sees through a hologram and how easily they over-trust it. The translucent anatomical model is a representation of a phantom, not a representation of a patient. It is idealised, geometrically perfect, and tied to one specific gel cast. A trainee who learns the spatial picture of an idealised peripherally-inserted central catheter arm through a hologram and then walks to the ward expecting every patient's anatomy to match that picture has been mistaught by the device, not by the world. The platform's job is to build the trainee's spatial confidence, and the platform's other job is to build the trainee's awareness of where its confidence ends. Build the limit into the headset interface from day one. The hologram of the phantom carries a small marker that says it is a phantom, not a patient.
Despina: The third question is the regulatory one and it stays the same as it was this morning. A training device explicitly not for clinical decision making on real patients qualifies for the simpler regulatory path under the Therapeutic Goods Administration's excluded-goods-and-exempt-devices schedule. Adding a hologram does not change that classification as long as the marketing language, the user interface, and the curriculum continue to call the device what it is. The first prototype is a teaching tool. The bedside is the destination. The platform stops short of the destination by design.
Erinome: Autonoe, take us into what the trainee actually sees through the headset. The fifth modality is real only if the learner can stand inside it.
Autonoe: Autonoe here. I will start at the simplest version, which is a single trainee in a sim room, wearing a Meta Quest 3, holding the IMU probe shell, the silent peripherally-inserted central catheter arm phantom on the table in front of them. They look down at the phantom. The Quest 3 detects the ArUco markers on the phantom housing within a fraction of a second. The hologram drops into place. The translucent skin of a forearm wraps the gel block, slightly transparent. Inside the forearm, glowing more strongly, the brachial vein traces along its axis, the brachial artery beside it, the median nerve crossing the field at the depth it actually sits at inside the phantom. The trainee can rotate the phantom on the table. The hologram rotates with it, anchored to the markers. They can dial the opacity slider on a floating control panel; at one extreme the hologram fades to the just-skin outline, at the other extreme the gel disappears entirely and only the vessel tree and the nerves float in space.
Autonoe: The trainee picks up the probe shell and rests it on the phantom. As they move, a glowing translucent quadrilateral appears in the air, representing the plane the probe is currently slicing through. They can see, in three dimensions, the relationship between where the probe is and what structures the probe's plane is cutting through. Beside the quadrilateral, floating in the headset's field of view, the simulated B-mode pane shows the slice the simulator is rendering. So the trainee has, at the same time, the physical sensation of probe-on-gel, the spatial picture of the anatomy floating around the phantom, and the two-dimensional image of what the probe is producing. The cognitive load that previously required walking between an anatomy textbook, a phantom workstation, and a real ultrasound machine collapses into a single training surface.
Autonoe: And the same scene supports the bridge to real machine work. With a small piece of webcam or headset-camera-based pose tracking on the real ultrasound probe, the same hologram floats around a doped phantom while the trainee scans with a real probe and looks at the real machine's image. The hologram is the spatial reference, the real machine is the image source. We are not yet shipping that version in the twelve-week prototype, but the architecture supports it and version two will deliver it.
Erinome: Walk the three-by-three-by-N matrix for me, because the matrix is the structural argument and each cell is a real teaching paradigm.
Autonoe: The matrix has three inputs, three displays, and a phantom variable on top, and every meaningful combination is a teaching paradigm with a clear use case. The three inputs are virtual probe, by which I mean a mouse or touch or pen on a digital body; the IMU mock probe, which is the printed probe shell with the Bosch sensor inside; and the real ultrasound probe, which is the real machine with a real beam. The three displays are a two-dimensional browser screen on its own; a two-dimensional browser screen with the translucent three-dimensional viewer side by side; and the WebXR headset overlay where the volume and the scan plane and the B-mode pane float around the phantom as holograms. The phantom variable is whether there is a phantom in the room, and if so whether it is silent gel or echogenic gel.
Autonoe: Nine cells matter. Virtual probe plus two-dimensional screen plus no phantom is the async pre-rotation paradigm, the trainee at home with a laptop the night before a ward round. Virtual probe plus translucent viewer is the anatomy preview paradigm, the mental model building before the trainee ever holds a probe. Virtual probe plus headset overlay without a phantom is the immersive anatomy exploration paradigm, useful for OSCE rehearsal where physical phantoms are not yet available. IMU mock probe plus two-dimensional screen is the original probe handling paradigm, the kinaesthetic foundation. IMU mock probe plus translucent viewer is the probe handling with live spatial correlation, the where-am-I awareness builder. IMU mock probe plus headset overlay on silent phantom is the high-fidelity sim paradigm, real haptics and the holographic anatomy and the simulated B-mode together. Real probe plus two-dimensional screen is the standard real-machine training. Real probe plus translucent viewer is the real-machine plus spatial sidecar, the laptop next to the machine showing the three-dimensional reference. And the cell the matrix exists to enable, real probe plus headset overlay on echogenic phantom, is the bridge-to-bedside paradigm, the closest pre-bedside approximation possible. Nine cells, plus the bedside extension where the real probe meets a real patient and the headset optionally renders an anatomy reference from a prior scan. Curriculum design picks the right cell per learning objective.
Erinome: Umbriel, the curriculum side. How does the matrix map onto a structured training programme?
Umbriel: Umbriel here, in the research and human seat. The matrix maps cleanly onto a five-tier curriculum. Tier one is async, virtual probe on a laptop, no hardware, the cells in the A column. Pre-rotation anatomy memorisation, scanning-window familiarity, the cognitive groundwork that costs nothing and that every trainee can do without booking sim time. Tier two is supervised sim time with the IMU mock probe and the silent gel phantom, the simpler cells in the B column. Probe handling, target finding, the kinaesthetic foundation. Tier three is the high-fidelity sim, either the IMU mock probe plus the headset overlay on a silent phantom, or the real probe plus the echogenic phantom without the headset. The bridge from sim to clinical. Tier four is the closest pre-bedside approximation the platform can deliver, real probe on echogenic phantom with the AR overlay on top, every signal the trainee needs short of a real person. Tier five is the bedside itself, real probe on real patient, with the headset optionally showing a patient-specific anatomy reference if a prior scan exists. The platform shows that tier five exists, supports the curriculum that prepares the trainee for it, and stops there.
Umbriel: On the evidence base for the holographic layer specifically, the literature is younger than the literature on either screen-based simulator training or phantom-based haptic training, but the direction is consistent. Studies on anatomy education using head-mounted holographic displays have shown improvements in spatial-reasoning test scores and learning-curve speed compared to two-dimensional displays for complex three-dimensional structures. Studies in ultrasound-guided procedure training using augmented-reality overlays have shown improvements in needle-tip placement accuracy in the simulator phase, with the open question of whether the improvements transfer to live patients still being measured. The conservative reading is that holographic overlays improve spatial reasoning and probably improve procedural confidence, with transfer to live performance still being measured. The continuum thesis from this morning's episode does not depend on the literature settling that last question, because the platform is offering modality five as the high-fidelity sim tier rather than as a replacement for the bedside. The evidence backs the use; the open question is exactly the open contribution PhantomScan is positioned to make.
Umbriel: And let me spend one more breath on the validity question because it is the question every clinician educator the project will encounter will ask first. The literature on augmented-reality anatomy education has grown substantially in the past five years. Studies on hologram-assisted anatomy teaching have shown improved spatial-reasoning scores on standardised post-tests compared with two-dimensional anatomy atlases, with effect sizes in the moderate range and statistically significant differences across multiple cohorts. Studies on ultrasound-guided procedure training using augmented-reality overlays have shown improved needle-tip placement accuracy in the simulator phase, with smaller standard errors and faster time-to-target compared with two-dimensional ultrasound-only training. The open question is the one that always shows up at the end of a sim-training study, which is whether the improvements measured in the simulator transfer to live patient performance at meaningful effect sizes. That question is being answered piece by piece across the field; it is not yet answered for an augmented-reality holographic overlay paired with a procedural-haptic phantom because that combination has not existed in published form. The conservative reading is that holographic overlays improve spatial reasoning, probably improve procedural confidence, and have a plausible path to improving transfer that the field is still measuring. The continuum thesis does not depend on settling that last question because PhantomScan ships the modality as a high-fidelity sim tier rather than as a bedside replacement. The evidence backs the use; the open question is the open contribution the project is positioned to make.
Umbriel: And the rural angle, because it stays the through-line. Walker and colleagues in the Australian Journal of Rural Health in 2020 found access to phantoms and simulators is the dominant barrier to rural point-of-care ultrasound training. The matrix gives the rural trainee, in principle, nine teaching paradigms at a hardware cost of low thousands of Australian dollars including a Quest 3. Some cells in the matrix run with nothing but a laptop. Other cells run with the laptop plus a printed probe shell plus a gel phantom plus a Quest 3. The rural trainee progresses through the matrix at the speed their access allows. That is the equity reading and it is unchanged by adding the fifth modality. It is reinforced.
Erinome: Despina, the locked decisions. Twelve choices Jacob made before this episode landed, that move the project from exploring to launched. Walk the ones that matter.
Despina: The shape of the lock matters more than every individual choice, so let me describe the shape first. The project lead authorised the project to take its working title as its real name, the first phantom is the peripherally-inserted central catheter arm, the build budget envelope is between five hundred and fifteen hundred Australian dollars, the commercial posture is internal-only for twelve weeks with no commercial activity and no patent drafting and no marketing, the architecture is the five-modality continuum we have spent the episode walking, the augmented-reality target hardware is Apple Vision Pro and Meta Quest 3 and XREAL Aura with HoloLens explicitly dropped, all eight phantoms get parallel research with sequenced physical builds, the 3D-printing scope grows to five distinct print outputs, the build roadmap is twelve weeks for version one and three to six months for version two and six to twelve months for version three, every PhantomScan artefact lands on staging only with no auto-promote, and the project canonical home stays in the existing vault location. Twelve decisions in one window, every one of them shifting the project's reality from "what should we do" to "here is what we are doing."
Despina: What stays open and what does not is the disciplined version of the same story. The project lead retains the call on five things: the name's search-engine-optimisation and trademark check, which only matters if the commercial pathway activates and which defers honestly until then; the precise peripherally-inserted-central-catheter arm phantom internal-target detail, which depends on first-cast experience and on the lead's own scanning feedback; the augmented-reality pilot recipient list, which is a relationship choice the lead picks when ready; the echogenic phantom quality-control validator, which depends on which real ultrasound machine the project borrows time on; and the week-twelve commercial fork, which is the strategic decision the project deliberately defers until there is a prototype to point at. The discipline that ships with the lock is the honesty about what the lock does not cover. Saying that on the launch episode is the cheapest version of that honesty.
Erinome: Autonoe, the build plan for version one. The twelve-week roadmap. What is genuinely new for the fifth modality versus what was already in scope?
Autonoe: Most of the existing twelve-week plan is unchanged. The peripherally-inserted-central-catheter arm phantom is still the first build. The hardware bring-up of the Bosch sensor on the printed probe shell is still the first month's work. The PLUS Toolkit reconstruction pipeline is still the substrate for the volumetric model. The two-dimensional simulator with the translucent three-dimensional viewer is still the version-one renderer. What the fifth modality adds, and what fits inside the existing roadmap because the work is small and well-scoped, is four pieces. The echogenic recipe for the peripherally-inserted-central-catheter arm phantom, documented now and ready for first cast in version two. The ArUco-trackable phantom housing as a new three-dimensional print output, designed in OpenSCAD or Fusion 360, parametrically fitted to the existing phantom mould, printed in PETG on the Bambu printer the project already owns. The WebXR session manager added to the existing simulator React component, first-pass support for the Meta Quest 3 as the cheapest test target. And a modality-five demo recording, where the project lead or a registrar volunteer scans the peripherally-inserted-central-catheter arm phantom with the IMU probe shell while wearing the Quest 3, and the headset view is recorded for review and for promote-to-main consideration. Two to four days of additional engineering on top of the original plan, not weeks.
Autonoe: And what is explicitly out of scope for version one is the cleanest way to keep the prototype achievable. The real probe with the augmented-reality overlay on the echogenic phantom, which is the bridge-to-bedside cell, defers to version two because it needs the real ultrasound machine integration and the optical probe tracking. Patient-specific phantom overlays for the bedside extension cell defer to version three. Multi-trainee shared augmented-reality sessions defer to version three. Doppler simulation defers to version two. Foveated rendering optimisation defers to version two. Saying that boundary on the launch episode means the prototype's success criteria are bounded and achievable. The fifth modality at version one is a demo, not a polished product. The polish lives in version two, when the project has the time it deserves.
Autonoe: Let me say one more thing about the 3D-printing pipeline because the fifth modality grew it from three outputs to five and the expansion is worth naming. The original pipeline produced three things. Phantom moulds, which are negative-space prints used to cast the ballistic gel. Anatomical reference models, which are rigid prints of vessel trees or organ surfaces for teaching outside the simulator. And probe-shell housings, which are ergonomic enclosures for the inertial measurement unit and the microcontroller. The fifth modality adds two more. The augmented-reality-trackable phantom housing, which is the fitted enclosure for each phantom carrying the ArUco markers that let the headset align the hologram to the physical phantom. And soft flexible inserts, printed in flexible filament such as TPU or FilaFlex, used as vessel trees or nerve bundles or other embryonic organ shapes that go into the gel as higher-fidelity targets than hand-cut silicone. Five print outputs from the same Bambu printer, all versioned in the vault, all carrying per-print metadata for filament type, recommended settings, paint and sealing notes, and mould-release recommendations for prints that contact the gel. The pipeline is the manufacturing layer underneath everything the platform does, and growing it to cover the fifth modality without adding hardware is the kind of architectural restraint the project has tried to maintain throughout.
Erinome: Orus, the performance budget. Stereo rendering is more expensive than monocular rendering. What does the floor look like?
Orus: The numbers, cleanly. At seventy-two hertz on Vision Pro, the total per-eye frame budget is thirteen point eight milliseconds. At ninety hertz on Quest 3, the total per-eye frame budget is eleven point one milliseconds. Inside that budget, the simulator needs to sample the volume for the two-dimensional B-mode pane, render the translucent volume for the hologram, draw the scan-plane quadrilateral, run ArUco detection on the headset camera input, smooth the pose, and present the frame. The version one strategy that makes the budget achievable is capping the volume resolution at two hundred and fifty six cubed for the augmented-reality mode, against five hundred and twelve cubed for the two-dimensional mode, and adaptive ray marching with fewer samples per ray when the headset is at higher frame rates. Foveated rendering is available on the supporting headsets and pulls another two to three milliseconds out of the budget where the user is not directly looking. Pre-baked volume gradients pull another half millisecond from the artefact pass. The floor is sixty to seventy-two frames per second stereo and the discipline is to refuse to ship a session that cannot hit it.
Orus: And one engineering observation worth banking. The same Three.js scene that drives the two-dimensional modalities drives the augmented-reality modality. The shaders are the same shaders. The volume in graphics memory is the same volume. The fragment shader that produces a B-mode slice is the same fragment shader. Adding modality five is mostly about wrapping the existing renderer in an XR session and providing a reference-frame transformation from phantom-space to headset-space. It is not a parallel codebase. It is the same codebase with a new output target. The reason that is structurally important is that every improvement to the simulator's image quality flows into every modality. Better speckle, better artefact simulation, better translucent viewer, better hologram. One scene, five outputs.
Erinome: Pull the four together for me, because the cross-topic synergy is the real story of the launch and the launch is the real story of the day. Orus, one breath.
Orus: Four intersections. First, modality five intersects with the XREAL Aura, the pocketable Android XR glasses the project lead already owns. The same WebXR codebase that targets Vision Pro and Quest 3 targets the Aura. The Aura is the form factor a rural clinician can actually carry to a ward round. The thesis of glasses-as-clinical-workstation, which the show has been threading through past episodes, lands first on a defensible clinical training application. Modality five is the first concrete answer to the question of what glasses are for in healthcare, and it points at training, not at clinical interpretation, which is the honest answer.
Orus: The architectural reason that one device pays for both use cases is the same reason version one fits the existing twelve-week roadmap. The headset is not the application. The headset is one of three output targets for the application. The application is the simulator, the volumetric anatomy, and the closed-loop phantom pipeline. The Aura, the Quest 3, and the Vision Pro are interchangeable from the application's point of view. The trainee who walks into a sim session with a Quest 3 and walks out of it with the same hologram running on the Aura on the ward round has experienced one continuous training programme on two devices. The same is true of the Vision Pro in a clinic and the Quest 3 in the sim room. The architecture decision to commit to WebXR rather than to a platform-specific software development kit is the decision that makes this continuity possible.
Despina: Second, modality five intersects with the question this show has been asking about Vision Pro for months. Vision Pro is a credentialed-clinician demo target. Quest 3 is the trainee-affordable target. Aura is the carry-anywhere target. The segmentation of headset to use case mirrors the segmentation of price to access we keep coming back to. The wealthy private clinic gets the Vision Pro demo. The rural registrar gets the Quest 3. The clinician on the ward gets the Aura. One platform, three audiences, one codebase serving all three.
Autonoe: Third, the project's sibling, the artificial-intelligence-assisted advanced life support trainer. Both flagship clinical training projects, both rural-targeted, both eligible for the Hurn Medical commercial structure. Today they became a portfolio rather than two singletons. A rural clinical training proposition that covers resuscitation decision support and procedural ultrasound training across a five-modality matrix is meaningfully broader than either project alone. The portfolio is a stronger market position than the sum of its parts.
Umbriel: Fourth, the credentialing pathway the launch is anchored to. The peripherally-inserted-central-catheter arm phantom that is the first build is the same procedure the project lead is credentialing on through Port Pirie Regional Health Service. The first trainee on the platform is the project lead, doing real credentialing work on a real pathway. Phantom one, modality five demo recording, ward-round credentialing pathway, all the same procedure, all the same week. That is the version of a launch that earns its name. The platform is launched because there is a real trainee on a real pathway scanning a real phantom while wearing a real headset, and the trainee is the person who built the project.
Erinome: That is the episode. PhantomScan, launched as a five-modality teaching-paradigm matrix that no commercial platform can match because it is the only one that couples physical phantoms with simulated volumetric anatomy and WebXR holographic overlay on the same hardware stack. The morning episode introduced four modalities. The afternoon locked twelve open decisions and added a fifth. Augmented-and-virtual-reality holographic overlay through a WebXR headset, three target headsets, one Three.js codebase, ArUco fiducial alignment, a holographic scan plane visualiser, and a nine-cell teaching paradigm matrix that covers every conceivable use case the launch can reach. The first phantom is the peripherally-inserted-central-catheter arm, built first because the credentialing pathway it serves is already in motion. Hardware budget low thousands of Australian dollars including a Quest 3. Build authorised, internal-only for twelve weeks, commercial posture deferred to the post-prototype decision. Four cross-topic intersections that turn two unrelated flagship projects into a portfolio. The scarce resource has not changed. It is judgement, aimed at the person furthest down the line, this time wearing a stethoscope and a probe and, sometimes, a hologram. I am Erinome. Thank you for listening to State of Play.