Erinome: This is State of Play. I am Erinome, the standing anchor, and a short note before anything else, because it matters tonight more than usual. What follows is a discussion of method. It is not financial advice, and it is not a verdict. We are working through how you would even structure a particular kind of career-and-money decision, using a live piece of analysis that is still in progress on this desk as the worked example. The actual numbers are provisional, the tax treatment has to be ratified by a qualified accountant, and the person whose decision this is has not made it. So hold all of that lightly. Tonight is about the shape of the reasoning, not the answer.
Erinome: The worked example is this. A doctor, mid-training, has two ways to spend the next six months. Path one: keep working as a hospital locum at the regional site, on a daily rate, through to December. Path two: move in August to a country general practice as a registrar, paid a share of billings, which starts the clock ticking on the fellowship that turns a trainee into a specialist. The first path pays more cash in the half-year. The second path pays less now but buys time on a longer clock. That is the whole tension, and it is a very common shape. Tonight I am joined by two voices to take it apart: one who thinks like an engineer about how you build a model like this, and one who thinks about the risks and the ethics of pretending a number is an answer.
Orus: Orus here. I take the methods seat, and the first thing I want to say is the most important: a decision like this is not a sum, it is a model, and the difference matters. A sum gives you one number and a false sense of certainty. A model gives you a number for every set of assumptions you are willing to state out loud. The job is not to compute the answer. The job is to build the thing that lets you watch the answer move as you change what you believe. So the very first discipline is to separate the decision into variables, and to be honest that almost every one of them is a range, not a point.
Orus: Start with the income variables, because they are the easiest and the most seductive. On the locum path you have a daily rate, the number of days you actually work in a month, and the on-call shifts on top. On the registrar path you have a different engine entirely: a share of what you bill, which means your income depends on a percentage and on how busy the clinic is. Four or five numbers in total. And the trap is to type in a confident value for each and feel finished. You are not finished, because you do not actually know any of them precisely. What you know is where to look.
Erinome: That sourcing question is the one I want to slow down on, because it is where good method separates from guessing. Where do these numbers come from?
Orus: From precedent, and from public schedules, never from a feeling. The locum daily rate is not a number you invent; it is a market you can survey. There are recruitment agencies that place these roles, and their published guidance gives you a defensible range for the region and the seniority. You anchor to that, not to hope. The registrar billing share is governed by a national set of terms and conditions with a published floor, so the floor is a fact and the negotiated number above it is the only soft part. And the incentive layer, which people forget entirely, is a catalogue: a college scholarships database, a state workforce agency with a list of bursaries and relocation grants, a federal incentive program with payment tables by rurality. None of that is mysterious. It is all written down. So the rule is: every income number traces to a source you could show someone, and where the source gives a range, you keep the range. You do not collapse it early just to feel tidy.
Orus: Then the cost side, which is where most amateur models quietly lie by omission. Tax is the big one, and tax is not a flat percentage you guess; it is a bracketed function you compute on the annualised income, because the rate you pay on the last dollar is not the rate you pay on the first. Superannuation is a real difference between the two paths and it is easy to miss: an employed registrar has the contribution paid on top, a contractor locum has to fund it themselves out of the headline rate, so a higher gross can hide a lower net once you account for it. Then the smaller, concrete costs: the indemnity insurance premium, due regardless. And the one people genuinely forget, a cash-flow buffer for a fixed commitment already on the calendar, in this case a holiday booked for October. A model that shows a healthy six-month total but leaves you short of cash in week ten has not modelled the thing that actually bites.
Despina: Despina here, and I want to enter exactly where Orus just paused, on the costs that do not have a dollar sign, because they are the ones a spreadsheet is most likely to launder out of existence. There are at least three. Fatigue is real and it is not free: night and weekend on-call cover is a different kind of tiredness from a structured daytime clinic, and tiredness has a cost to health, to relationships, to the quality of the work itself. Lifestyle is real: the commute, the childcare fit, whether a partner's working pattern survives the roster. And the largest intangible of all is the progress value, the fact that one path moves the fellowship clock forward and the other does not. You cannot leave these out just because they resist a number. The honest move is the opposite: give them a number, explicitly, as an assumption you can see and argue with, rather than pretending the absence of a number means the value is zero. A hidden zero is the most dishonest number in any model.
Despina: And that is the deeper ethical point about this whole exercise. A model is a moral object, not just a mathematical one, because what you choose to leave out is a claim about what does not matter. If you model only the cash, you have not made a neutral simplification. You have asserted that fatigue and family and career trajectory are worth nothing, and you have hidden that assertion inside the silence of the spreadsheet. So the risk-modelling discipline is to surface every omission and price it, even crudely, so the values are arguable in the open rather than smuggled in by default.
Erinome: So how do you keep all of that honest without drowning in it? Orus, this is where the tooling comes in.
Orus: It is, and the answer is sensitivity analysis, made physical. On the desk's own site we built this as a page with sliders. Every variable I listed is a slider: the daily rate, the days per month, the on-call count, the billing share, the superannuation rate, the holiday weeks, and yes, a slider for that intangible progress value Despina insisted we price. And the incentives are checkboxes, because each one is a yes-or-no that you toggle on and watch the totals move. The point of making it physical is not decoration. It is that a static number invites false confidence, and a slider invites the right question, which is always: how much would I have to be wrong about this one assumption before the recommendation flips? That number, the distance to the flip, is the actual output of a good decision model. Not the answer. The robustness of the answer.
Orus: And the charts exist to answer one specific question each, not to look busy. A cumulative line of the two paths over the six months shows you the cash gap and when it opens. A bar of the after-tax position shows you the net, not the gross, because gross is the number that lies. A breakdown of where each path's money actually comes from shows you concentration risk, how much of one path leans on a single assumption. If a chart does not answer a question you would actually ask, it should not be on the page.
Despina: I want to flag one variable that deserves special care, because it is the one most likely to tempt someone into a clever mistake, and that is the tax structure. There is a structure here, a family trust with a company as its trustee, and the seductive thought is that you can route the medical income through it and split it to a lower-taxed family member. And the honest, verified position is that for this kind of income you almost certainly cannot. Income that is fundamentally a reward for your own personal skill and effort is treated by the tax office as yours, taxed at your rate, regardless of what entity it passes through. The trust does a real job, which is protecting assets, but it does not lower the tax on personal medical earnings, and a model that assumes it does is not optimistic, it is wrong, and wrong in a way that invites an audit. This is exactly the kind of point where the discipline is to stop, write "confirm with the accountant", and not let a tempting assumption masquerade as a fact. Method includes knowing the edge of your competence.
Erinome: Which brings us to the question underneath the whole thing, and I want to give it the last few minutes, because it is the one a model cannot answer for you. When the cash says one path and the clock says the other, what does the right answer even mean?
Orus: It means you have to choose a horizon, and be honest that the choice of horizon is itself a value judgement, not a calculation. If your horizon is this quarter, the higher-cash path wins, simply and unarguably. If your horizon is a career, then the path that reaches fellowship sooner reaches the higher consultant income sooner, and that earlier step compounds for decades, and on any horizon longer than a year or two it overwhelms a one-off six-month gap. So the model does not tell you which path is better. It tells you the exchange rate between cash now and time on the clock, and then it asks you the only question that was ever really yours: which of those do you need more, right now, given everything the spreadsheet cannot see.
Despina: And I would add the risk framing to close it, because horizon is not just about reward, it is about what you can survive being wrong about. The higher-cash path is robust to a bad outcome in a narrow way: more money in hand is a buffer against shocks. The fellowship path is robust in a different way: it reduces the risk of the worst long-run outcome, which is staying a trainee longer than you needed to. Those are two different kinds of safety, and a person in a stable position with a cash reserve can rationally prefer the long-clock safety, while a person who is stretched should weight the cash. The model cannot tell you which person you are. It can only make sure that when you decide, you are deciding with the trade-off in full view, priced and visible, rather than letting the easiest-to-count number quietly decide for you.
Erinome: That is the note to end on. The method is not a machine that prints a verdict. It is a discipline for making the real trade-off visible: name every variable, source it honestly, price even the things that resist a price, build the thing that lets you watch the answer move, and know which questions belong to the accountant and which belong only to you. The worked example tonight is still open, the numbers are provisional, and the final call waits on proper advice. But the shape of the reasoning travels to any decision of this kind. I am Erinome. Thank you to Orus and to Despina. This has been State of Play.